Chapter 0: Prologue

Disclaimer: Yes, yes, obviously I didn't invent these characters, yadda yadda.

o-o-o-o-o

Prologue

October 31, 1981

The view out the window was dark. The new moon had come a few days before, and only a sliver of white showed in the sky. There were no electric lights to be seen either - the window looked out onto a small rear yard, sheltered from streetlights and traffic by enclosing buildings and fences.

But the small room inside was warmly lit by a fire, and a pair of side-table lamps on either side of the sofa. One lamp illuminated the pages of the spy novel being read by a young brown-haired man in corduroy slacks and a beige sweater-vest. The other shone upon the non-fiction book - 'The Mismeasure of Man', as it happened - being read by a young brunette woman in a thick beige cardigan, her legs obscured by an afghan. The firelight itself danced merrily on the pages of a thinner book, pressed open on the floor by the stubby fingers of a two-year-old girl in a white nightgown. The flickers of orange and yellow made the illustrations of rabbits in waistcoats seem almost as if they might come to life at any moment, but the girl paid them little heed, her eyes instead lingering over the crisp black letters.

Though she knew the words by heart long since - she'd read the book more than once, after all - the girl often returned to it for pleasure. It had been the first book she'd read, a few months ago, and re-reading it reminded her of that first amazing thrill when she'd realized that these marks on paper - not pictures, mind you, just black marks they called 'letters' - could somehow turn into words in her head. It was rather magical, when you thought about it.

The girl was not in costume, and no children came to the door, for the American tradition of trick-or-treating had not yet made its way across the Atlantic, and the family was not one for fancy-dress parties. Not that the girl was much given to fancy in general - her imagination was thus far firmly focused upon deciding which book she would next ask her mother to fetch down from the high shelves. Nor would children calling upon this home on later Hallowe'ens leave with much satisfaction - the man and the woman were both dentists.

At around the same time, quite some distance West, something horrible was happening (and also, if one was of a sufficiently pragmatic bent to consider it so, something miraculous). None of the residents of the house were aware of it, or even of the context in which the event was taking place. Nor would they ever have even learned of it, but for one simple fact; a few years hence, a certain quill would write the name Hermione Jean Granger - and beside it her birth date - in a certain book, in a certain room, in a certain tower, in a certain castle, the very existence of any of which both she and her parents would have been equally unlikely to suspect at all.

But then, look closely enough at anything important and you're bound to find a book in there somewhere, aren't you?

o-o-o-o-o

A/N: If I'm interpreting the viewer stats correctly, more than 50% of people apparently drop the fic in disgust/disinterest after reading solely this Prologue. If you're about to join them, are you sure it wouldn't be worth reading an actual chapter, just in case?

Chapter 1: Statistical Sampling

Chapter 1 - Statistical Sampling

Hermione Granger was not like other girls her age. That much could be clearly illustrated - and had been - via simple bell curve charts based on surveys she'd given to her classmates. She'd asked how many books they'd read in the past year, how many books on average they read per week, and so on. In every relevant category, the dot that represented Hermione was sitting by itself off on the right side of the paper (except the chart showing school absences, where she was on the left, instead).

It was just as clearly (if more symbolically) illustrated in noting how few other girls had administered surveys, and that no one else at all had calculated the standard deviations. But that was something Hermione had learned early on.

At first, whenever she had a question, the path to answering it was simple - ask an adult, or find the right book. But she'd eventually discovered that there were some questions that weren't answered in books. Usually, because the question wasn't important enough that anyone else had asked it, or it was very specific. So she stepped back to the problem of question-answering in general, and there were a great many books about that. They were so interesting, in fact, that she couldn't remember what question she'd wanted to answer in the first place when she'd come up for air a week or so later.

But now she had some tools for figuring such things out, even if other people seemed to use them even less than they used books. Of course, these tools had their own difficulties at times. Take statistical sampling, for example. You needed a large enough pool of examples before you could be at all confident about any patterns you thought you saw. That began to become troublesome when Hermione's classmates started answering her surveys unhelpfully, or even untruthfully. They seemed to think it was funny (and based on the proportion of students who laughed, objectively it probably was funny, even if it didn't seem like it to her).

There were questions that were hard to pin down for other reasons, though. She'd begun to notice...odd things. Coincidences, you could call them, taken individually. Sometimes when she was particularly excited to look something up, the book she wanted seemed to leap off the shelf into her hand before she'd really pulled on it at all. The time she'd been having trouble tuning out other students' chattering at school while she read, then suddenly gone deaf for half the day. The horrifying occasion when she'd accidentally torn the page of a library book - or thought she had - but when she looked at it again, the page was quite unblemished.

How could you account for that, though? Unlikely things didn't happen very often taken in isolation, but collect a few million people and have them do a few dozen things every day, and they happened to everyone, all the time. Just because Hermione seemed to notice more pleasant coincidences than not didn't mean that formed a real pattern. The idea of 'luck' was just a combination of superstition and people not understanding probability.

Besides, for every minor thing she might call mildly lucky, there were other examples of misfortune. Her front teeth, for example, protruded a bit. When other children had teased her about them, she'd done her best to ignore it, but she'd also naturally looked at a few books, and it seemed like something easily fixed with orthodontia. Yet when she'd brought it up to her parents - who were dentists, after all - she got nowhere. They seemed to think orthodontists were stuck-up and unjustly full of themselves and were thus quite against employing them for any reason.

Still, the question of these coincidences remained, tucked in the back of her head along with a few other open mysteries, like what caused differences in individual preferences (specifically, why so few other students ever cared to raise their hands in class), or why it was so hard for her to make friends. Things she kept lightly in mind, just in case she happened to read some odd fact or theory that might clear everything up.

One summer afternoon in 1991, after receiving a certain Letter, she did in fact read something that purported to clear everything up. However, considering it did so by suggesting that nearly a third of everything else Hermione had ever read was wrong (or at least woefully incomplete), it was rather difficult to accept at face value.

Of course, it was possible it was just a prank - she'd been on the receiving end of many over the years - though if so it had required rather more research than anyone had gone to previously. It had been addressed with peculiar specificity, down to the position of her bedroom (First Bedroom on the Left, Second Floor), which, to her knowledge, none of her classmates knew, as she'd never had occasion to invite any of them over. But it would not have been all that difficult to find out if someone had been properly determined.

If it was a prank, however, she didn't see what the payoff would be, seeing as the letter had advised her to expect a school representative to arrive at her home in three days to 'explain the situation more fully' to her and her parents. If it had said she was to post a ten pound note 'for registration' or to go to some remote location where pranksters might show up and pelt her with toads or something similarly imaginative, that might have made more sense. But surely no prankster would be eager to face Mr. and Mrs. Granger, who were no-nonsense sort of people, and likely to give short shrift to any such shenanigans, particularly at their own home?

She'd have just asked her parents, but they were still at work, and the Letter gnawed at her, so naturally, she walked to the local library. After a couple hours of very interesting reading (primarily in the New Age and History sections), she'd decided that believing in things that didn't provide much helpful evidence was probably an effective way of practicing creativity, as the latter gave a strong showing in books on 'practical magic' while the former was seemingly absent. Nor was there any hint of the existence of any school called 'Hogwarts', past or present.

Two hours in a library might have exhausted the patience, curiosity (or likely, both) of an average eleven-year-old, but Hermione had been gifted with perseverance to match her intelligence, and she was not nearly inclined to give up yet - though unfortunately she didn't have much time before her parents were due home for dinner. Accordingly, she went to the reference desk and got the telephone numbers for every government agency she thought might be relevant to a school for magic, then walked home.

Chapter 3: Needful Things

Chapter 3 - Needful Things

The trip into London was uneventful. Hermione's parents spent most of the time contrasting their brief visit with Professor McGonagall to Professor Flitwick's visit, with a lot of comments on how normal Professor McGonagall had seemed, aside from vanishing from their foyer before their eyes, of course. Hermione kept to herself, going over the encounter in her memory.

Professor McGonagall had seemed very...professorial. Not like Professor Flitwick, who'd been quite social and gone to considerable lengths to put everyone at ease. She was also obviously surprised to hear he'd visited them, which made Hermione curious. Clearly he hadn't mentioned it to her - maybe they just hadn't run into each other? But then why had she sounded so...put out about it? Hermione resolved to pay close attention to interactions between the Professors. It wouldn't do to get on anyone's bad side before even turning in a single assignment!

But that vanishing trick seemed quite useful, rather more so than turning an entire room colors, no matter how proud Professor Flitwick had seemed to be of the accomplishment. Hermione made another note to keep an eye out for that while reading her books, something she was frankly itching to begin. The past couple days waiting had been almost torture - Professor Flitwick had said there was probably no point in reading the Wicca and other 'magic' books at her library, which left her with little she could do to prepare.

She'd memorized the Letter, of course, including the list of books, equipment and supplies she would need. And after hearing the Professor's explanations about 'Accidental Magic', she went over all her memories of the odd 'lucky' experiences she'd had over the years, writing them down in as much detail as she could remember and going over common features. It seemed clear that emotion was a frequent contributor, if not necessarily intent. But need had been an element of almost all of them, and that made her wonder a bit about her priorities, but only for a moment. Books were important, after all. But she hadn't tried to do any more Accidental Magic on purpose, partially since the very concept was rather contradictory, but more because of Professor Flitwick's intimations that though it rarely caused lasting or irreversible harm, Accidental Magic could on occasion be dangerous.

So instead she'd resorted to one of her problem-solving techniques, which told her that if she couldn't do anything productive at one level of the problem, to move up or down a level and try again. She'd seen for herself that precise wand motions were important, so she'd checked out a few books on increasing her manual dexterity, and had spent several hours working through both juggling and sleight of hand exercises. From what Professor Flitwick had said, spellbooks weren't referred to in practical situations, spells were meant to be entirely memorized, so she re-read her books on mnemonics as well.

But finally the day had arrived, they were here, and they were approaching number 113. Hermione felt as if her eyes were sponges, ready to soak in every detail and file it away for proper consideration.

The Leaky Cauldron was, accordingly, something of a disappointment.

"A pub?" said Hermione with mild incredulity. Little more than a small window and a door, hardly noticeable between the large and busy shops on either side of it. But then, Witches did apparently have that concern about secrecy, so she supposed they'd want it to be easily missed. Her parents, however, were scrutinizing the pocket street map they'd brought, looking back and forth between the bookshop and record store.

"Maybe it's one of those out-of-sequence places, further up or down a ways?" mused Mr Granger. Hermione, perplexed, cleared her throat, glancing at the pub's entrance.

"Not by the listings...not that there was a listing for this place anyway," observed Hermione's mother.

"Um," said Hermione.

"She really ought to have given us landmarks if it was going to be trouble to find," complained her father.

"Hey!" Hermione interrupted, raising her voice a bit. Her parents turned to her, looking surprised and a bit irritated. "I'm sorry," said the girl, "but it's right there," she explained, pointing. The couple looked at the bookshop, then the record store, then their daughter. Their eyes didn't even slow as they passed over the door of the pub. Admittedly, it was extremely dingy, but it's not like it was hidden. Unless...secrecy…?

"Take my hands," she said suddenly, reaching an arm up towards each of her parents. For a moment it seemed they would object, but they looked at each other, then did as she asked.

Their mouths fell open.

"I guess that means you can see it now?" asked Hermione excitedly. "Let's go, then!" She tugged them forward, and her father opened the door to the pub with his free hand, staring in wonderment. As the three entered the darkened interior, they saw Professor McGonagall stopping short in front of them, looking quite different - the drab flower print had been replaced with an elaborate pointed hat and a sort of formal robes in emerald green.

"I was just coming out to explain how to resolve the protections against muggles noticing the Leaky Cauldron, but I see Miss Granger has worked that out on her own," she said, sounding mildly impressed. "Well, it's done at any rate, so shall we get started?" The Professor spun and led them through the pub towards the back, the hem of her robes waving gently with the vigor of her stride, and somehow looking much more natural than the very normal dress she'd been wearing before.

The other denizens of the Leaky Cauldron wore a collection of equally unusual garments, and glanced with mild interest at the Grangers as they passed. Hermione's parents seemed freshly intimidated by the suddenly-appearing pub door and the mild strangeness inside and stared fixedly at the Professor's back, while Hermione instead tried to look around in every direction at once, lingering on the chalkboard listing drinks and dishes on offer (Butterbeer - two sickles, Gillywater - three sickles, Vagabond's Pillow - five sickles, eleven knuts), as well as the sole book visible - being read by a young man in the corner, it was titled 'Creatures of the Far East and Which Parts of You They Find Delicious'. But before she could really begin to puzzle out the illustration on the back, they were already through, and into a cramped courtyard.

It had the look of exactly the sort of place - had this actually been an elaborate ruse - where a couple of toughs would've emerged from the shadows and demanded all of the Grangers' money and valuables. But before Hermione's parents had time to form such thoughts, McGonagall had withdrawn her wand from her robes and smartly tapped a particular brick in the courtyard wall three times. There was an eye-twisting rearrangement of the bricks into an archway, beyond which was a bustle of color and activity. The Professor urged them through, then followed herself, the archway shifting back into a solid wall as quickly as it had formed.

Diagon Alley was impossible in several ways. First, it clearly couldn't fit where it was situated, at least not if Hermione's parents' street map was at all accurate. Second, many of the buildings looked as if not only building codes but indeed fundamental principles of load and balance were not so much laws as polite suggestions, easily worked around if you were in a hurry. And Third...it was too much. Her parents might've been rooted to the spot if they hadn't feared losing Professor McGonagall in the busy streets. Whereas every direction Hermione looked revealed at least a dozen things she didn't understand and would dearly like to have had explained to her (or have her guesses confirmed), except half of them would be gone when she glanced back and every step they took brought another dozen into view.

In desperation, Hermione focused on just memorizing the names and locations of each shop they passed, with a few examples of what seemed to be on display in the windows - and giving special attention towards any that seemed to sell books, of course.

The Professor's businesslike pace brought them quickly within sight of Gringotts, whose bright and straightforward architecture quite clearly stated 'I am a Bank. I am sturdy and reliable - indeed impregnable - and none of that haphazard tilting nonsense will be brooked here, thank you kindly.' The very normalcy of it - even if the bronze doors were a bit ostentatious - helped the elder Grangers relax a bit.

"Some muggles are taken aback at discovering that Gringotts is a goblin-run bank," said Professor McGonagall suddenly as they approached. "A few have even screamed upon seeing their first goblin, though you seem more open-minded than that sort," she added with elaborate casualness, aiming a friendly glance towards Hermione's parents. Hermione wasn't sure she'd ever heard anyone refer to her parents as open-minded, but having heard themselves suggested as such, they'd no doubt be doing their best to live up to that expectation. Just in time, too, as there was in fact a goblin standing guard outside the bank. Mr. and Mrs. Granger nodded politely to him, trying not to let their eyes widen, while Hermione examined him as closely as she could without actually staring, and added another fifty or so questions to her mental list of things she needed to know immediately or sooner.

The Professor coached Mr. Granger through the relatively simple money-changing transaction. He had to do it himself, as the goblins took fiduciary responsibility very seriously, and would not allow the Professor to act as an intermediary without a lot of tedious documentation - which they would also have charged various fees to witness and certify. Mostly she stressed that he should not count the coins as he received them. Hermione's father actually seemed a bit more nervous due to all of the fuss, but managed to get through without incident. He'd apparently taken the Professor's advice about excess to heart, as he'd given the teller around three hundred pounds, and received three sizeable bags of coin in return. After leaving Gringotts, the family examined some of the coins curiously while Professor McGonagall explained the coins' relative values.

"They're so light, but solid," remarked Mrs. Granger, hefting a couple of Galleons in her palm. "Gold is at two-eleven per troy, isn't it, dear-" she glanced at her husband, who nodded, "so at five pounds to the Galleon there can't be much more than a third of an ounce of gold in each coin. What's the rest?" Dentists had to buy metals for fillings regularly, and she seemed relieved to have something familiar to discuss for a moment.

"Magic," said Professor McGonagall, with a prim smile. "As I understand it, the minting process makes counterfeiting quite difficult while also enhancing durability, though goblins are quite reluctant to discuss the details of their metal-magics with outsiders." Mrs. Granger's brief comfort slipped visibly from her face. Hermione was still thinking it over, however.

"What do the goblins do with the normal...ah, muggle money they get?", she asked. Without people on each side frequently buying things from those on the other, she wasn't sure her mother's assumptions about the exchange rates made sense. Professor McGonagall frowned, then shrugged.

"I'm sure I do not know...I suppose they keep it on hand for customers who need exchanges in the other direction?" She seemed about to say something else, but visibly changed her mind. "Best get you to Madam Malkin for a fitting first, then we can complete the rest of your shopping while she's preparing your uniforms and pick them up after." The tall woman strode away, leaving the Grangers to scramble in her wake to catch up. Hermione's mental list was getting rather long, and she resolved to write it down as soon as she had a pen and paper.

The fitting went smoothly, though Professor McGonagall waited outside with Hermione's parents so she had no chance to ask any useful questions - Madam Malkin was extremely focused on her task, which Hermione found commendable in general but a bit irritating in this particular circumstance. She began to worry that Professor McGonagall's efficiency would be equally inconvenient, not allowing her any time to explore more than the bare minimum, and used the remainder of her fitting to work out a solution to that problem. Outside the shop, she tried to put it into practice.

"Um, I was thinking, rather than visiting each shop in turn, maybe we could split up? The larger book shop - Flourish and Blotts, was it? - looked rather busy. I could go there and get all the books...I mean, well, not all the books-" she laughed nervously, "but the ones on the list, plus you know, if I saw one or two other interesting ones...while you three went around for the other things?" It really was a good idea - the fact that it'd let her have as much time as possible to peruse the book stores was just a happy bonus, wasn't it?

Her parents were accustomed to this sort of negotiation, and chuckled. They didn't have a problem with it, but checked with Professor McGonagall. The older witch shook her head ruefully and muttered something Hermione didn't catch, though it sounded like it ended with '-claws', but also didn't see a problem with it, as long as Hermione stayed in the shops on Diagon Alley proper, taking - and she stressed this - no side streets. Hermione cheerfully agreed to this condition, though of course she had to ask why. The Professor did that eyebrow thing she did for a moment, then admitted that the street connected to other areas, 'less appropriate for children'. Whereupon her parents reconsidered their earlier agreement, and Hermione had to convince them she was entirely responsible and only wanted to look in bookstores, and she'd done the same thing in the City before, and it's not as if there weren't some unpleasant parts of London…

In the end, they gave in. She was very, very responsible for a girl her age, after all.

o-o-o

A couple hours later, the little fellowship had reformed, quite a few galleons lighter but along with the other items and supplies, over a dozen books heavier. Even Hermione's parents hadn't been able to resist picking something up from one of the book shops they'd checked before locating their daughter - 'So, Your Daughter's a Witch: A Guide to Magical Adolescence'. It wasn't written with muggles in mind particularly, but it didn't seem to be aimed at a particularly intelligent audience so they figured they could puzzle things out from context. All that remained now was to buy Hermione's wand, so Professor McGonagall led the way to Ollivanders Wand Shop. The sign read 'Makers of Fine Wands since 382 B.C.', and Hermione scratched another question onto her list with the self-inking quill she'd since acquired.

"We shall wait outside for you, Miss Granger," declared Professor McGonagall.

"Oh...is wand-buying a private process?" asked Hermione, fascinated. McGonagall pursed her lips.

"Personal, certainly, but not particularly private - it's just that it can occasionally take time and it would be quite cramped inside for four." Hermione was somewhat nonplussed by the answer, but nodded. She collected a handful of galleons from her parents, then entered the shop.

She could see immediately what McGonagall meant - the shop was narrow to begin with, and tightened further by shelves of long narrow boxes covering every available inch of the walls. No one was immediately visible, but the door caused a bell to ring somewhere in the rear of the shop. She studied the boxes while she waited. Few of them were labeled in any way, unless the color of the box was some sort of code. Though many of the boxes were so coated in dust the color wasn't even immediately apparent. Hermione wondered why they would keep so much unsold inventory in a shop so small. With wands a seemingly central part of magical life, she'd have expected it to be much more like an electronics store showroom, with various models displayed prominently - as other shops had in fact displayed broomsticks, come to think of it.

"It's a problem of selection, you see," issued a soft voice behind her. Hermione whirled around with a startled 'eep'. She stopped as she came to face a white-haired old man who was watching her quietly. There was something odd about his eyes.

"Sorry?" Hermione asked when she'd regained her composure, not sure if the man had been literally answering her thoughts, but not ruling it out either. He waved a hand lazily at the shelves surrounding them.

"Selection. But in reverse - 'the Wand chooses the Wizard', as goes the saying. Or Witch, of course, but it's a very old saying, you know," he elaborated, apologetically. "Wands do not think, not truly. But they can mirror our emotions in many ways. They feel. A wand is an extension of your personal essence, and the ideal wand is matched to that essence as closely as possible." Hermione drank in the words greedily. This was clearly someone who knew things worth hearing.

"So you need to keep a disproportionately wide variety of wands on hand, since you never know what will be needed until someone walks in?" she confirmed.

"Just so," said the man, his eyes twinkling. They were not just light grey, but actually silver. Hermione wondered if he had non-human ancestry, like Professor Flitwick, or if sliver eyes were just a natural variation for wizards.

"Garrick Ollivander," said the man, introducing himself. "And your name, young lady?"

"Hermione Granger," she said, after offering her hand politely. At her name, the man stiffened slightly in the act of shaking her hand.

"Just so," he whispered, in a strange echo of himself. For a moment he just stared at her, until Hermione began to shift uncomfortably, and he seemed to shake himself out of a daze. "Muggle-born, I see," he noted, glancing down at her clothes, "I suppose you've no hint of your ancestry...magical, that is?" Hermione shrugged.

"If anyone in our family has known about magic, they certainly never mentioned it to us - we were all quite surprised - though it sounds like they would've been expected to keep it to themselves?" The old man nodded, then began to peruse the shelves, muttering to himself.

"No, no...no...I know it's here somewhere." He moved further into the shop and climbed most of the way up a ladder, craning his neck to examine more out-of-the-way boxes. "Have to try it of course, after so long…ah." The old man stretched an arm up to extract a box from a shelf near the ceiling, then clambered back down to rejoin Hermione. The box was actually itself made of wood, carved with intricate vines. He slid back the lid and withdrew a delicate-looking wand of a pale tan wood. "Muggle-born...which hand do you write with?" he asked.

"Right," said Hermione, raising that hand. Ollivander extended the wand to her, thick end first. It had been intricately carved, making it seem as if six vines had twined around each other to form the shaft. She took the wand gently, her fingertips nestling easily into the gaps in the carving, and at the man's urging motion, waved it through the air. Immediately the tip gave off white sparks, and Hermione felt a tingle up her right arm. She was thrilled and amazed, but Ollivander wasn't done yet.

"Now the left," he said, leaning forward slightly. Hermione obediently switched the wand to her left hand and waved it similarly. This time, a thin line of blue vapor trailed behind the wand's tip, swirling slightly in the air. Ollivander's eyes widened. "There it is, then," he whispered. Hermione was distracted from her pleasure at producing the trail of smoke, which was both pretty and fascinating, and gave the wandmaker a somewhat vexed look.

"Um. I have to ask, because you keep whispering like that, and you seemed to recognize my name...is there something unusual about me? Or this wand? It seems quite old, but it looked like you picked it out specifically, and Professor McGonagall said that buying a wand can sometimes take a long time, which - along with the old saying you mentioned - implies I might have to test a few out, like shoes, only this one does seem to have worked quite well on the first try, which means you expected it would work for me in particular for some reason…" Hermione rambled a bit, because she still wasn't comfortable enough with magical customs...maybe speaking in hushed tones was just a normal part of the process?...but the whole experience had been a bit weird.

Ollivander regarded her for a moment, clearly weighing his words, then nodded to himself, seeming to come to a decision, and shrugged.

"'Unusual'? I couldn't say - we are each unique in our own way, are we not? But to be sure, you are meant for that wand...among other things. You have a destiny, Hermione Granger. But I think that if you knew it in full, you might not necessarily fulfill it as naturally." His words dripped with meaning and portent, but also a sort of absent casualness (which was a trick common to wandmakers).

"I really need to know what all of that means, absolute top of the list, right now. And if this is just some sort of terribly elaborate sales pitch, I shall be very cross and ask Professor McGonagall to help me buy a wand somewhere else," said the girl, crossing her arms and attempting to sound stern, though there was a note of pleading in her demand as well. The old wandmaker shook his head and withdrew a gnarled dark wand from his robes.

"I have little doubt you will learn...everything in Time, Miss Granger. But it will not have been now, nor from me," he intoned. Hermione's brow furrowed at his choice of phrasing, but before she could complain about it, a bright flash issued from the tip of Ollivander's wand, and she was Obliviated.

For the second time that day.

o-o-o

Hermione emerged from the shop, swishing her new wand and staring wonderingly at the white sparks.

"I see your purchase went well," remarked Professor McGonagall. Hermione nodded absently, still staring at her wand.

"I had to try out almost a dozen until this one worked. Vine wood, with a dragon heartstring core, apparently? Is it always white sparks," she asked, producing another burst of them, "or does that depend on the person? I meant to ask Mr. Ollivander, but I...guess I got distracted." Her brow furrowed a little, but her train of thought was broken by Professor McGonagall's reply.

"Usually sparks, the color may vary, and please refrain for the moment, Miss Granger?" Hermione stopped swishing her wand, looking contrite. "There is a law that prohibits under-aged children from using magic outside of the auspices of appropriate magical supervision, with a few extremely limited exceptions," continued the Professor. Hermione was appalled, and her mouth fell open for a moment.

"I can't practice at home?"

A respectful but lively debate on Ministry policy ensued as they receded from the shop towards the Leaky Cauldron, their progress followed, unnoticed, by a pair of silvery eyes behind a darkened upper window.

o-o-o-o-o

A/N: Thanks for being patient with all this set-up and mysterious foreshadowing. I promise we'll actually get on the Express next chapter, and start taking canon really off the rails (see what I did there?).

A/N 2: In response to a couple of questions on reviews: No, you didn't miss something - the first obliviation isn't shown at all, it was left out for added suspense (and hopefully dramatic effect)!

Chapter 6: Unexpected

Chapter 6 - Unexpected

Hermione was eating breakfast at the Ravenclaw table with her new House-mates. When the food had appeared, the Ravenclaw table had been the only one with a full complement of first-years in attendance...apparently some of the other Houses' new students were having some difficulty in finding their way to the Great Hall. Hufflepuff was only missing one - who'd apparently wandered off - the rest having been led there by older students. The young Ravenclaws had been left to work it out on their own, but had all managed. Late first-year Gryffindors and Slytherins were still gradually trickling in, being welcomed to their tables with ribbing and derision, respectively.

As Hermione had discovered after they'd gained entrance to the Ravenclaw welcome party the night before, the large common room held a great many bookcases, comprising a private library of sorts. Many of the books were rare and some were not even found in Hogwarts' main library itself. One particularly helpful volume - Engineering Enigmas: An Evaluation of Entry and Egress in an Educational Edifice of Easy Excursion from Edinburgh - had contained a careful accounting of many of the castle's more changeable features, and various tips for navigating confidently. It took a bit of puzzling out, though, as it had been written very obliquely - apparently for some reason the author hadn't wanted to use any names or phrases that would explicitly identify Hogwarts.

The Ravenclaw 'party' itself had consisted chiefly of students oohing and aahing at the books, occasionally waving people over to share an interesting passage, and in general a lot more quiet reading than most people would expect to find at a celebration of any kind. Even the older students were involved, as the Tower Library (as it was called) was apparently updated and expanded with quite a few new books each year, over the summer holiday. Hermione had been pleasantly surprised, and had headed up to her bed only slightly later than her habitual bedtime, leaving plenty of other Ravenclaws still absorbed in the books.

She had risen early, not just because it was the prudent thing to do on her first day of classes - which it was - but also so that she might have extra time to visit the kitchens on her way to breakfast. She had not forgotten the disturbing things she'd heard the previous night, and had used what she'd read in Engineering Enigmas to gain access to the only place she was certain she'd find some house-elves, where she might get some first-hand information. After that meeting, she wasn't at all sure what to think. She'd been appalled, of course, that they were dressed only in tea-towels, and they'd confirmed that they were not paid in any way. But every one of them had stridently, indeed vehemently insisted that they were deliriously happy to be working at Hogwarts where there was so much to do and they were very rarely beaten, and had seemed quite scandalized by many of Hermione's questions. In the end, she'd decided to put the matter off until she could talk to Professor Flitwick about it. While he was in the Great Hall for breakfast, it seemed impolite to interrupt his meal for what might be a long conversation, and since she had Charms first thing, waiting until after class didn't seem like too much of a compromise in the face of injustice.

Plus, she had to eat something if she wanted to concentrate well in her morning classes, and the eggs were delicious…

"So...this is the new competition?" The voice had come from behind her right shoulder, then after the pause, switched to her left. Hermione turned, and saw two identical grinning boys with bright red hair standing behind her, their arms folded over their chests. She recognized them as Gryffindors from the sorting, the first ones who'd stuck their tongues out for Hannah. Probably third or fourth years, by their height. Their grins didn't seem malicious, but she wasn't sure they seemed entirely friendly either. "We just wanted to compliment you on your turnabout with Scabbers," said one. "Not that it took us all that long to figure it out - Ron's rubbish at most things, including looking innocent," continued the other. From this, and the hair, it wasn't hard for her to guess that they were Ron's older brothers.

"It wasn't meant to impress you," Hermione said, primly. "I just thought you might think better of tormenting your brother if you had a taste of it yourselves."

"A taste? We've older brothers as well, you know...we've had a banquet," said one of the Twins with a scoff. "And does this mean you weren't challenging us to a prank war?" asked the other, teasingly. The nearby Ravenclaws glanced at each other, listening, and Hermione looked horrified.

"A 'prank war'? Of course not...that sounds rather juvenile, and likely a horrible distraction from our studies," she said, unconsciously doing a passable McGonagall impression, albeit without her accent. The Twins looked at each other, then shrugged back at Hermione.

"Huh. I suppose we'll have to try to call off all the things we've already set up now," mused one. "Of course, we don't want to be distracted from our studies, so we might not have time to get to all of them between classes…" said the other, his seemingly contrite tone spoiled by a broad grin. Hermione's eyes widened in alarm. "And you know, since you turned him yellow for noble reasons, that just makes Ron's fit about it even funnier."

"What?" Hermione asked, confused. Ron had seemed happy about it at the time…

"Oh, you didn't hear? Well, that new Slytherin goon that Scabbers bit apparently made a fuss about catching something from him - with the yellow, he does look even more sickly than usual. So the rat - Scabbers, that is-" they grinned at the unnecessary clarification, "is in a cage down in the hospital wing until Madam Pomfrey can make sure he's not actually as diseased as he looks. Even if he checks out, first-years aren't really supposed to have a rat. Dad had wrangled an exception for Scabbers ages ago, but since he's gone after someone, they might actually revoke it. Ron's pretending not to care, but he's taking it a bit hard. Anyway, good luck..." The two strolled jauntily out of the Great Hall.

Hermione sighed. She really ought to have restrained herself on the train...this was what came of stooping to someone else's level. She'd have to apologize to Ron during Charms, though his brothers had a point about first-years only being allowed owls, cats or toads...exceptions to rules made Hermione instinctively purse her lips in disapproval. She began to wonder why she hadn't noticed that at the time.

"You're dragon bait," commented Marcus Belby, a nearby second-year. "It's not as if those two need an excuse for mayhem, but if you've gone and challenged them to a Prank War…"

"I have not," insisted Hermione. "Weren't you listening?"

"Well, maybe you hadn't intended to…" he shrugged.

"What did you do, anyway?" asked Terry. Hermione explained, as briefly as possible. The first-years stared at her and a few of the older students glanced in her direction as well.

"You were already casting spells on the train?"

o-o-o

Ravenclaw shared Charms class with Gryffindor, and Professor Flitwick made a fuss over Harry Potter during roll call. This embarrassed Hermione slightly on the Professor's behalf - he'd been at the Sorting, so it's not as if he could really be surprised now. She supposed that, taken in context, it wasn't all that unreasonable to have an emotional reaction to having the Boy Who Lived in your class, but still.

The tiny Professor gave an overview of all the things they'd be learning to do this term, and demonstrated by making someone's quill leap out of their hand and fly around the room, which everyone found quite impressive. As well as a bit disappointing, since he then had them start practising the simple Wand-Lighting Charm instead. Only it apparently wasn't simple, since only a couple Ravenclaws managed it on the first try - not counting Hermione, of course, for whom it wasn't actually the first try anyway.

Flitwick was very much as she'd found him on his visit to her house. Affable, enthusiastic, talented and clever. It made perfect sense that he was Head of House for Ravenclaw, though when Hermione overheard other students mentioning that he was a past duelling champion, she found it hard to credit, despite her respect for the Professor. It was just hard to picture, though to be fair, she had not yet learned much about duelling. Maybe his size would actually be an advantage, since he was a smaller target and all?

As everyone continued struggling to light and unlight their wands, Hermione quietly gave advice to nearby people she saw having particular trouble. She discovered Tonks was correct - the Professor did in fact give her points for helping, though not everyone she aided seemed grateful to be told what they were doing wrong, which baffled her. Weren't they here to learn? And wouldn't they rather hear it quietly from her than be embarrassed if the Professor pointed it out in front of everyone? Nevertheless, she persisted, and gradually made her way closer to Ron and Harry. The former had in fact been casting frequent sullen glances in her direction throughout the class.

"I'm sorry about your rat," Hermione said, awkwardly. Ron shrugged.

"Probably is diseased, and all he does is sleep anyway, useless lump...good riddance," he replied, a bit unconvincingly. And uncharitably...the rat had leapt - literally - to Ron's defence, or at least to the defence of his sweets.

"Still, I never meant for anything like this to happen...I should've been more responsible," Hermione said, sounding genuinely regretful. Ron looked at her oddly.

"Naw, it was brilliant, really. And he was the one that bit Goyle, not you...just one of those things," he said.

"Still, I feel like I'm partially to blame," Hermione insisted. "If they do end up not letting you keep him, I'll get you a replacement pet...one from the actual list." Ron had no response to this other than to look embarrassed.

"How's Ravenclaw?" asked Harry, trying to break the awkward silence.

"Oh, goodness, it's lovely so far," Hermione said, and described the books in the common room. Possibly in more detail than was warranted, but they were quite an interesting collection, and she hadn't even gone over the titles of all of them yet.

"I noticed your Sorting took a while," she said casually to Harry, after she'd finished. It wasn't prying if she didn't ask outright, right?

"Yeah, it wasn't sure what to do with me...said Slytherin could 'make me great' or some such," he replied with a shrug. A few nearby Gryffindors looked surprised.

"Go on, really?" asked Ron, gaping at him.

"Yeah. I gave it some thought, since Hermione'd said the Houses weren't entirely like how they sounded, but there was no way I was going to share a dorm for seven years with Malfoy, so at the end I just insisted," he said with a shrug. Ron nodded his emphatic agreement with this sentiment.

"Well, just because you didn't go that way doesn't mean you can't be great...just think about what you might've learned from being Slytherin, and try to develop that on your own," Hermione suggested. Ron made a scoffing noise.

"Pfeh...all they'd've taught you is how to be a slimy git, not very great if you ask me…", he said, but Harry nodded thoughtfully.

After class was dismissed, Hermione had lingered to ask Professor Flitwitck about the house-elves. He'd first confirmed that there wasn't anything it was outright illegal to simply discuss - aside from matters covered by Secrecy Statute, with respect to muggles - but there were quite a few things that might be considered inappropriate for first-years. But he'd answered her actual question readily enough, basically echoing what the house-elves themselves had said. It was uniformly their greatest desire to provide good service and unflagging loyalty - the magical contracts which bound them to the house they served were entirely voluntary, and enforced via their own magic. He didn't know how these arrangements had come to be common - he dimly recalled reading that once, millennia ago, house-elves had been independent and wandered, though even then they had often performed the same sorts of services they did now.

Hermione wasn't happy about this, but given it was voluntary, there wasn't much to do about it, as long as they weren't being tricked into it somehow. The best she could think of right now would be to try to make sure the local house-elves were informed that they had options, and obviously to do some research on how they'd come to the current arrangements. She duly added it to the list of things she wanted to look into.

o-o-o

Herbology was pleasant enough, and Hermione thought it'd be an interesting class, since there were plenty of hands-on experiences they'd be provided beyond what was in the book. All they really did the first class, though, was to do roll call and then take a tour of the greenhouses and school grounds, with professor Sprout pointing out every interesting plant within sight. The Professor was not quite as ebullient as Flitwick, though she had a determined cheerfulness that befitted her other position as Head of Hufflepuff, and her enthusiasm for Herbology seemed easily equal to that of his for Charms.

After that was lunch. The Weasley Twins grinned at Hermione when she came in, but there'd been no sign of any pranking yet. She had decided to ignore them, of course. If there was a prank, she'd just have to deal with it as it happened, but it had occurred to her that they might be pulling a meta-prank - trying to make her paranoid when there actually were no threats - so her best defence there as well was to simply act normally.

The class groupings changed in the afternoon, and Hermione's next two classes were with Slytherin. First came Defence Against the Dark Arts. Though it became immediately clear that the class was poorly named, or ought to have been two different classes - there seemed to be a distinct division between defending oneself from dangerous creatures and defending oneself from actual Dark Arts, as the former did not generally use the latter. Hermione wondered if they'd just been lumped together under the common ground of 'bad things', or if it had been done to pad out the curriculum in the earlier years - based on her own reading, a child had little realistic chance of defending themselves against an adult wizard in general, let alone one inclined to use the Dark Arts, whereas driving off minor pests wasn't all that hard even for a beginner, and sometimes didn't even require magic. Regardless of her doubts, she paid proper attention...a class was a class, after all.

At the same time, she also paid some attention to the Slytherin first-years sharing the class with the Ravenclaws, hoping to see some evidence for her theories about them not necessarily being all that bad. She got a chance when at one point in the class, Professor Quirrell had asked if anyone knew anything about Hags. Hermione had waited, but after only one person had raised their hand (to mention they ate babies), she raised her own, and when called upon gave a brief (she'd thought) but thorough overview of the topic, then sat down.

"Got one in the family, have you?" asked Malfoy. There was scattered laughter - all of the Slytherins joined in, and even a couple of Ravenclaws, though those got disapproving looks from their fellows. Hermione felt warmth in her cheeks, though she forced herself to meet people's eyes, the Slytherins' particularly. Some of the laughter, she decided, was just at the inappropriateness of the question, but a little more than half of the Slytherins did seem to be taking malicious pleasure in the implied insult. It was much the same as she'd endured for years in her muggle school, and it felt just as bad.

Though curiously, her embarrassment was receding a little more quickly than it used to, and the laughter hadn't lasted as long. Maybe it was her open question about the Slytherins...having something to analyse instead of just feeling embarrassed, was letting her brush it off more easily? Or the fact that she was in a House meant that she now had implied friends, and wasn't quite as vulnerable a target? In any case, she took special note of which Slytherins had (Malfoy and his 'goons', plus Millicent, Pansy and Sophia) and hadn't (Theodore, Blaise, Tracey and Daphne) seemed to delight in the cruelty itself, to see if that pattern held later.

Professor Quirrell didn't intervene at all. He appeared not at all sure of himself, though his rather untraditional (even among wizards) choice in headwear seemed to speak to at least some kind of self-confidence. But he had a stammer, and jumped at loud noises. Nearby students whispered that they'd heard he used to teach Muggle Studies, but he'd gone abroad somewhere to get hands-on experience for this new position, and only barely escaped with his life - the classroom smelled strongly of garlic, which he'd apologized for and explained was 'a regrettable necessity'. Despite his timidity, class discipline didn't break down entirely, since everything was so new to the first-years, and they were genuinely interested in the discussion.

o-o-o

Transfiguration would be the last class of the day for first-years, and before she'd even taken roll call, Professor McGonagall firmly set the tone for her classes.

"Transfiguration is the most dangerous form of magic you will be taught about at Hogwarts, with only the possible exception of Dark Arts. Can anyone tell me why?" She looked quite serious, in a way that few teachers who Hermione had encountered previously had managed. "Miss Davis?" she said, acknowledging the Slytherin girl who had raised a hand.

"Well, Charms can do things to you, and Dark Arts can hurt you or kill you in lots of ways, but Transfiguration can really mess you up," she said, and she sounded like the idea was more interesting than concerning.

"That is part of the answer, yes...many mishaps in Transfiguration can be fatal in extremely unpleasant ways, or indeed so unpleasant in general that death would be preferable." The class absorbed this sombrely, trying to (or not to, depending on their constitution) imagine Transfigurations that would make someone wish they were dead. "Any ideas as to the other part?" Hermione thought she saw where the Professor was going with this, and raised her hand. "Miss Granger?"

"Well, most Transfigurations aren't permanent. They're tricky to undo since you have to know exactly what was done and do it in reverse, but if you just wait, eventually they'll revert. However, um-" she hesitated for a moment, trying to think how to describe the concept, "interactive changes persist. That is to say, if you turn a rock into a stick, and break the stick, when the Transfiguration wears off, you'll have a broken rock. Or if you transfigure water to acid, and spill it on your hand, the acid would later turn back to water, but your hand would still be burned, and I suppose maybe some of the water would be changed because of how the acid reacted with your hand, though that'd depend on-"

"That is sufficient, Miss Granger," interrupted Professor McGonagall, nodding, "but you are mostly correct. The effects of most Charms and even Potions can generally - so long as they are not fatal - be reversed by cancelling the magic involved directly, or as you noted, simply waiting...though depending on the strength and skill of the caster, you may have a considerable wait. However, a flawed transfiguration - particularly of living subjects - can become effectively permanent, if too much time passes. Additionally, again as Miss Granger noted, changes other than the Transfiguration itself do persist indefinitely, so care must be taken when Transfiguring anything into fragile or otherwise volatile forms."

"However, even more importantly, and with greater relevance to first years - since it will be some time until any of you could manage even a flawed Human Transfiguration - even a simple mistake in basic Transfiguration can result in a form or substance which has unknown qualities, the secondary effects of which are permanent, unless they can be repaired in other ways!" A sea of confused looks greeted this declaration, though many of the Ravenclaws seemed to be trying to puzzle it out.

"An example," the Professor continued, accustomed to this reaction. "A fellow student during my own time attending Hogwarts attempted to - outside of class - Transfigure a pair of rocks into earrings for herself, that glowed with blue light. Some of you might be concerned about what happened to her earlobes when the Transfiguration wore off-" several female students winced, "but Untransfiguration is accommodating. That is to say, a Transfiguration itself, when properly reverted, will generally not cause harm or changes to other things as a result. So in that sense, her attempt seemed both innocent and successful. It was not." The Professor paused for effect. "The next day, most of her hair had fallen out. The day after that, she fell deathly ill. It was clear she'd been cursed or poisoned somehow, but even after it was known to be the result of proximity to a flawed Transfiguration, no remedy attempted could halt the progress of her condition. A boy she'd...spent some time with grew similarly ill. She died after lingering quite painfully for another two days, though the boy eventually recovered. To this day, we still do not understand precisely what happened." She let this sink in, then leaned forward, and her voice gained intensity.

"I have been instructing Transfiguration for over three decades. No student has ever died during one of my classes, or as a result of misuse of Transfiguration outside of classes. But there have-been-close-calls." The class was silent, and entirely cowed. "Accordingly, you will pay complete attention in my class at all times to what you are doing. You will follow any instructions I give in my class immediately. If at any time your behaviour in or out of class causes me to feel that you are not giving Transfiguration the proper respect and are thereby endangering yourself and your classmates, that will mark the end of your Transfiguration classes at Hogwarts. Additionally, in that event, a Permanent Injunction Charm against even attempting to use the true Transfiguration Spell would be cast upon you by a Ministry official and not lifted until such time as you or your parents presented good evidence at a Ministry hearing that you had matured sufficiently to try again, and you had found a Ministry-approved private tutor - as you would be unlikely to rejoin my classes in any case. You would of course be expelled from Hogwarts in the interim, since until your sixth year, Transfiguration is a required core subject. I trust I have made myself clear?" There were a couple of yesses, but mostly frightened nodding.

"Now that the introductions are covered, I will call roll - when I call your name, please respond by restating your own name, followed by, 'I understand and agree to the conditions as stated'." She tapped the board at the front of the class and that phrase suddenly appeared in large yellow letters, then picked up a scroll from her desk and began reading names.

Needless to say, her instructions were followed. Hermione, who had read every word of every EULA for every program she'd installed on the Amiga or the IBM-compatible at home (and in fact cancelled the installation of a handful as a result), and who had developed a vaguely sceptical view of the quality of the Muggle Studies curriculum at Hogwarts based on her background reading, hastily reassessed the latter opinion.

"Now that's over with," she said with a sudden smile, once everyone's name had been called, "and lest you expect your next five years in Transfiguration - or more, if you apply yourselves - to be spent in mortal terror…" She tapped her wand on her desk, and with an eye-watering twist it became a large pig, which stood there docilely, only shifting slightly. The students leaned forward eagerly, and a few made quiet exclamations. "At the risk of immodesty, true Transfiguration is the pinnacle of the magical arts. No other discipline requires the same combination of knowledge, concentration and precision, nor allows for as much creativity in practice and immediate flexibility in application." The Professor paused a moment, then tapped the pig and her desk returned.

She chose to capitalize on the enthusiasm this demonstration had generated by launching immediately into a lecture on the basics of Transfiguration, insisting that everyone take careful notes. Though Hermione had already read all of this, she took notes just as carefully, due - aside from her natural inclinations - both to Professor McGonagall's warnings of the dangers as well as Hannah's insight that their books might not be current, or even complete. Some of the notes were on the differences between Transfiguration Charms, which were very numerous and quite specialized, and the true Transfiguration Spell, which was easy to cast - the incantation was "Mutato", and there was no required wand motion - and which could theoretically do anything involving Transformation, but which was very difficult to get to do exactly what you wanted. Most of the notes were specifics on how to approach the latter.

The Professor finally passed out matchsticks to everyone, and explained that their first project was changing them into needles with true Transfiguration. Many students immediately began their attempts, with predictable utter failure. Hermione followed her notes and the reading, which said the first step was to identify and keep a firm mental image of as many points of comparison as possible between the target and the destination, and only then cast the spell, aiming to eliminate all the divergences. After a couple of minutes, she had the obvious list, as did most of the Ravenclaws, who began their own attempts. But it seemed clear from the reading that, since they were so inexperienced with the proper concentration and had little 'magical strength' to speak of, their success today would depend much more on their mental pictures. So Hermione continued on, making estimates from memory of the chemical structure and composition of wood versus steel, and even of carbon, hydrogen and oxygen versus iron, filling several parchments with relevant calculations and diagrams.

She got so involved in this that, by the time the class was nearly over and Professor McGonagall was coming around to collect matchsticks - which were largely unchanged except for those of a couple of Ravenclaws who'd managed to make them slightly more pointy - Hermione hadn't started a single attempt. She hadn't even taken her wand out.

"Miss Granger, practice and practical application is essential to your understanding of Transfiguration. I am aware that my introductory speech can be intimidating to some students - as it is meant to be - but please at least attempt the assignment in future classes?" The Professor sounded a bit disappointed, and to hear disappointment in a teacher's voice struck at Hermione's heart like a poisoned dagger.

"Oh, goodness, no! I just wanted to write down as many points of comparison as possible before I started. I thought that would make it quicker in the long run, since the eventual Transfiguration would be easier..." she explained, anxiously.

"I might have commended you for that preparation, if you'd actually done it, but I cannot help but note that your parchment is blank," McGonagall noted, her lips pursed. Hermione looked down at the parchment, which had been covered in calculations of atomic weights only a moment ago. It was blank. She flipped back to the other parchments she'd used for comparison and her initial Transfiguration notes, and they, too, were blank. She didn't understand. Had she mistaken a regular quill for the Self-Inking one she'd bought? But no, she'd seen the writing on the pages, obviously. In her concentration, had she imagined writing all those notes? That seemed very unlikely, and besides, she took parchment from her bag one scroll at a time only as needed, thus there wouldn't be several out now if she'd never really written at all.

A sudden noise distracted her from her panic, and she looked to her right to see that Terry Boot had knocked over his bag. When he bent down to right it, he looked up at Hermione and mouthed silently, dragon bait. She stared at him for a moment, then looked at her quill, frowning darkly.

"I think my self-inking quill...or maybe the parchment...may have been jinxed," Hermione said, in a tone sufficiently grim for one discussing a horrific murder. Professor McGonagall looked unimpressed.

"Traditionally students wait until after their first homework is due to trot out that old gem," she said dryly. "I suspect this establishes a new record." Hermione gaped at her in horror, and several students - all Slytherins - snickered, earning them a stern glance from McGonagall. She didn't believe her! Not only had she lost all her notes and not even tried to Transfigure anything, the Professor thought she was just making excuses. Her mind began to cast frantically around for some argument that would convince the Professor - the Twins were in her House, surely she'd know of their proclivities - but Hermione feared everything she could say would only sound like another excuse. Suddenly she realized there was only one way she might prove she'd actually been paying attention and doing the work, despite all evidence to the contrary.

Hermione pulled her wand from her bag, and before the Professor could say anything, touched it to her matchstick, focused desperately on all of the comparisons she'd done, and said, "Mutato!" Within seconds, the matchstick had become thinner, silver, and pointed.

"Stop!" said the Professor, her eyes widening in mild alarm. Hermione wanted to keep going, it just needed to have the eye added, surely only a couple more seconds would-

...follow any instructions I give in my class immediately...

Hermione's mental justifications cut off sharply as she remembered the Professor's rules. Her fingers sprang open as if her wand had become red-hot, and it clattered onto her desk, the not-quite-a-needle remaining incomplete. For a moment, the room was quiet, students cautiously standing and or craning their necks to see what Hermione had done to produce such a reaction, Hermione looking up at Professor McGonagall with worry that she'd made a mistake somehow, and the Professor looking back at her with an unreadable expression. McGonagall shook her head gently and cleared her throat.

"My apologies, Miss Granger," she said, sincerely. "See me after class and I shall examine your supplies for tampering." She gave Hermione a soft smile, then collected her quasi-needle and the rest of the students' matchsticks.

After the class was dismissed, a handful of students immediately surrounded Hermione, asking how she'd managed her Transfiguration. After several patient assurances that she'd explain later, she managed to extricate herself and approach the Professor's desk.

"Let me see your parchment first, Miss Granger," McGonagall asked. "Most commercially-enchanted items - Self-Inking Quills included - are strongly charmed against tampering." Hermione handed the curls of parchment to McGonagall, who began waving her wand over them. On a sudden suspicion, Hermione also searched in her bag for the notes she'd taken in her earlier classes, and found they were blank as well. She closed her eyes, trying to hold back the tears of frustration she felt coming.

Laughing at her, calling her names, messing with her clothes, slipping nasty notes into her bag - she'd regularly endured all of them before coming to Hogwarts. And they'd made her feel small and weak, partly in the natural way, but also because she knew they were intended to do that, and that if she'd only been...better, somehow, they wouldn't have been able to. But interfering with her studies? That was a new low, it was just...just… Hermione couldn't think of a word - at least, not in the subset of appropriate words she allowed herself to think - that was sufficiently bad to describe it.

"There are lingering traces, but nothing amiss here," McGonagall said. "I'll have to examine the quill after all." Hermione took her parchment back and handed the quill over, wordlessly. "There was something else I wanted to discuss," she continued, as she began examining the quill. "Could you explain the mental images you used when Transfiguring the matchstick?" She sounded casual, and it appeared most of her attention was on the quill, but there was a note in her voice that suggested more than idle curiosity.

Hermione pushed her feelings down for the moment and explained everything she'd thought of. She did not define the scientific concepts involved, assuming that McGonagall had to be familiar with such things already, teaching Transfiguration as she did. But during the entire part where Hermione was describing alloys and lignin and atomic mass ratios, she could not miss the Professor's slight frown. McGonagall put the quill down and looked up at Hermione, folding her hands on her desk.

"Did you practice Transfiguration at all before today?" she asked, calmly. Hermione shook her head.

"No, I obviously couldn't do anything at home because of the law, and I only practised some basic Charms on the train - the book was quite clear about how dangerous Transfiguration can be, though it wasn't quite as forceful as your speech…" The Professor nodded, as if she'd expected this answer.

"No child with no practice whatsoever - indeed no first-year in general, in point of fact - should have been able to perform that Transfiguration so quickly. I must assume, then, that your advantage lies in the muggle 'sciences', of which I understand very little." She paused for a moment, choosing her words, and Hermione shifted uncomfortably. She wasn't used to teachers who admitted ignorance of any kind, and while the words had seemingly been complimentary, they hadn't sounded like praise.

"I am hesitant to forbid you a talent based on obvious study...you presumably earned what...knowledge...the muggles have given you. However, I must warn you - the student in the example I gave, Moira Leigh-Smith? She seemed to have a natural talent for Transfiguration, and was highly praised by...the Professor at the time," she said, a bit awkwardly.

"He had a soft spot for muggles, you see, and she was a muggle-born as well - I believe her mother was a 'doctor', as your parents are?" Hermione nodded, and didn't bother to correct the minor detail, too curious to know where the Professor was going with this. "I'd simply ask that before you attempt any Transfiguration involving muggle science, you consult with me first. Not that I am suggesting you are irresponsible...just that...I would be remiss if I did not consider the parallel."

Hermione nodded, slowly. She might have resented the unique restriction, except that she'd just had an inkling of what might have happened to Moira and her boyfriend, in light of which McGonagall's caution seemed entirely justified. She really ought to have thought of it immediately, maybe she even had on some level but had discarded it, because it was brilliant and yet very stupid - though that depended partially on how long ago it had happened, exactly - and all for what...glowing earrings? Not that watch dials were a particularly more worthy goal...

"I will, of course. Although if you don't understand muggle science, I'm not sure how...er...consulting with you will help? If it's any consolation, I think I might understand that student's mistake…" The Professor frowned, and Hermione began to worry that McGonagall might've taken her question as an insult. But after a moment, she nodded.

"I pride myself on my knowledge of Transfiguration, and if muggle science can have such significant effects on it, it behoves me to correct that obvious deficiency. My impressions of you suggest that you will have such notions frequently, and it would be safer if they were not discussed in front of the class. Accordingly, we can arrange special tutoring sessions in the evenings or on weekends when you can discuss your ideas with me...while at the same time, you can do your best to teach me muggle science." Hermione nodded along until the Professor reached the last part.

"I...um. I did bring some of my books from home, which will help...but that might take...quite a while," Hermione hedged.

"We do have seven years...I suppose we shall just have to be patient with each other. The Hat did offer me Ravenclaw, if it's any consolation," she added, wryly, echoing Hermione's own words.

"Now that's settled, back to the matter of your notes. I believe this quill-" she nodded at the quill on her desk, "is not one you had originally purchased. It is a Self-Inking Quill, but the ink it produces is Disillusioning Ink, a change that could likely be produced only during the original charming of the item." Hermione's heart fell. She'd been so distracted by the other conversation, she'd actually forgotten about her notes for a couple minutes. "Presumably it was switched for your original quill at some point - do you have any idea who might've done so?"

She had a very good idea, but she hesitated to immediately name the Weasley Twins. For one, informing on students in her old school had for some reason never resulted in a punishment to the offender as unpleasant as the offence itself, and had frequently led to even greater taunts later. Things might be different here, but there was also the other matter - she had no proof it was them. Hermione reminded herself to add 'forensic spells' to her list of things to look into.

"In any case, as wholly inappropriate as it was, I do not think it was meant maliciously," continued McGonagall after Hermione had remained silent for a moment. "Disillusionment is easily reversed - which I will do for you now - but this particular ink could likely only have remained hidden for a day at the most, and would have reverted naturally of its own accord." Hermione felt a ridiculous surge of relief that she hadn't lost all her notes. Of course, she'd written them, so she remembered nearly every word anyway, but it would've taken a long time to re-copy them, which could now be spent more productively. For a moment, she felt a strange sort of gratitude, until she remembered whoever'd done this had deliberately made her feel awful in the first place, and got a bit conflicted.

"Thank you, Professor." she said, opting to focus her gratitude on Professor McGonagall, who genuinely deserved it. "For fixing the Disillusionment, but also for...apologizing," Hermione added. The Professor smiled ruefully.

"You are welcome. But if I did not set an example for my students of both honesty and graciousness, I would be hard-pressed to consider myself an educator of any worth." Hermione beamed at her, and noted to herself that there were apparently a few things that made Hogwarts special that had nothing at all to do with magic.

o-o-o

Transfiguration had been Hermione's last class for the day. This meant she was free until dinner, so she took the opportunity to finally visit the library. If she was honest with herself, it was actually a bit…disappointing. After the rest of Hogwarts, she'd expected it to be amazing, wonderful, and awe-inspiring. Instead, it was cramped, disorganized and downright inhospitable.

To be fair, based on her rough estimates (and Hogwarts, a History), it did have tens of thousands of books - obviously mostly about magic, which had to count for something. But Hermione had frequently visited the London Library, which held over a million books, and while she had not yet qualified for a Reader Pass at the British Library, she knew that it stored 150 times as many items in turn. She supposed that the magical population was so low that they simply didn't publish all that many books each year.

But Hermione reminded herself that the value of a library was not in its size, but in what it could teach you. There was no point in complaining about it until she ran out of things to learn, which she suspected would take quite a while. Particularly given the labyrinthine collection of bookshelves, scattered throughout an assortment of randomly-sized rooms on the third floor, with no hint of even an old-style card catalogue. She hoped that the librarian could help her, though she'd heard vague reports from other Ravenclaws that she was rather...intense.

"Excuse me, Madam Pince?", she asked quietly, once she found the thin woman's desk. "I was wondering if you-" The librarian shushed her noisily. The noise was actually louder than Hermione's question had been, but she dutifully lowered her voice to a barely-audible whisper. She made it a rule to humour librarians, though she'd never actually met one who fit the stereotypes quite so well before today. "Sorry. I was wondering if you could help me research a few-"

"I don't have time to help students with homework, nor should you expect such help," she interrupted, sternly.

"Oh, well it's not actually for classes, it's just a few-"

"I certainly do not have time to help with personal projects." Interrupting seemed to be the woman's natural mode of conversation.

"Oh. Well, I'm muggle-born...what is it that librarians-"

"Librarians are guardians of the library, and the books within, of course. I ensure that these rooms maintain a suitable atmosphere for serious study and research, that no harm comes to the volumes, and that they are only borrowed - and returned - by responsible students."

"So if a student needed to find a particular-"

"She would consult a professor, or other students, and not take up the librarian's valuable time." Hermione gave up at this point, and took Madam Pince's 'advice', seeking out an older Ravenclaw.

"You got a lot further with her than most people do," said a third-year, Roger Davies, after Hermione had - quietly - explained her difficulties to him. "She must like you." Hermione took a moment to digest this.

"So, how do you find particular books around here?" she asked.

"Well, the bookshelves are grouped into Sections of course, but beyond that it's a matter of practice, memory, and diligence. Madam Pince does go to considerable lengths to ensure the books are always replaced in the exact location they came from, so at least you can rely on that. Though if there's some pattern to it, she's never told anyone, and no one's ever figured one out." Hermione sighed. She went over her list with Roger, and he was at least able to point her towards the right Sections for most of them.

She'd started with house-elves, as though it was perhaps of the least practical value, it was ethically the most important question she'd come up with so far, ahead of both what was being done to children sorted into Slytherin and her concerns about the pre-Hogwarts education of magical families. But in the back of her mind, she couldn't help continuing to think about other things that demanded understanding.

As the hour for dinner approached, she found herself frequently distracted by other students' talking in the library, and was starting to commiserate with Madam Pince's increasingly strident attempts to quash such disruptions. Finally, the librarian was apparently pushed past her limits, and closed the library entirely, herding everyone out with exhortations not to come back until they could maintain proper decorum. Hermione, vexed, approached one of the knots of students left gossiping outside the doors to the library.

"You know, some people actually wanted to use the library for studying," she began, crossly.

"How can you think about studying now?" asked a second-year girl she didn't know.

"Why...what's going on?"

"It's Madam Pomfrey," said the girl, breathlessly. "She's dead!"

o-o-o-o-o

A/N: Whew! Once again, sorry it took so long to get this update up, but I had a lot of background to work out, including a canon-respecting but actually sensible class schedule and nailing down (for this fic, anyway) some open questions about how magic works. Plus, some lazing about. But mostly the schedule, which I am unreasonably proud of.

However, procrastination pays off in some ways, as just as I was about to post this, I noticed a PM from LovingPillow, who figured out the door riddle! Congratulations! As it happens, the way I ended up writing the next chapter, I couldn't work the answer smoothly into the story, so it'll be left unsaid for future readers to puzzle over. I'll continue shout-outs to other readers who PM me the correct answer, but please don't pester previous winners for hints!

On the upside, things are starting to heat up plot-wise (in addition, of course, to the canon plot that's still going on). Hopefully none of my readers are too fond of Madam Pomfrey. I occasionally write some hidden scenes that won't necessarily ever be published, just to keep things straight in my head, and what happened to Poppy hit me with some feels. I also hope it isn't too obvious what happened there (it's hard for me to tell, since obviously, I know already), but rest assured, even if you're a smarty-pants and have figured that out, there will be more twists to come.

2016-06-02: Thanks to /u/benthor for the brit-pick on lockers not being a thing in the UK!

Chapter 7: Discrepancies

Chapter 7 - Discrepancies

The Great Hall was buzzing with whispers as Hermione sat down at the Ravenclaw table for dinner. Their content was mostly along the lines of what she'd heard outside the Library - that the school healer was dead - along with rumors and speculations as to what had happened. Among other things, she'd heard that it had been a rare and lingering disease she'd contracted while doing aid work in Borneo, that Peeves had finally managed to scare someone to death, that she'd sacrificed her own life in a grand ritual to permanently rid the world of Influenza, and that Professor Snape and a Beater for the Kenmare Kestrels (whatever that meant) were both secretly in love with her and she'd been killed by a stray spell as they dueled for her hand.

Hermione wasn't sure how to behave - no one she'd ever known had died, and she hadn't even met the school healer. She was certain she ought to feel sad, and felt a bit guilty that she didn't feel sadder, but trying to make herself feel sad didn't seem appropriate either. Hermione did point out to several people she overheard that all these rumors seemed implausible at best and disrespectful at worst, but received only dirty looks for her efforts. Maybe no one else knew how to behave either, and the gossip was just their way of filling in the gaps? Eventually, Professor Dumbledore stood, and everyone quickly quieted, waiting expectantly.

"As you have by now undoubtedly heard, earlier this afternoon Madam Pomfrey was found dead in the Hospital Wing." Only a few quiet murmurs followed, as indeed this was hardly a surprise. "Her death appears to have been a tragic accident...one of the lionfish spines in her supplies had somehow been contaminated with salamander blood, and the act of grinding it to powder - in a rare and unfortunate reaction - produced an invisible, odorless, and poisonous vapor, to which she succumbed. Though it may be slight comfort, Professor Snape assures me that the effects of the vapor, though deadly, would have been quite painless." At the Head Table, the Potions Professor, whose class Hermione didn't have until Thursday but who had been pointed out to her, nodded gravely. The expressions of the rest of the staff were a study in discomfort, ranging from Professor Trelawney, who was trying to appear unsurprised while wiping away genuine tears, to Professor Quirrell, who seemed genuinely terrified, to Professor McGonagall, who appeared to be grinding her teeth.

"Fortunately," continued Dumbledore, "the Hospital Wing was otherwise unoccupied at the time, and the vapor quickly dissipated, so there were no other casualties. Nurse Wainscott will be taking on the duties of Hogwarts Healer and Matron for the time being, a position I am sure she will grow into." A dark-haired young woman at the Head Table looked exquisitely uncomfortable at the uncertain and scattered applause that followed this announcement.

"A memorial service will be held Thursday evening after dinner, and any evening classes will be cancelled both that day and tonight, to allow everyone an opportunity either to attend or for private reflection as they prefer. In times such as this, we must remember to cherish the good in one another, for even when we journey onward, our love and laughter remains behind, to brighten the world. But for now, please, eat. If not from appetite, then out of respect for Madam Pomfrey's tireless care for our collective health - nourishment of course included." The food appeared, and it was an assortment of appropriately un-elaborate and comforting dishes. While it was possible someone had instructed them specifically, Hermione reminded herself to express her appreciation to the house-elves in the kitchen later, in case it had been their own idea.

Conversation over the meal was subdued. Apparently without the distraction of speculation, most students were content to keep their thoughts to themselves. What few found the heart to speak were mostly upper-years, reminiscing fondly over injuries or maladies they'd had or seen treated by the talented healer.

After dinner, once it became clear that the Library would not be re-opened, Hermione made her way back to her common room with most of the rest of the Ravenclaws.

"Without moving, we hurt. Without touching, we poison. We carry every truth and form every lie. What are we?" intoned the knocker.

Someone else got the answer first - Hermione was distracted by the inclusion of 'poison', which seemed highly inappropriate in light of the evening's tragedy. Maybe the door knocker, as smart as it seemed, didn't keep up with current events?

The Ravenclaw common room quickly segregated according to the students' respective coping mechanisms. Though it was only the first day, the upper-years already had a significant amount of homework, and most took advantage of the cancellation of evening classes to throw themselves into it as a distraction. The bulk of the younger Ravenclaws, Hermione included, instead sought closure in understanding, and began searching the Tower Library for appropriate books that might explain the rare reaction between lionfish spines and salamander blood.

"Here…" said Roger Davies suddenly. "''Salamander blood has rejuvenating and strengthening properties, and thus is often employed in healing potions'..." he quoted from the book he held.

"Well obviously, if Madam Pomfrey had some, it'd be good for healing," quipped Marietta Edgecombe. Roger shot the second-year girl a look.

"I wasn't finished…" He cleared his throat elaborately, then continued reading aloud. "'In its dried form, however, when ground, the salamander's dynamic properties are invoked, encouraging the release of more potent essences from other materials. The prudent potioneer thus makes certain his ingredients are pure before any grinding step, as salamander blood contamination can produce unexpected results.'"

"I s'pose she wasn't prudent enough," mused Kevin. Roger shook his head.

"That's just the thing," the third-year said with a frown, "she was. I never heard of her making a mistake at all, let alone one like this."

"Well," said Hermione, "how does one check for the purity of ingredients, exactly? Just a visual inspection, or something more involved?" No one knew the answer to this question offhand, so they returned to the books, and eventually determined that identifying ingredient mixtures or contamination required careful testing with other substances that produced known reactions.

"So, it's labor-intensive enough that you could do it every time, but in practice you'd need to rely on your supplier?" Hermione paraphrased. "Although...it sounds like that's for identifying contamination, specifically. Couldn't you just use a general cleaning charm on any ingredient before using it and be safe?"

"I suppose," said Cho. "Though I'm not sure they'd work right on everything without vanishing part of whatever it was you wanted to keep as well. But I'd think lionfish spines ought to be cleanable. As well as her mortar and pestle, obviously." Hermione frowned, and considered this.

"Well, I imagine it might get tedious, always cleaning your ingredients beforehand, when they're supposed to be clean anyway. Even responsible people can become lax about things they're supposed to do regularly," she noted, thinking of her parents' regular complaints about people who were haphazard in brushing. Cavities and gum disease could actually become life-threatening in rare cases, so it wasn't a bad parallel. But Roger shook his head angrily.

"I don't think so...you didn't know her, it's just...no." Hermione didn't think much of Roger's objection in terms of logic, but he was clearly upset at the implication that it might actually be Madam Pomfrey's fault. She knew from her own practice that cleaning spells weren't particularly difficult to cast, though she hadn't tried casting any repeatedly...maybe it would get tiring? Or maybe using magic on potion ingredients beforehand might cause some side-effect just as bad as what you were trying to prevent?

"I haven't even had Potions yet, though I read the book, and it doesn't mention anything about cleaning spells," Hermione offered, in a conciliatory tone. "Maybe there's some reason not to use them?"

"That's right...we've never used them during brewing, ever, only to clean up our workspaces afterwards," Roger said. "I have my first third-year Potions tomorrow, I can ask Professor Snape about it." Hermione nodded.

"I'm sure we can find an explanation for what happened, and it needn't reflect poorly on Madam Pomfrey," she said. "I was actually thinking of finding out where her supplies came from and sending an owl to inquire anyway."

These declarations seemed to satisfy everyone that there were no further immediate avenues for discovery, and the group broke up, heading to their respective dorms.

Hermione penned the first draft of a letter, but it was past curfew, so she'd need to wait until the morning to find out where to send the owl anyway. She spent the last couple hours before going to sleep continuing to read one of the - rare, as it turned out - books she'd found in the library that mentioned house elves more than in passing.

She'd considered writing her parents as well, but she wondered what they would think if she mentioned that the school healer had died. Not exactly confidence-inspiring, that. They might even pull her out of the school. But writing and not mentioning Madam Pomfrey would be lying by omission. Better to wait to write at all until she had all the facts and could frame things in the best possible light.

Before falling asleep, she thought about the Weasley Twins. She supposed they'd heard about her reaction in Transfiguration class. Depending on what sort of bullies they were, either that would satisfy them and they'd move on, or it would only encourage them...but the way they'd framed things as a "war" suggested they weren't solely interested in cruelty for its own sake. She'd have to just try re-surrendering tomorrow morning, and hopefully that would put an end to it.

That night, she had troubling dreams that she couldn't quite remember upon waking.

o-o-o

Before breakfast, Hermione found her way to the kitchens once again. The choice of fare last night had been the elves' own notion, and she thanked them for their consideration. A few alluded to some past conflict with Madam Pomfrey - conflicting orders from her on appropriate nutrition, and from students who wanted special treats - but they held only the highest respect for her, as she had been as devoted to her job as they were to theirs. The elves were all quite pleased at being thanked, though, and seemed inclined to lavish Hermione with favors. Her protests and refusals took so long that by the time she escaped the kitchens, she had no time left to search out potion ingredient suppliers.

Hermione reached the Ravenclaw table just as the food was appearing, and sighed. Apparently at least one of the kitchen elves hadn't heard her strident refusals, or perhaps "hadn't heard" - in practice there did appear to be some leeway in the obedience clause of their contracts - because in addition to the other dishes, a plate of pancakes had appeared directly in front of her seat, which unlike the others was festooned liberally with whipped cream and sliced strawberries. The special treatment did not go unnoticed.

"Hey!" said Michael Corner, a bit loudly, "Why've you got dessert for breakfast? Is it your birthday or something?" Hermione shook her head, but before she could explain another interjection cut in.

"She's been down to the kitchen to butter up the help again, I expect," said Morag, who'd noticed Hermione's nearly-late arrival. Hermione gave her an exasperated look.

"I wasn't buttering them up," she protested, "I just wanted to thank them for their consideration with dinner last night." Morag shrugged, but did not look convinced.

"It did seem rather homey and normal," mused Padma. "Nice of them to think of it, I suppose."

"We can find the kitchens after History of Magic today," Terry suggested to Michael, "and thank the elves for Hermione's pancakes...then tomorrow we should get 'em, and we can just keep on thanking them in turn and have dessert-breakfasts forever!" Hermione sighed again, and refrained from pointing out that they could likely simply ask for what they wanted and the house elves would bend over backwards to provide it, with or without thanks. If they were inclined to overindulge every day, at least this way they'd be showing some appreciation for it.

"This is actually a bit much for breakfast, honestly, so you're welcome to share if-" She leaned back hastily as the boys lunged over the table to begin scraping her serving onto their own plates. Hermione replaced it with more sensible selections, though she couldn't help one wistful glance at the sliced strawberries as they vanished with alarming speed into Terry and Michael.

Once she'd finished eating, she got up and began to make her way toward the Gryffindor table, but Roger Davies rose as well and caught up to her first.

"Hey," he said, a trifle awkwardly. "I just wanted to thank you for helping with - you know - finding out what happened, and not just assuming the worst."

"Oh...it's no trouble. I suppose I'd want someone to do the same if something like that happened to me. Did you...know her well?" Hermione asked, not without her own awkwardness.

"Sort of. I had a few spills first-year in Flying, and I got sick last year, so I've spent a lot of time in the hospital wing." He looked even more awkward, though Hermione wasn't sure why. She supposed he might be embarrassed about falling off a broomstick, but that didn't really fit with getting sick.

"Well, I'll let you know when I get any responses...I should be able to send the owls before dinner." He nodded and withdrew. Since it seemed so important to him, Hermione really hoped for Roger's sake that whatever they discovered did excuse Madam Pomfrey from responsibility, though she knew that was not a foregone conclusion. She resumed her path and arrived at the Gryffindor table, nodding at the friendly waves from Ron and Harry. Though her stomach felt unsettled as she neared and second-guessed her plan. Surrendering immediately hadn't worked yesterday, what if it only egged them on? Was there some other way?

"Misters Weasley, could I have a word in private?" she said a bit stiffly, and Ron looked confused until he realized she was speaking to the Twins, at which point he still looked confused. The elder brothers shared a silent look, then shrugged and rose, each extending an arm away from the table.

"After you - Miss Granger," they said, dividing the sentence and mimicking her formal tone with an added subtle hint of mockery. Hermione pursed her lips, but didn't comment, and preceded them to a deserted corner of the Great Hall. Once they arrived, the brothers didn't say anything, instead waiting for Hermione to start. She took a deep breath and tried to keep her voice steady.

"As I'm sure you already know, I discovered yesterday that my Self-Inking Quill had been replaced somehow with a similar one that held Disillusioning Ink instead," she said, quietly.

"Really? - for shame!" they said, alternately. "It's shocking what some miscreants - get away with these days. Although, we've some familiarity with these matters, and we'd be surprised - if any notes that vanished hadn't come back by dinner tonight. Assuming you haven't re-used the parchment, anyway…"

"Oh no," said Hermione. "They're back already...Professor McGonagall was kind enough to see to it." This casual remark was rewarded by an uncertain glance between the Twins. "At the time I decided not to name any likely suspects...though I would like the original quill back...it wasn't entirely inexpensive, and I suspect every time I have to use a spare I'll be thinking about it...if that happens too often, maybe a couple names will come to me," she mused theatrically. Though she tried to keep her face neutral, Hermione clutched her robes at her sides to keep her hands from shaking - she'd never actually tried blackmailing someone before, though she wasn't sure just getting her proper quill back really counted anyway. But the boys looked only a bit concerned, and even managed to appear mildly wounded.

"Please, Miss Granger...a true Pranktitioner of the Unexpected Arts is not a thief. I suspect, if we were to actually engage in such a caper - not that we're admitting complicity in any such thing - the victim might find, upon counting her stash of spare quills - that she had one more 'spare' than she expected." They looked quite pleased with themselves, and Hermione blinked in surprise.

"Ah. Well...I hope this is the end of it? I have no intention of responding in kind, and I'm happy to publicly surrender again if you'd like. Any further incidents of this sort will only result in my own unhappiness and immediate appeals to authority. I really have better things to do with my time, and I'd so hoped that this school wouldn't be like my previous ones..." She'd planned here on using the sort of wistful guilt-inducing tone her mother was ever so good at, but she found that she couldn't help recalling her earlier school days vividly and was forced to swallow a genuine lump in her throat. The Twins shared a glance and their expressions grew more somber.

"Our sincere apologies," they said in unison, bowing with elaborate arm flourishes and continuing their formal tone. "We'd been sure you would be a capable and enthusiastic opponent - and still think you could be. Accordingly, we will call this not surrender but rather negotiated truce - and you may consider our Prank War in abeyance until such time - if ever - that you wish to formally declare a renewal of hostilities - I actually think you mean 'festivities' there, Fred - ah, right you are George, renewal of festivities." Hermione wasn't sure how to react to this unexpected show of respect. In the face of her old memories, it threatened to overwhelm her fragile emotional state in the opposite direction. She took a moment to compose herself and decide how exactly to respond.

"Accepted. For what it's worth, all told it's the...well, the second-most considerate prank I've ever fallen victim to," she admitted, thinking of the Hufflepuff on the train. People were beginning to file out of the Great Hall at this point and after each giving Hermione a nod, the Twins joined the flow, talking as they went.

"That was downright gallant of us, wasn't it George? We could've at least left the original quill in the castle eaves or a loo or something... - No other word for it, Fred, Knights Errant of Pranking, we are - of course we can't afford to get a reputation for consideration - obviously not, we just need to focus on more deserving targets for a bit - so we'll not be as inclined towards mercy…"

Hermione shook her head and joined the throng of students heading to class as well.

o-o-o

Hermione's schedule for Tuesday was identical to Monday's, with the exception of History of Magic in fifth period, so she caught up with Ron and Harry on their way to Charms.

"What was that about, with Fred and George?" Ron asked, as she joined them.

"I'm honestly not sure...they're very peculiar, aren't they? But I was just trying to put their ridiculous 'Prank War' to rest," she said.

"Oh...pity," said Ron, looking disappointed. "After your trick with Scabbers, I was sort of hoping you'd give them a proper run." Hermione grimaced and sighed.

"There's so much to learn here...we really don't have time for that sort of thing, even if I were so inclined, which I'm not. Besides, I still regret that and-" she broke off, her hand going to her mouth in horror. Ron and Harry noticed she'd stopped walking and turned back, looking confused and concerned, respectively.

"What is it?" asked Harry.

"Oh, Ron, I've just realized about Scabbers...I am so sorry…" The Gryffindors shared a baffled look, then turned it upon Hermione. She looked even more uncomfortable, assuming their confusion meant they hadn't found out yet. "He must've been in the hospital wing with Madam Pomfrey, when...the vapor…" she trailed off, her expression stricken. As Ron realized what she meant, his expression became surprised, but not unhappy.

"Blimey...he dodged a bludger there, I hadn't even thought of that!" he admitted. Now it was Hermione's turn to be confused.

"He...dodged...what?" she asked, baffled on more than one level.

"Scabbers was already in our room when we got back from Defence Against the Dark Arts," explained Harry. "Madam Pomfrey must have finished her examination and dropped him off there before…it happened." Hermione nearly collapsed in relief, though it was short-lived as she realized they were nearly late for Charms, and she hurried everyone along.

Charms class was mildly irritating. Lavender Brown had apparently somehow lost her wand already, so Hermione (who'd clearly already mastered the Wand-lighting Charm) had to share her wand with the Gryffindor girl, then listen to her frequent complaints about how it didn't feel right as she tried to coach her through casting the spell.

"Honestly, how could you misplace something so important?" Hermione eventually asked, exasperated.

"I didn't misplace it, I know I had it in Defence yesterday, and I put it in my bag afterward. I didn't go looking for it until now, and my bag hasn't been out of my sight except for while I was sleeping. Besides, you saw Professor Flitwick cast all those spells trying to find it, and he couldn't...it must be one of those weird Hogwarts things that the upper-years say are always happening." Hermione frowned at this, but Hogwarts, a History did have a great many mentions of odd things that had never been properly explained. Still, it was an article of faith for her that everything had an explanation, even if no one had managed to figure one out yet.

"I don't know what I'll do if it doesn't turn up soon," Lavender continued, oblivious to Hermione's skepticism. "I suppose my parents will have to take me back to Ollivander's to find a new one. Which is a pity, as I so liked the original...fir and unicorn hair, ten inches, just a hint of spring…" She sighed elaborately, staring into the distance as if pining over a lost love. When Hermione cleared her throat gently, the flighty Gryffindor came back to herself and grimaced at the wand in her hand as if it were a spoiled sausage.

"Maybe Peeves took it, they say he goes everywhere, even our bedrooms," suggested Hannah from her adjacent desk, her tone scandalized.

"If it's any consolation, he may look like a little man, but he's not really. I've read he's not a proper ghost...he was never actually alive to begin with," Hermione pointed out, trying to reassure Hannah.

"Still...yuck," she said, and Hermione could only shrug and nod.

Charms finally finished, and mercifully Herbology still didn't involve any wandwork, so Hermione was able to reclaim her wand from Lavender. For just a moment, she wanted to stroke it and murmur soothingly to it, but that felt a little too close to the other girl's irritating feelings for her own wand, and she refrained. Still, it couldn't hurt to try and pick up some wand cleaner...she wasn't certain that she was only imagining being able to see Lavender's oily fingerprints on it…

Defence class passed uneventfully, although Professor Quirrell was behaving oddly in a significantly different way than he had yesterday. Instead of jumping at noises and looking around shiftily, he stared off into the distance as if lost in thought, often for minutes at a time, sometimes in the middle of a sentence. Of course, when someone cleared their throat to snap him out of it, then he'd jump. At first it was prompting from Hermione, who only wanted to minimize the interruptions to their education, but later it was largely the Slytherins, who delighted in having a legitimate excuse to provoke such a reaction from the Professor.

Transfiguration turned out to be surprisingly uncomfortable, in an unexpected way. The class proceeded as it had yesterday (albeit without the introductory warnings and agreement), with lecture and discussion for the first half, then practice for the second. After Professor McGonagall handed out the matchsticks, Hermione briefly reviewed her now-restored notes and dove straight in. In considerably less than a minute, she had a brilliantly shining needle.

"So, can you tell us now how you're doing that so fast?" asked Su Li. Most of the nearby students immediately turned to listen.

"Just like the book and Professor McGonagall say, compare, contrast then conform. Just...it helps to be as detailed as you can," she began, slowly. But she realized that wouldn't help them much if they didn't understand the details, and she'd promised the Professor not to share her scientific insights with the students until the woman herself had learned enough muggle science to ensure general safety.

"I thought I had been," said Padma. "Here, let me see your notes," she continued, moving to read over Hermione's shoulder. Instinctively, Hermione flipped the small stack of parchment over, hiding the writing. The look of surprise and offence on the girl's face immediately made Hermione feel awful. She was about to hastily explain her promise to the Professor, but she paused to consider the implications. Just giving them the idea would complicate things, if they knew any science at all they'd have to make the same promise...and if they didn't understand science as well as her, they might not take it quite so seriously. Furthermore, if she just told them she'd promised McGonagall not to say without explaining why, it'd seem like she was "conspiring" with a Professor, which from past experience would not go well. And if she just refused and didn't say anything about why she was refusing…

"So that's how it is?" asked Morag, softly. "It's fine tae help with things like wand-licht, but when it comes tae real magic, it's every witch for herself, hmm?" Padma's expression hardened, even as Hermione's grew more unhappy.

"It's not like that," Hermione protested, but had no words to continue with. Padma went back to her seat without another word and Morag nodded. Even worse, all of the nearby Slytherins were giving her looks that Hermione could only call appraising...like they were positively updating their estimations of her deviousness, or worthiness - for the few that might even consider those two concepts separable.

"Diligent practice, I suspect, will serve you much better in the long run than conversation," Professor McGonagall called out primly from the front of the classroom. Everyone turned back to their matchsticks, with only occasional glances at Hermione, who couldn't decide if the Professor had done her a favor or not by cutting the discussion short.

When class was over, she didn't linger to ask the Professor for advice - there was no sense in giving anyone more ammunition, and anyway she still had a new class to get to, today. Besides, just because she hadn't been able to think of a solution in an hour's time didn't mean there wasn't one to be found.

Hermione took a seat in the History of Magic classroom, and felt a familiar tightness in her chest as some Ravenclaws deliberately left empty desks between themselves and her. But she told herself it was for the best anyway, until she worked out how to handle the situation, trying to ignore the whispers she couldn't quite make out.

Though she knew what to expect, having read about Professor Binns in Hogwarts, a History, Hermione jumped a little with most of the other students when the ghost entered the classroom, not through the doorway, but by simply floating straight through the chalkboard at the front. In a low drone, the translucent, wizened figure began to take roll, seemingly oblivious that no one responded to any of the names he read off, none of which sounded familiar at all. Hermione would've attempted to point this out, but he turned his back on the class and launched straight into a droning lecture, scrawling notes onto the chalkboard as he spoke in blurry and illegible ghost-chalk.

The students collectively shrugged and began to take notes or quietly talk amongst themselves, according to their individual predilection. Even Hermione found it difficult to pay attention and take proper notes, as the old ghost's voice seemed to have a hypnotic quality. She brought all of her late-night study-focus tricks to bear, but even she still found her attention wandering to the problem of her Transfiguration insights. Of course her housemates liking her wasn't as important as safety, but she still thought it unfair. And unfair to them as well, as they could be doing just as well as her if they had the right information. Maybe Professor McGonagall would let the other Ravenclaws sit in on their science tutoring?

The students jolted back to attention (or consciousness, depending) when the class bell rang. Professor Binns asked them to write fourteen inches on the establishment of the International Confederation of Wizards by next week and Hermione glanced suspiciously at her notes, unsure of whether she'd actually missed something, or if the ghost was giving them homework entirely unrelated to what he'd been lecturing on.

"Thank Merlin we've only got him once a week," sighed Daphne. "Much more napping would mess up my sleeping schedule."

"And we all know you need all the beauty sleep you can get," sneered Pansy. The bigger Slytherin girl was in fact considerably less pretty than Daphne, but the latter grimaced slightly and didn't offer a comeback.

Hermione absently noted the byplay and added it to her mental tallies of Slytherin behavior, but left the classroom without delay, heading straight for the library. She needed to get the information about suppliers for the Hospital wing and send owls, resume her reading on house elves and continue her efforts to make sense of Madam Pince's organization of the library, catch Professor McGonagall at some point to schedule their extra lessons and ask about including her housemates in them...

o-o-o

As she walked to the Owlery to post her letters, Hermione thought about what she'd read. The information about house elves sounded well-reasoned, but it didn't seem to be supported by any actual historical references. This in itself wasn't necessarily damning - witches and wizards didn't seem to use many footnotes or bibliographies in any of their books - but it did sort of remind her of early Classical philosophers, who tended to judge the truth of explanations largely by how they sounded. Once they found one that sounded "true", they stopped looking, even if there might have been other explanations that actually fit better. Hermione found it hard to imagine an elf coming up with what she'd read as something to do rather than a Wizard coming up with it to try to explain something that already was.

The bit about the clothes, for example. The very few modern wizards who'd chosen to write at all about house elves explained it as an exchange of loyalty and dependence. Clothes were, above a basic level of modesty and personal comfort, an expression of status. Since an elf properly bound to a house was considered simply an extension of the family's wishes, they had no need to display their own status, and given their size it wasn't hard to satisfy modesty with whatever happened to be lying around. Further, a loyal elf would always put her family's comfort above her own, plus spend most of her time in a comfortable home anyway. Clothes were thus obviously an unnecessary distraction, except in the rare case of an elf being dismissed (they did not use the term 'freed', Hermione noted). Though few wizards would apparently take on an elf so disgraced, it was judged a generous mercy that they be allowed to present their best face to prospective employers, which is why being presented proper clothing was the magical trigger for ending an elf's contract.

Hermione found herself dissatisfied with the situation, but at a loss for what to do about it. Particularly since the elves themselves seemed quite opposed to any efforts to change their conditions, or even to discuss them in that context. Maybe if they were just used to how things were, she could think of some way to get them interested, thinking about the possibilities?

Once her letters to potion ingredient suppliers were off on various owls, she went in search of Professor McGonagall's office, and after being forced to backtrack a couple times, she managed to locate it. As she was about to knock, Hermione noticed the schedule of office hours helpfully affixed next to the door, which indicated that the professor was currently teaching sixth-year NEWT Transfiguration. In fact, the only time before curfew that she wasn't teaching classes was Fridays between eight and nine in the evening, or the weekend. Hermione frowned, discouraged, and regretted not trying to catch the professor on her way out of the Great Hall after dinner.

"Miss Granger?" Hermione was not ordinarily a particularly jumpy person, but having just vividly imagined what Professor McGonagall might be teaching sixth-years at this very moment, when she heard the professor's voice behind her, she barely stopped herself from shrieking. The woman's lips twitched, but her eyes showed only concern. "My apologies, I didn't intend to startle you."

"It's not your fault, just the schedule…" she pointed over her shoulder, then wondered why the professor was here if she was supposed to be teaching, and trailed off in confusion.

"As a duty to my students, I do keep to that schedule, though it is not impossible to find me elsewhere, if I have other business," the professor explained. This did seem to make sense, though there was something about the way she'd said it that felt odd to Hermione.

"Oh, I can come again later if you're busy…"

"If you've come to work out when we shall be having our 'lessons', that certainly qualifies as 'other business'," noted Professor McGonagall, arching an eyebrow. Hermione nodded, and followed her into the office, taking a seat.

"I think, given my other duties, it shall have to be weekends, though I suppose if more time is required I could give you a note to allow you to visit my office after curfew." The girl blinked at this, but nodded again.

"I'm not sure how to go about this, Professor...I've helped people of course, but I've never officially tutored anyone before. I did bring some basic books for you to start with…" Hermione extracted three books from her bag, introductory texts on chemistry, biology and physics. Professor McGonagall accepted them, then flipped through the top one, blinking slightly at the small font size and color - but un-animated - photos and illustrations. "You'll need at least some basic maths...are you familiar with algebra and statistics?"

At the professor's blank expression, Hermione began to worry, but some brief back-and-forth established that Arithmancy did cover similar bases, though with some differing terminology.

"Here is my suggestion, then," said the professor. "Each week, I shall read a chapter from each and take notes of any concepts which seem confusing or unfamiliar, then we can meet and you can attempt to clarify matters. After a session or two, it should become clear how much time we will require, and whether more than one meeting per week is indicated."

"That seems sensible, though I wondered if it would be possible to include the other Ravenclaws as well?" The professor frowned.

"I should think not...at least until I have a sufficient grasp of the material to gauge its dangers." She noted Hermione's slightly crestfallen expression with a weighing look of her own. "Why do you ask?"

"I really do like showing other people what I've learned, and they were asking. But you'd said not to, and...some of them think I'm not sharing deliberately, so I can...look better than them." Even as she felt the injustice of it anew, Hermione also felt a bit guilty, saying it out loud. Knowing things other people didn't had always made her proud, so much so that it was hard to resist showing. But she'd never imagined trying to keep other people down...not that she'd ever really had peers, much less significant rivals...there'd really been no one to keep down. On the contrary, she'd often wished she knew people who found everything as interesting as she did.

"Did you not explain to them the prohibition I'd given you?" Hermione shook her head.

"It's...well, I've noticed that classmates sometimes...don't like it if someone is too friendly with the teacher?" The professor pursed her lips.

"I am familiar with the concept, Miss Granger, I was once a young student myself. But you might try giving your fellow Ravenclaws the benefit of the doubt...they are, after all, as eager to learn as you, and thus perhaps more willing than some to take a professor's judgement and instructions at face value?" Hermione nodded. She had to admit, this hadn't occurred to her at all. She wasn't exactly relieved - it did make her feel a bit better, but at the same time worse, because she'd assumed the worst of her housemates, possibly unjustly.

"Now, curfew is nearly upon us, but before you head to your dormitory, I would like you to try to explain your theory about Moira Leigh-Smith, making allowances for the fact that I have yet to even begin to gain what I presume is the proper context." Hermione blinked. It'd have to be very generalized...but it might also be useful...she'd always found learning even easier if she had some goal of understanding she was working towards. The professor waited patiently as the young Ravenclaw tried to choose the words to explain radioactivity without using any concepts more modern than the sixteenth century or so.

"Um. So, muggles have found certain...substances...that are, I guess you could say they're constantly Transfiguring themselves into something else...or no, not really, because they don't want anything, it's just happening, because...er...the way they are inside is unstable...like each tiny bit of the substance is a pile of salt on top of tiny circular pedestal...and when I say tiny bit I mean much tinier than a single grain of salt...and if there's too much salt it spills grains off of the edges? That's actually a pretty good analogy, because, well, these substances, as they change, they cast off little bits of...not themselves, exactly, but other substances, or sometimes just energy...and anyway, those substances can, when they hit certain other substances, or even sometimes the air, cause a glow. But they also can do really bad things to, ah, the smallest parts of a living creature, and worse if the original substances get somehow taken inside first. And until fairly recently those bad parts weren't really common knowledge, so I could see someone maybe trying to do that if they'd only sort of understood it…" Hermione trailed off, and watched the professor hopefully.

Professor McGonagall's eyes flicked down to the books, and for the briefest instant Hermione thought she might've seen trepidation in the woman's face, but if she did it was quickly buried under firm, if perhaps grim, determination.

Chapter 9: Independent Study

A/N: Thanks to torac for pointing out a word-drop mistake in Chapter 8, and feepingcreature, who introduced me to FF dot net's endearing abhorrence for links, even to itself, and RMcD94 for correcting my flub on "How to Win Friends and Influence People" and stringless for another typo. Apologies again to Enoket, I've updated the author's note at the bottom of Chapter 5 (where I'd said I'd reveal it in Chapter 6) so people aren't expecting the answer to the riddle right away.

Also, sincere apologies for my lack of updates for so long. Life gets in the way and all that, but I swear I'll keep at this doggedly until it's at least one complete-ish story, I just can't guarantee a particular schedule. Thanks to everyone who has continued to offer encouraging reviews and PM's in the interim, it really keeps my spirits up.

Edit: Thanks to ZeroNihilist for the Brit-pick (missed a "mommy") and who noted that only the movies were sexist/stereotyping, and in canon Beauxbatons is not an all-girls' school!

o-o-o-o-o

Chapter 9 - Independent Study

Hermione sat at one of the library tables, her papers spread out across more than half the available surface. Her list had grown long enough that, along with her cumulative notes on each topic, it now took up a great many sheets of parchment. She'd even had to go into her trunk for some of her extra sheets, which she originally hadn't expected to need for at least a couple more weeks - she made a mental note to owl-order more. She'd tried to keep the first page relatively clean, though - as a sort of table of contents - and once again glanced over it, trying to confirm what was most important.

~Architectural Charms? Or entirely alternate physics around enough magical activity?

~Goblins - why can't they just make their own wands? Another Secrecy Statute?

~Teleportation? (Disapparition/Apparition)

~Electronics fail around magic. Electricity in general? But what about biological electric fields?

~Incantation pronunciations - "original" Latin? Why Latin and not Greek?

~How are spells constructed?

~Classmates' pre-hogwarts education

~How does the Sorting work?

~Why is Slytherin being pre-poisoned?

~Ghosts?

~Book - "Hat's Off" (ref back to sorting) - who mentioned that, a fourth year boy?

+House Elves - Slaves? History - origin of binding magic, servitude?

+Potion ingredient supplier(s) - purity/cleaning?

~Science education for Prof. McGonagall - adult teaching methods/teaching in general

~Owls - intuitive navigation? Understand English? Are they just a magic sub-species, or are all owls like this, and if so, how? Secrecy Statute again? Owls understand laws?

Her work with Professor McGonagall was probably of the most immediate significance, but she wasn't sure what she could do there. She hadn't read and or brought any proper books on how to teach complex subjects, and the Hogwarts Library hadn't been much help there either - if the Professors used books to help improve their teaching methods, they seemingly hadn't obtained them here. Though she found it hard to be certain of that, given the horribly inefficient organization of the Library. There was the Restricted Section, but she couldn't think of an obvious reason at the moment why abstract educational theory would be in there.

Again, she thought, if she could find some way to improve that situation, then everything else ought to become much simpler...which just reaffirmed her earlier determination that an effort towards library efficiency was the best thing she could do now.

Hermione slid over a fresh sheet of parchment and began mentally reviewing all the spells she'd seen so far, in the Standard Book of Spells (Grade 1 and 2), Practical Household Magic, and incidental discussion in classes or with other students - noting down any that related to finding, fetching, organizing. Even if there wasn't anything immediately suitable (which she didn't think there was, or she could've used it to help find Neville's toad), maybe she could start to see patterns in spell elements and make some headway on spell construction.

~Reminder Charm - plays short voice "recording" up to 3 hours later - memory storage, timing

~Housewitch's Secret - Copies down recipe used to prepare a dish (provides spell names, but not instructions or potion ingredients, ref. "Scarpin's Revelaspell"?) - analysis, decomposition

~Packing Spell (advanced) - Moves a large number of belongings into a container (but does so with most efficient use of space possible) - satisficing

~Amnesia Detection Charm - Makes you glow if you've forgotten something (but doesn't tell you what, which sort of makes sense, except how, then?) - self-telepathy + consistency? "divination"?

~Place-setting Charm - Sets out tableware properly for the desired number of guests - patterning, partitioning

~Intruder Charm - Sounds alarm if "intruder" enters area, can distinguish between individuals? - identification/classification

~Assembly Charm - Assembles something if all the proper parts are present (even if caster does not know how, manually?) - patterning

~Repairing Charm - Reassembles something, if all of the proper parts are present - patterning

~Four-Point Spell - Points wand north (which? Surely not magnetic north?) - gyro- or magneto-metry or "divination", "sourceless" knowledge?

~Summoning Charm ~ Floats an item directly to you as long as there's an open path, even around corners. No firm distance limit, but depends on strength of casting, familiarity of item, size of item. Spell takes an "argument", like a Pascal function, in plain English - can be very specific or vague up to some unspecified limit, spell generally does what you intend - Location, navigation, comprehension(!), identification

She couldn't think of anything else at the moment, and considered what she'd gathered. The Summoning Charm really was shockingly flexible and useful, almost as if there was an intelligence behind it. But none of her reading thus far had suggested there were sapient intermediaries in the effects of any spells. Could it be borrowing the caster's mind somehow? It was a more advanced spell, but if she could manage to cast it just a few times, she might do some tests, see if she was slower at maths or something while the spell was operating. But something about the idea of an external agency, and the Place-setting Charm, kept teasing at the edge of her mind. Tablewear, tables...

Hermione's train of thought was interrupted as she noticed extra writing had begun to appear on her parchment, from the bottom of the page up, and furthermore upside-down. She stared. It wasn't as if it were being written by an unseen hand exactly, but rather each line fading into view...as if a temporary Disillusionment charm was gradually wearing off the ink. Which now that she thought about it actually seemed quite likely, considering recent events, but when she rotated the page around to read the words, she was no less confused.

but without deliberate effort? Send owl to Beauxbatons library to check, but how do I get a reply without alerting Y.H.? Buy owl, instruct it to wait for reply and then wait in Hogwarts owlery when it returns?

Next, what changed (not like T.T. - why)? O. knows something, but what? "Destiny"? Could owl him, but if he is willing to Obliviate, what else might he do? Also, too soon after I "arrived" for a butterfly effect. Could T.D. have also come, but earlier? And then N.T...and P.P. on the train…anything before that? After...

I'm so sorry, Poppy. My fault. Should deal with P.P., but Merlin help me, "damage is done", he's likely to just go back to hiding until he's forced out. Unless T.R. notices...and how could he not?

I can feel myself slipping, but even when she's asleep, it's so hard to even think clearly without risking pushing Y.H. out entirely. I may not have much time. Such irony, even D.R. would get it.

Just tell A.D. everything? Could save him, save a great many people, but still might provoke backlash, make things worse. Hold off for now, but also prepare for the worst - have to leave comprehensive notes somewhere secure just in case, try to limit damage to ~~ to ~~~

~~ test X X ~ test oh, honestly

The first theory that occurred to Hermione was that this was another, deeper level to the Weasley Twins' prank, though it was more bewildering than vexing, which did not exactly argue in favor of that explanation. Also, under the circumstances, including references to Madam Pomfrey seemed further than they were likely to go. Plus, by the time she'd reached the end, her heart was unaccountably fluttering in her chest, and she somehow knew that this was real, it was important. And it was dangerous.

Which was utter nonsense, she told herself. Knowledge came from evidence combined with logic. Where was either in these cryptic notes, or this mysterious alarm she felt? By all rights she should take this immediately to Professor Flitwick (or maybe Professor McGonagall, who had some relevant background information already even if she wasn't Hermione's Head of House), explain how they'd "appeared", and then let him handle it. If it was the Weasley Twins, she'd given them fair warning, and they deserved whatever came of it. If it wasn't, if her strange foreboding was somehow correct, then telling a responsible adult was also the right thing to do.

Hermione closed her eyes and took a few deep breaths, which is the first thing the best book on anxiety she'd read had said to do, when you suspected you were having a panic attack. Next was to acknowledge the situation. I am feeling fear. Fear is a signal of danger, fear itself can't hurt me unless I do something in reaction - unless there is real danger, in which case I should go somewhere safe. Even if my fear is illogical, it does not mean something is wrong with me, it just means some part of my brain is interpreting something differently than my conscious awareness. So. Is there danger?

She opened her eyes and looked at the parchment again, slowly, word by word. She felt a certain unease, but no immediate sense of panic. The first line is cut off. This is a continuation of another page of notes. Hermione quickly sorted through her other notes, and the other blank parchment she had with her, but nothing else showed unexpected writing. "without deliberate effort?" The writer is confused that something has happened spontaneously. Something that might be found in the library of France's premier magical school? Wait, they send owls as far as France? That seems- Hermione shook her head, interrupting herself. Don't get off track. "Y.H." Initials were used in various places, the writer did not expect the notes to be read, but wanted them to be unclear just in case. Do I know anyone with the initials Y. H.?

Hermione thought for a moment, but couldn't think of anyone, let alone someone who might be at Hogwarts and would be alerted by an owl. Still, she was feeling better, breaking things down, analysing, step-by-step. This was how you solved problems involving writing - an elevated heart-rate was helpful for running away from wild animals (and even then, only if you didn't know better), not for thinking.

But...why would anyone be alerted by an owl, since they (somehow) know whom to bring replies to directly? Does someone at Hogwarts monitor owl traffic? Some administration staff who isn't a professor and isn't mentioned in Hogwarts, A History? She frowned, and considered the next sentence. Is there a registry of owls in Hogwarts, who owns which? See if someone has recently bought an owl? Hermione made another brief note on a clean sheet, underneath where she'd already written "knowledge unique to Beauxbatons library?" and "Y.H.?"

Changed, she thought, upon re-reading the next bit. Something has changed, which is not like the writer would expect of "T.T." Again she couldn't think of anyone by those initials except Tina Turner, which seemed quite unlikely - unless she was secretly a witch? - and the only other thing that came to mind was "Triwizard Tournament", which also didn't seem to make any sense in context.

O. knows something, but what? Provided with the clues "single initial, one name or well-known" and "starts with O", Hermione's memory immediately answered, "Ollivander". The wandmaker had certainly seemed very mysterious and knowledgeable, so she supposed that might imply he knew things you wouldn't expect? Things about...whatever it was the writer was concerned about, but even she isn't sure what those might be.

She read the next word, and once again her heart started racing. No. Stop. It's just a word. It's not even a word that describes a concept I believe in at all. But for all her mental insistence, her fear rose, and her gaze flicked along the paragraph, bouncing in a frenetic triangle between "O.", "Destiny" and "Obliviate". She closed her eyes again, but before she could try to even begin taking deep breaths, she felt a sudden dizziness, and then she saw.

"Hermione Granger," she said, after offering her hand politely. At her name, the man stiffened slightly in the act of shaking her hand. Huh?

"Just so," he whispered, in a strange echo of himself. For a moment he just stared at her, until Hermione began to shift uncomfortably, and he seemed to shake himself out of a daze. "Muggle-born, I see," he noted, glancing down at her clothes, "I suppose you've no hint of your ancestry...magical, that is?" Hermione shrugged. Is it just me, or...

"If anyone in our family has known about magic, they certainly never mentioned it to us - we were all quite surprised - though it sounds like they would've been expected to keep it to themselves?" The old man nodded, then began to peruse the shelves, muttering to himself. Ollivander was acting peculiar - or more peculiar, rather - this isn't how I remember this happening. Have I already changed things somehow?

"No, no...no...I know it's here somewhere." He moved further into the shop and climbed most of the way up a ladder, craning his neck to examine more out-of-the-way boxes. "Have to try it of course, after so long…ah." The old man stretched an arm up to extract a box from a shelf near the ceiling, then clambered back down to rejoin Hermione. The box was actually itself made of wood, carved with intricate vines. He slid back the lid and withdrew a delicate-looking wand of a pale tan wood. "Muggle-born...which hand do you write with?" he asked. He knew which wand was hers, on the first try? And what was that odd wooden box it was in? This isn't right at all.

"Right," said Hermione, raising that hand. Ollivander extended the wand to her, thick end first. It had been intricately carved, making it seem as if six vines had twined around each other to form the shaft. She took the wand gently, her fingertips nestling easily into the gaps in the carving, and at the man's urging motion, waved it through the air. Immediately the tip gave off white sparks. That part is familiar, at least...

"Now the left," he said, leaning forward slightly. Hermione obediently switched the wand to her left hand and waved it similarly. This time, a thin line of blue vapor trailed behind the wand's tip, swirling slightly in the air. Ollivander's eyes widened. "There it is, then," he whispered. Hermione gave the wandmaker a somewhat vexed look. That came from me, not her! What in Merlin's name is going on here? How can he possibly-

"Um. I have to ask, because you keep whispering like that, and you seemed to recognize my name...is there something unusual about me? Or this wand? It seems quite old, but it looked like you picked it out specifically, and Professor McGonagall said that buying a wand can sometimes take a long time, which - along with the old saying you mentioned - implies I might have to test a few out, like shoes, only this one does seem to have worked quite well on the first try, which means you expected it would work for me in particular for some reason…" Well, look at you being all sharp on the uptake. You tell him, girl.

Ollivander regarded her for a moment, clearly weighing his words, then nodded to himself, seeming to come to a decision, and shrugged.

"'Unusual'? I couldn't say - we are each unique in our own way, are we not? But to be sure, you are meant for that wand...among other things. You have a destiny, Hermione Granger. But I think that if you knew it in full, you might not necessarily fulfill it as naturally." His words dripped with meaning and portent, but also a sort of absent casualness. Now honestly, that's just over-the-top, even for-

"I really need to know what all of that means, absolute top of the list, right now. And if this is just some sort of terribly elaborate sales pitch, I shall be very cross and ask Professor McGonagall to help me buy a wand somewhere else," said the girl, crossing her arms and attempting to sound stern, though there was a note of pleading in her demand as well. Yes, what she said, doubled! The old wandmaker shook his head and withdrew a gnarled dark wand from his robes. Wait, what's he-

"I have little doubt you will learn...everything in Time, Miss Granger. But it will not have been now, nor from me," he intoned. Merlin, he's going to Obliviate you! Protego, dodge, do something you little idiot! A bright flash issued from the tip of Ollivander's wand-

Hermione found herself on the floor beside the chair, nearly hyperventilating - she'd apparently shoved herself away from the table to try to get away from the flash, but there was no flash, no Ollivander, she was just in the Library, libraries were safe, libraries were where things made sense.

Were supposed to make sense, anyway.

A trio of nearby Gryffindors were staring at her, but after a shared shrug, went back to their own studying. Hermione stood and straightened her robes, calmed her breathing, then deliberately sat back down.

What? she thought, somewhat desperately.

Some part of her that wasn't still spinning around dizzily hesitantly offered the opinion that she'd just remembered something, and which the close of strongly implied the whole thing had been magically removed and replaced with something else. Which she knew was possible, because there was a whole profession in the Ministry devoted to doing it to muggles. Except...that's not quite right, is it? That is, that's obviously not how I originally - or still, come to think of it - remember things, but what just happened now felt like...it wasn't happening to me, but I was watching...or watching someone else watching, because someone was thinking things about what was happening and those weren't my thoughts, but…

This line of "reasoning" crashed in a messy heap. For a moment, Hermione considered the possibility that she was, in fact, mentally unwell. If that was the case, she wasn't sure if there was anything useful she could do other than mention the possibility to someone qualified to diagnose such things, because if she was actually having delusions, how could she trust any of her own conclusions about them? Aside from the panic, and the admitted fuzziness around certain memories, she didn't feel like her thoughts weren't working right, but it's not as if she had anything else to compare them to.

She decided to keep turning herself over to Nurse Wainscott in mind as a fallback option, but explore other explanations for at least a little while first. In that vein, one bit of the "memory" stuck out...the watcher's reaction to Hermione's wand producing a different effect when it was in her left hand...something like "that came from me, not her". Which seemed to imply the watcher had been not just watching, but present...in Hermione… She slowly turned her head to look at her main List, and her eyes caught on the shortest line. She looked back at the cryptic notes, and she finally recognized something she really ought to have earlier.

They were in her own handwriting.

Hermione went very still, and wished she was better at knowing what research to prioritize, though honestly she wasn't sure how she could've been without actually knowing the future, and reading between the lines of some of the extra reading she'd bought, Divination in Magical Britain was viewed by serious people only slightly more favorably than it was by muggles. But there was no helping that now, so what should she do? She felt an urge to directly quote the relevant bit from the first Dirk Gently book - which had partially inspired her current theory - but she didn't trust herself not to flub it, and this really wasn't the time anyway, so she paraphrased.

"My mind is not just a thing my brain does," she whispered. "It is who I am. If you've some unfinished business or something that sharing my body can help with, I'm not necessarily opposed to that - though you might've asked first. I don't know what you and Ollivander have going on between you - it didn't seem like you were cooperating, exactly, but he apparently didn't erase your memories, did he? But when a part of my mind is destroyed, a version of me is effectively killed, and all the thoughts that might have come from her. It's not murder, but it's a difference of degree, not kind. So whoever's possessing me, if you've any decency at all, I'll ask you kindly to show yourself."

Hermione waited uneasily. Throughout this little speech Hermione had done her best to hold her voice steady - but there'd nevertheless been a bit of quaver - she still knew almost nothing about how ghosts really worked, and that uncertainty terrified her. Which maybe whatever was possessing her knew already, if it was in her head, but if it didn't there was no sense in making things easy for it.

For a moment, nothing happened.

The nothing continued in the next moment, and the moment after that, until it seemed clear that the dramatic appearance of a ghost was not in fact in the offing. It was certainly possible she'd been wrong about that, though the theory did seem to fit the evidence. The question was, could she risk doing some quick (if belated) research on ghosts to bolster that theory, or was this enough evidence that the situation was serious and she should go to an adult immediately?

The answer was often obvious when the question was asked the right way.

"Ok. I'll just have to get someone more knowledgeable about ghosts to help," she said, quietly. There was no particular reason to have said that aloud - she'd done it on impulse, as another experiment, but not particularly expecting any reaction.

At which point Hermione felt an immediate, irrational dread that if she told anyone, it would cause horrible, awful things to happen. She mentally planted her feet and clamped down on the reaction. Hermione was no stranger to occasional anxiety - thus having read up on it - she often analysed things to a degree that made her promote objectively unlikely scenarios to conscious consideration. But in all of those cases, the worries were irrational because the chances of them happening were very low, not because she had no logical reason to worry at all. Yet this feeling had no chain of logic, no train of thought attached to it, it just was.

But the feeling had to come from somewhere, and given she was already considering the existence of a separate...call it "mind"...inside her, Occam's razor suggested a single explanation was more likely (though a part of her felt dirty about invoking Occam's razor to argue that "a ghost did it").

"Is that you?" she whispered. "If it is, and you can't show yourself...do something else. Have a happy feeling instead of being afraid, maybe?" She waited, but nothing happened. Maybe ghosts, being dead, just couldn't be properly happy? Though the ones she'd seen so far seemed relatively genial, at least. "I'm sorry, but if you can't give me actual reasons, I really have to tell someone about this." Hermione stood up and began to gather up all her notes from the table.

The dread intensified, and it might have been her imagination, but perhaps mixed with a bit of frustration, now? Despite Hermione's determination to do the sensible thing, and increasing conviction that these feelings were not her own, her hands were shaking quite badly by the time she'd stowed everything away in her bag. Her rationalizing faculties instinctively began to look for ways to stop the unpleasant sensations, and unbidden, seductive and unverifiable scenarios started playing in her head.

Suppose the strange non-memory she'd experienced had really happened, and Ollivander had been protecting her, because there really was such a thing as "Destiny", and...there were people or creatures who could read minds, and if they knew, she would be in danger. Or maybe she'd somehow unknowingly blundered into a Dark Curse when she'd been looking at books in Diagon Alley, and this feeling was her sole warning, and if she did tell someone they would be hurt, and it would all be Hermione's fault for not reading enough first? Or…

Even while her mind filled with one increasingly implausible justification for delay after another, she slowly, stubbornly, continued to make her way through the stacks toward the Library's exit. That's what being responsible meant, you did what was right even if it was hard, or uncomfortable.

She felt a surge of frustration and grew dizzy, pausing to steady herself against a bookshelf. Her vision swam, and for a moment she was-

Hermione pulled up the covers of her new bed at the top of Ravenclaw Tower and started the relaxing routine that was the only thing that kept otherwise chronic insomnia at bay. Every night, as soon as her head hit the pillow, sleep always seemed to be the furthest thing from her mind, in favor of going over everything she'd learned and read that day. But she'd practiced structured relaxation as diligently as she approached anything else until it was second nature, and soon her eyelids were drooping…

Hermione blinked. Another memory...but there wasn't anything different about that one, it was just as it had been the first night after arriving at Hogwarts, what did-

The letters of the CRT monitor grew blurry, and Hermione rubbed at her eyes automatically. She'd been taking notes from her Hogwarts books on the Amiga for ease of searching in the short term, though she knew already that she couldn't take it with her, more's the pity - she'd have to print everything out before she left. But at night she always stopped using the computer and went to bed at the very first sign of eye strain - she took her vision very seriously, because stressing her eyes to the point where she'd need glasses and make it harder to read for the rest of her life wasn't a good deal on balance no matter how tempting it was to read "just one more page"…

It wasn't just dizziness now, her whole body felt heavy and weak and only a firm grip on the bookshelf kept her from dropping to the floor. "If you're trying to communicate, I don't understand," she murmured, surprised at how slurred her words sounded-

She was so hot, she wasn't under the covers, and her nightgown was soaked with sweat. But more than that, she was afraid, because she'd read about fevers and if they were high enough they could cook your brain and you might not think right afterward, and also you might die, but the first thing scared her more because if she couldn't think right, she just wouldn't be her, it'd be like someone else pretending, in her body, and mummy and dad would think it was her but be sad because she wasn't smart anymore...

"I know it's awful, sweetie, just try to close your eyes?" She felt a blissful coolness for a moment as mummy put a fresh wet washcloth over her forehead. "You just need to rest, sleep will help you get better." Mummy knew what to do, because even though she only fixed teeth and not whole people, she'd still gone to school for ages and knew practically everything, so Hermione closed her eyes and let mummy's soft words fill the rest of her head with a different kind of coolness, but just as nice as the washcloth…

With a dull sense of alarm - the dullness of which was itself alarming - Hermione realized this wasn't an attempt at communication. It was the middle of the day and it was putting her to sleep. But she found she'd already sat down against the bookshelf and couldn't summon the strength to rise. She reached into her bag for her wand, but she knew you couldn't use an awakening spell on yourself...maybe she could make a loud noise and attract someone's attention. She tried to remember the wand gestures that accompanied Sonorus, and closed her eyes for just a moment to picture the illustrations in the book - and discovered, too late, that she'd just forfeited.

Chapter 11: Perspective

o-o-o-o-o

Chapter 11 - Perspective

Hermione, as she slowly walked to the Great Hall for breakfast Thursday morning, tried to determine what, if anything, she'd learned. She paid a bare minimum of attention to navigating - it had only been three days, but even first-years of other Houses had learned the onus of avoiding collisions with students in blue-trimmed robes and an absent expression was on them.

When she had woken up in the hospital wing, she'd been somewhat surprised to discover that she had no trouble remembering everything from yesterday, the strange notes, the "memory" of Ollivander's, the disturbing glimpses "of the future". Or at least, she thought she had no trouble - she'd need to double-check her hurried notes to be sure. She'd tossed them out of the window in the hopes that her "uninvited guest" wouldn't be able to get to them under the watchful eye of Madam Wainscott. But the fact that she even remembered the notes existed in the first place suggested she hadn't been Obliviated. The potion, however, seemed to have been effective, as she remembered no dreams or additional "glimpses" (she refused to call them "visions", even to herself).

As soon as she'd dressed - her clothes and robes had been laundered and neatly folded, she'd discovered - she'd immediately gone out onto the grounds to check outside the window, but that part of her plan had worked as well - the notes were gone. Before tossing them out the window, aside from the Imperviuses in case of rain, she'd added a Reminder Charm in the hopes that the voice would attract the attention of someone outside, so if she had been Obliviated, there'd at least be someone who might be able to do something - the short personal note she'd added at the top had urged whoever found them to be cautious, to make a copy and give it to someone else before even attempting to talk to Hermione about it, and when they did to be subtle - if she seemed not to remember at all, they were to take her notes immediately to a Professor.

Of course, if that did happen, they might just discount it because of the hex misinformation, but she'd drawn specific attention in the notes to the Ollivander incident, which was past, rather than future, and wasn't as well-explained by some Cassandra-esque Confunding. They were, in any case, the best precautions she'd been able to come up with in the time she'd had. No one had attempted to contact her yet, even subtly, but that was equally plausible if whoever had found the notes was being cautious, or if they'd simply ignored or discarded them.

All this implied her guest had been either unable or unwilling to Obliviate her while she slept. Perhaps the potion had prevented her body from being borrowed, or Nurse Wainscott was too vigilant to risk it, or Hermione's precaution with the notes made Obliviating her too likely to be discovered, or it simply did not suit their plans, whatever they were.

It seemed, from a collection of things, that her guest had some concern for Hermione's welfare. Thinking back over the cryptic notes in her handwriting in that light, Hermione began to see a theory that might fit, though it was not one she enjoyed at all. Divination was one thing, but this…

The tenuous chain of reasoning started with a line that had gone something like, "I can feel myself slipping. It's hard to think clearly, even when she's asleep, without risking pushing Y.H. out completely." From the Library incident (and the existence of the notes in the first place), it appeared that Hermione's guest had more agency when Hermione was sleeping...which made a kind of sense, she supposed, if they were somehow sharing the same brain. Ignoring for the moment how impossible that was. But that made it likely the "she" in that line was Hermione herself. And though the notion gave her a shiver of dread to contemplate, the balance could be inferred that Y.H. was also her, and there wasn't enough room in her brain for both of them...and there was an ongoing risk that one or the other would be "pushed out".

But the context also implied that her guest didn't want that. That, along with other bits of the notes - expressing regret about Madam Pomfrey, talking about "saving people" - suggested rather strongly that her guest had morals at least similar to Hermione's, even if they weren't being terribly nice about trying to follow them.

Next there was the "commentary" on Hermione's "memory" of Ollivander's. It was a lot harder to remember the exact wording, as it hadn't been visual or even verbal, more like a memory of thinking. But it, too, implied that her guest had some concern for Hermione's welfare, hadn't wanted her to be Obliviated. And also that her guest, even then, was thinking in terms of changes and remembering.

Then there were the "glimpses", of apparent futures, the only common elements being something extremely unpleasant, and that they all featured an older version of herself. But if they hadn't come from some weird Confundus, where else could they have, other than her guest? Again, if they were sharing the same brain, even if direct communication might not be possible, it didn't seem implausible that there might be some "leakage" in either direction.

All of which added up to a conclusion that, even tenuous as it was, Hermione would've called obvious, if it hadn't been so blatantly impossible. There had been nothing in her reading that suggested such a thing was magically plausible. But, aside from insanity, it was the only solution that seemed to fit. Even Madam Wainscott's attempts to detect Hermione's guest fit - she'd said, "there's nothing in your head that didn't originate from your own mind", and Hermione stressed the last bit in her head as she recalled it. If she wasn't Confunded, how could her mind be her own, and yet not, at the same time?

Her guest was herself. But a later version, "Older Hermione". And from her perspective, Hermione would of course be "Younger Hermione"...Y.H.

Which, if she accepted the impossible theory as true for the moment, meant Hermione had to reconsider all of her decisions in light of the fact that an older, more experienced version of herself thought it was for the best that Hermione didn't tell anyone about any of this, even very experienced, responsible Professors. And then Hermione had written everything down and tossed it out a window in the specific hope that a random person would pick it up and read it.

The term "embarrassment" didn't really cover it.

The only things keeping her from falling into an oscillating spiral of self-beratement and gibbering panic were that she wasn't sure she was right about this, and even if she was, her guest didn't seem to know what was going to happen, she just expected it to be dangerous, bad, or both. But even the latter was in the context that O.H. seemed surprised about what specifically had happened, but not about the fact that it involved some form of time travel.

Hermione was broken from her introspection not by the sound of breakfast in the Great Hall, which she'd anticipated, but by the change in the sound as she entered, not dropping in volume exactly, but lowering in tone. She looked up, and saw that at least a third of the students were looking at her, not just a casual glance at someone entering, but watching, while they talked to adjacent students.

Even while her heart fluttered from the unwanted attention and whatever it implied, Hermione steadfastly ignored it and walked directly to an open seat at the Ravenclaw table. She could just immediately ask what all this was about, but this was the Ravenclaw table, which meant all she had to do was count to-

"So what was the-"

"Who actually-"

"Do you remember-"

Hermione couldn't properly make out all the words as several of her housemates began asking different questions simultaneously, before her mental count had even reached "one". She held up one hand peremptorily and used the other to select a croissant and a couple other bland items she thought her churning stomach could tolerate.

"One at a time, please," she said. "Mandy?" she prompted, nodding at one of her interrogators.

"Do you have any idea who hexed you?" the girl asked, a little breathlessly. Hermione considered her answer, but decided to leave things as they were for the moment.

"No. I don't even remember it happening." It was technically true, anyway. Hermione picked up an unused glass and gestured it towards Anthony to go next, then began to pour herself some water. He paused for a moment, probably mentally adjusting to the new information that Hermione didn't remember it happening, which rather limited the scope of useful questions.

"The Nurse let you go, so you must be okay now, but you were in the hospital wing, so it had to be bad...what was it exactly?" Hermione, again, wasn't sure how to answer that.

"Why don't you tell me everything you - and everyone, apparently - does know about this, and also how you know it, and then I'll be better able to fill in the blanks?" 'Able to' doesn't technically mean 'willing', she thought, and suddenly recalled Tonks' grinning face on the Hogwarts Express. But before she could smile, the memory was just as quickly replaced by an image of the Hufflepuff's body, ashen and still, and Hermione's mouth twisted instead, in synchrony with her stomach. Anthony hesitated, perhaps taken aback by her expression, but Marietta, a few places further down, stepped in efficiently.

"Professor Dumbledore made an announcement at dinner last night. He said that a first-year had apparently been the victim of a very powerful hex, and that while the hex was not, strictly speaking, Dark, ah, 'such an egregious and inappropriate misuse of magic will not be tolerated' - he can look quite stern if he wants to, you know. Then he said the Professors would be making pointed inquiries, but if the 'offending party' chose to come forward privately, before they were identified, it would weigh in their favor..." Hermione was gratified to learn that the staff would take some infractions seriously, though she felt bad about Professors possibly wasting their time searching for a culprit that did not exist.

"That was about it," Marietta continued. "He didn't say who had been hexed, but there were only a few people missing from dinner, and the only one who didn't turn up after was you, so Q.E.D."

"Not really," objected Penelope Clearwater faintly, from three times further down the table. "There's nothing that says even a powerful hex had to cause an overnight stay in the hospital wing - the victim might've already recovered and actually been at dinner." That end of the table devolved into a heated debate on induction vs. deduction, quickly moving rather beyond the immediate matter at hand. All the first-years still waited expectantly for Hermione to elaborate.

She chewed slowly to give herself more time while she thought. Hermione didn't want to lie, or even withhold information, particularly after (mostly) resolving the whole Transfiguration secret-keeping drama. And if it had been someone at the Ravenclaw table who'd found her notes, they'd know she wasn't being honest. But if her guest's apparent concerns were valid, she might not be doing anyone who heard any favours, depending of course on what exactly the problems with time travel were.

"I was in the Library, and I felt strangely tired, and the next time I was awake I was in the hospital wing. I don't remember anyone hexing me, but Nurse Wainscott believes a hex made me confused, and also see things that weren't true. But before you ask, no, I'm not going to say what I saw, because if they're not true they don't matter, and she specifically said I shouldn't even think about them." All true, and yet so misleading and incomplete that Hermione felt dirty, like she'd cheated on an exam, or something equally unthinkable. Still, even if it likely hadn't really satisfied anyone's curiosity, it seemed to have forestalled further questions on the topic - everyone went back to eating and random conversation. With one exception.

"All this is impressively distracting, but don't think we won't remember tae ask Professor McGonagall in class this afternoon about what ye claimed," said Morag, quietly. For what seemed like the dozenth time, Hermione wondered why the other girl seemed so eager to challenge her at every opportunity. She considered just asking, but decided to wait - it didn't seem likely to help the situation while Morag still thought she had a valid grievance, and the next Transfiguration class would finally clear that up at least. In the end, she just sighed, and nodded.

Morag nodded as well, with a grimly satisfied smile.

o-o-o

All the first-years had a free period Thursday after breakfast, and Ravenclaws the period before lunch as well. Most wandered away from the Great Hall towards their respective common rooms, or just off to explore the castle a bit more. A few headed towards the Library to actually study, or finish up any coursework - most students and even Professors still called it 'homework' at Hogwarts, even though no one went home to do it, excepting holidays.

Hermione was left trying to figure out a good way of communicating with her guest. Obviously she was able to write - and even speak, based on what Nurse Wainscott had said - while Hermione was asleep. So simple parchment, or alternating Reminder Charms if they wanted to be careful and avoid leaving evidence, would seem to suit. But her older self had to know that too, and she hadn't communicated, or at least not deliberately. Maybe now that Hermione had learned so much anyway, things would be different? But even if it were, it would be like having a pen-pal, only exchanging one "letter" each night, which wasn't very efficient, and her guest's notes had implied their time 'together' might be short, one way or another.

She knew from very recent personal experience that magical sleep was possible in at least two different forms - if she could find one that was reliably of short duration, they might be able to have a reasonably efficient conversation. Assuming, again, that her guest was willing now, when she hadn't been before…

Hermione made her way back to the hospital wing. When she arrived, she found the nurse dictating inventory, to a quill that was apparently both Self-Inking and Self-Writing, as it was dancing across a nearby scroll in response to her words.

"Madam Wainscott?" Hermione asked hesitantly.

"Miss Granger, I didn't expect you back so soon, are you- no, cancel, cancel!" Her concerned greeting to Hermione was cut off as she realized her quill was continuing to transcribe, and turned to address it instead, until it stopped. "Sorry, these things are never as smart as you'd like them to be, are they? Are you feeling any additional ill effects, I was going to ask?" Hermione shook her head.

"No, my stomach was a bit upset at breakfast, but I think that's to be expected with all that's been going on. And I should thank you again for the potion, I think that's the best night's sleep I've had since school started. In fact, that is actually why I came." The Matron (or perhaps Acting Matron? The Headmaster had said she was taking over Madam Pomfrey's duties, but not specifically her title...) gave a little frown.

"I'm sorry, but the potion I administered yesterday is to be used sparingly, for emergencies only. It isn't safe for repeated use." Hermione's eyebrows rose.

"Oh? I still haven't had Potions yet, but I hadn't read anything about cumulative toxicity…" The nurse blinked.

"It's not that...it's that, well, whether you remember them upon waking or not, dreams are necessary for healthy sleep. A sustained lack of dreams can cause poor health, or even forms of madness, eventually."

"Oh, right, I actually knew that, it just hadn't occurred to me." Now it was Madam Wainscott's turn to raise her eyebrows. "I read it in a muggle book - they actually know a fair bit about biology and medicine...they rather have to, since they don't have magic," Hermione explained, somewhat pointedly. The comment didn't seem to make the woman less skeptical. "But anyway, so it's not magical sleep itself that's dangerous, it's just dreamless sleep? Are there other convenient ways of promoting normal sleep, or even causing a quick nap? I do have diagnosed insomnia, I could try to get my parents to owl back a note from my doctor, I suppose, if you need some sort of verification…"

"Oh, you poor child, on top of everything? Well, there are lesser sleeping draughts, and a variety of Charms, of course, though those are probably a bit beyond what a first year can manage. I suppose I could brew up a small supply of Liquid Sheep for you, though you'd need to follow my dosing instructions precisely - it wouldn't do to have you waking up in the middle of the night, or sleeping straight through to Christmas. Come back either right after dinner, or after tonight's...gathering. I'll have some ready for you by then." Hermione felt a bit awful about the nurse's obvious compassion, given that she was misrepresenting herself. And also that the woman was expected to just carry on with her work, even with Madam Pomfrey's memorial tonight - Hermione assumed they'd been reasonably close, working together and all. But as far as sleep aids went, she did have diagnosed insomnia, so it wasn't exactly a lie, she just wasn't mentioning that she explicitly planned on subverting the dosing instructions for her own purposes.

"Thank you," she said, sincerely, but not nodding, since that technically might've counted as promising to follow the dosing properly. "...any means to achieve their ends…" came, unbidden, an echo of the Sorting Hat's song through her head. Shut up. That whole 'technically' thing came from a Hufflepuff, you know, so you can take your weird anti-Slytherin propaganda and foist it on someone else. And besides, this is extremely important. Hermione didn't actually think she was having a conversation with the Sorting Hat, though for a disturbing moment, it occurred to Hermione to wonder if the demonstrably telepathic artifact actually could use that ability at a distance? But after a tense moment of hesitation, no further mental intrusions presented themselves, exogenous or otherwise.

"I'll see you tonight, then," Hermione said quickly, after realizing she'd just been standing there and Madam Wainscott was starting to look at her oddly. She hurried off towards the Library.

o-o-o

Several hours later, Hermione's stomach felt no better than it had at breakfast as she quickly made her way to the Defence classroom. She'd had to add Time Travel (and Prophecy, just in case) and Sleep Charms, and Possession to the top of her List, and some of what she'd managed to learn had been exceedingly disquieting.

Prophecy, it seemed, was almost exclusively the province of Seers, who were apparently naturally gifted with their abilities (rather than as the result of any kind of dedicated study, which vaguely offended Hermione) via no obvious cause, though heredity was believed partially responsible. But it also seemed clear that a Seer never seemed to remember their own Prophecies, at least not true ones - they were more of a channel for information than a repository, as it were. Though there wasn't any useful information about the other end of that channel - most writers seemed to simply take it for granted that the Seer was drawing information through themselves rather than receiving something sent.

Time, Hermione had been surprised to discover, was mentioned, though never in a practical sense. It tended to come up in discussions of extreme magical mishaps - apparently people had been erased from Time (and yet somehow in a way that it was apparent it had happened). But the details were never discussed in depth because it was - and this was invariably mentioned alongside such references - due to various overlapping laws, more than 100% illegal to research Time magic, at least outside the Department of Mysteries. Aptly, what went on in there was left entirely mysterious - the people who worked there were literally called Unspeakables, Hermione had learned, with some unease.

But this directly implied that Time Travel was possible, or they wouldn't have made it illegal. And obviously dangerous, by the same reasoning. And yet before even coming to Hogwarts, Hermione had purchased and memorized the most current edition of the Legislative Guide to the Proper Use of Magic, and she certainly would've taken note of the possibility of Time Travel (as she had of the possibility of developing the ability to turn into a particular animal at will, which sounded delightful, but also difficult and dangerous beyond the practical benefits). But Hermione, despite her general confidence about things she'd read, always left room for fallibility on her part, so she'd dutifully pulled out her copy of the Guide, and double-checked.

Sure enough, there were a great many relevant statutes, nearly all of which carried mandatory terms in Azkaban, and Hermione had no idea how she'd missed that on her multiple readings. At least until she read a footnote noting that all published references to Time magic (including the entire relevant section of laws) were "Conditionally Obscured", such that to anyone who was not already aware of the existence of Time magic, the words appeared to be innocuous and redundant references to other material. The very concept of a spell which prohibited you from learning something unless you'd already learned it was just...just...it was similar to her feelings about Obliviation, honestly.

Even telling someone about the existence of Time magic without explicit written authorization from the Ministry was also illegal. Which had struck Hermione as being an extreme level of caution, to the point of possibly being self-defeating - what if someone independently discovered Time magic and then innocently (because they'd had no way to know they oughtn't to) went about developing it? But no, there were in fact regulations for spell researchers to explicitly, physically consult a current copy of the Guide before starting major projects and after any novel discovery. On top of all of that, all the relevant laws and regulations, like the Secrecy ones, were International Statutes, shared world-wide through a binding treaty of the International Confederation of Wizards. All in all, magical society had been terribly thorough and gone to tremendous effort, and it was certainly a strong implication about the dangers involved.

There had even been - but only in the laws restricting their use - mention of "approved" forms of Time magic. There were only two of them - which were really only one...apparently there was something called an Hour-Reversal Charm, which allowed a witch to travel physically back in Time one hour. But enchanted devices for producing the same effect were considered much safer, since the Charm was fiendishly difficult and unstable when cast manually. Even so, it was illegal to use the Charm or the devices, even in emergencies, for any purpose other than ones explicitly and individually authorized in writing by the Ministry on a case-by-case basis. It was illegal to attempt, by any combination of Reversals, to produce written works ex nihilo, to act upon any information gained therein prior to a point at which it could not have demonstrably been obtained otherwise without a Reversal, to attempt to cause any event or series of events to unfold in a manner other than what was previously observed to have happened, or to attempt to extend, suborn or otherwise bypass the Charm's inherent maximum scope of five hours.

At this point, Hermione was almost reconsidering her extremely poor opinions of Obliviation, as a practice. Technically, at this very moment, Hermione was breaking at least one law, simply because she had learned about Time magic through an unofficial channel, and wasn't immediately contacting "an authorized official of the Department of Mysteries". Plus there was the whole matter of her notes, which didn't explicitly mention Time Travel, but from the information in which she had eventually deduced it, so someone else might too, and she wasn't sure if that would count as her having told someone else. She tried to act as responsibly as she could on a daily basis, but she wasn't even twelve yet, these were unreasonably serious things for her to have to be involved in, and she considered it a matter of character to be very careful to obey all rules, let alone laws.

And though it was sort of overshadowed by the whole breaking international law matter, and possibly erasing people from existence, there was also what the Headmaster had apparently said, about the staff investigating her 'hexing'. It was probably a waste of their valuable time, or worse, if they mistakenly identified someone, and that person was punished, it'd be grossly unfair, which meant it wasn't just legally wrong for Hermione to remain silent, but to some degree morally wrong in an absolute sense. Though perhaps not ethically, if she ended up causing more harm by coming forward than she prevented by doing otherwise…

When Hermione arrived in the Defence classroom and took a seat mere seconds before third period began, to say she was agitated would be a considerable understatement. A number of students were looking at her oddly, and Padma actually leaned close.

"Are you entirely well? You look like you're going to sick up," she whispered. Hermione hadn't realized her inner turmoil was so outwardly visible, and made an effort to calm herself.

"I'm fine, thank you," Hermione whispered back.

"Are you sure? If you need to go back to the hospital wing, I can share my Defence notes with you later…" Which was probably the nicest offer a fellow student had ever made to her in her life. In her current state, an impulse of nearly desperate gratitude almost made Hermione want to take her up on it, but the Nurse wouldn't be able to help her with the actual problem until much later anyway, and stewing in the hospital wing might not be as helpful as distracting herself by actually learning things.

"Yes, I'm sure, but thank you, truly."

"Students!" came a surprisingly loud call from the front of the room. Many of the students who hadn't been paying attention, Hermione and Padma included, startled visibly. Professor Quirrell, as if taken aback by the reaction, lowered his voice excessively, to the point where it was necessary to strain to hear him.

"It..I have...that is, it has...been brought to my attention, that some s-s-students may be casting genuinely harmful magics on each other, for..ah...for s-sport? I have...some have said...I have heard that some say my c-classes have not included enough practical Defence, which isn't very fair since I'd only h-h-held two or three classes for any given s-s-student, and…" He continued speaking in a mutter too low to be made out, until one of the students near the front coughed loudly, causing the Professor to startle, once again as if surprised to discover he was in class.

"Accordingly," he said, and winced as he'd been much too loud again. He settled into a more reasonable speaking volume. "Accordingly, I will b-be adding additional instruction to the s-standard M-m-ministry curriculum. Unfortunately, there isn't m-much that first years can be taught without a solid f-f-foundation in Charms, but I shall d-do my best, starting with two spells that are the simplest c-c-counter-curses for a w-wide variety of lesser c-curses and j-j-jinxes - the Unlocking Spell, and the General C-c-counter-Curse. These spells are n-not normally taught until your s-s-second year, and you w-will not be required to c-c-cast them for your f-final exams...but I w-will mark you on effort during class." There was a general sigh of relief from nearly everyone but Hermione, who had already successfully cast both from her Standard Book of Spells, Grade 2 - Finite in particular had seemed like an important thing to know straight off if one was determined to practice magic frequently without a Professor present...she'd seen Fantasia, after all.

The Professor demonstrated The General Counter-Curse (which Hermione thought somewhat poorly named, as the spell could actually cancel a broad class of magics, whether or not they were unpleasant) several times while the class followed along. After, he had everyone divide into pairs, with one student either lighting their wand - if they could manage it, otherwise the Professor provided something similar that made the whole student glow softly - and the other trying to snuff it with Finite Incantatem.

Professor Quirrell had, for reasons he had not explained, segregated the pairings by gender, but mixed them by house, so Hermione found herself facing Tracey Davis of Slytherin. Hermione frowned, and wondered if he somehow thought girls were somehow not matched with boys, though she hadn't encountered any overt signs of a lack of gender equality in magical society. Though for all she knew it was because he was acting on boys' obvious propensity towards distraction. Or perhaps it was a policy he'd decided for older students, and was just staying consistent?

"So, how do you want to proceed?" Hermione asked absently, her expression still somewhat dark. The girl got a very queer look on her face for a moment, almost afraid, but when Hermione's features began to show confusion, her own expression suddenly cleared.

"Oh, right, um...I'll do the light first," she said, sounding oddly relieved. She couldn't think of a good reason the girl would've thought Hermione was angry with her, but she didn't know much about her in general, aside from the fact that she found disfiguring Transfiguration effects and baby-eating monsters interesting. Perhaps she'd simply assumed that Hermione would assume that whoever had hexed her was a Slytherin, and that Hermione would be indiscriminate in her reaction? Which seemed ludicrous - it's not as if she were a Gryffindor - but then not everyone thought these things through. Tracey managed to get her wand lit on the third try.

Hermione took a moment to review the spell mentally, checking her previous memory against what the Professor had just demonstrated. Hannah's insight that their books might not be entirely up-to-date seemed particularly apt here, since she was not actually in second-year Charms, and thus Professor Flitwick would have had no reason to give her any errata for the S.B.S. Grade 2. But they seemed identical. In fact, it occurred to her that the Professor's stutter and physical ticks seemed to vanish entirely when he'd been demonstrating actual spellwork, which was curious. Though she supposed if that hadn't been the case, they couldn't have really taken him on as a Professor, could they? She supposed public speaking and magical skill might just draw upon entirely different mindsets. Hermione focused back on the task and gave her wand the proper thrusting jab, with a smooth back-and-forth half-twist throughout.

"Finite Incantatem!" Tracey's wand obediently went dark.

"Excellent, Miss G-granger, two p-points to Ravenclaw for being f-f-first out of the gate," called the Professor haltingly, from across the classroom. Many of the Slytherins (and Morag) gave her dark looks, and Hermione considered the possibility that they might have a point...it's not as if anyone else had even really had the opportunity to practice the spell at all, though they could have bought the Grade 2 book as well, as she had. But she wasn't sure asking the Professor to revoke the points, and her accompanying explanation, would actually make anyone feel much better about it. Tracey, for her part, just looked impressed, and maybe a little scared again. Hermione tried not to frown, and instead just lit her own wand and nodded for the Slytherin to take her turn.

"Finite Incantatem!" Nothing happened. Hermione squinted at the other girl's hand position and motioned for Tracey to try again. "Finite Inc-"she started again, cutting off when Hermione held up a hand.

"You're only doing a half-twist, not a back-and-forth half-twist...you've still got to end up wrist-down at the end, you see?" Hermione demonstrated, and again Tracey gave her a peculiar look, but she nodded and tried again.

"Finite Incantatem!" Hermione nodded encouragingly, though her wand remained brightly lit.

"Almost, the motions were fine, but more accent on the 'ta', this time?" Tracey reset herself, and tried once more.

"Finite Incantatem!" This time Hermione's wand flickered, then went out, and Tracey beamed. Her smile grew even wider when the Professor awarded a point to Slytherin for Tracey being the second to successfully cast the spell, though it quickly wilted as she looked around. Hermione wasn't sure why - though their expressions were curiously muted, at least the other Slytherins weren't glaring at her as they had at Hermione, and the Ravenclaws only looked determined rather than angry. She thought there might be a glitter in Pansy Parkinson's eyes, though - maybe there was some Slytherin social convention she wasn't aware of?

As Tracey relit her wand - on the first try this time - and they began to trade spells back and forth, Hermione decided to distract herself from one world-shaking problem by exploring what might be another, if subtler one.

"So, I have a question," she began, cautiously. Tracey seemed to react entirely out of proportion, her whole body visibly tensing up.

"Go ahead," she said, in a tone Hermione imagined was normally reserved for speaking to one's own headsman.

"It's nothing bad, or at least, nothing that's your fault," Hermione reassured her. Again that queer look. "I just, I've been thinking about Hogwarts and the Sorting, and I just wondered...what is it like, being in Slytherin?" Once again, the girl seemed to let out a breath she hadn't realized she'd been holding. But her eyes narrowed suspiciously.

"Why?" Hermione was very curious about Tracey's attitude, but didn't want to upset her further, so rather than addressing it, she considered carefully how to word her response.

"It had occurred to me that Sorting is a hard problem, and I wondered if the Hat ever makes mistakes. But it's also possible that there really isn't all that much difference between the Houses, in which case it wouldn't be such a big deal. But I only know a bit about what goes on in Hufflepuff and Gryffindor, and none at all about Slytherin." While Tracey considered this, Hermione efficiently Finite'd the girl's light, then lit her own wand.

"It's...sort of like all of Hogwarts, with House points? Except every person has their own points, and you can't just look at the hourglasses to see how many there are, you have to guess based on how everyone else treats you. And people with more points than you can add points, and nearly everyone can take away points as long as someone else agrees with them - unless your parents are important and then maybe not - and it's not just schoolwork, it's every single thing you do or say or don't do or don't say." She'd lowered her voice conspiratorially - with a furtive glance towards Draco Malfoy when she'd mentioned 'parents' - and was somewhat out of breath at the finish, the words having poured out of her in a rush.

Hermione's mouth opened in horror, and then a little less horror as she realized this was actually an apt description of her own school experience prior to Hogwarts - if perhaps with a bit of additional classist prejudice added in - and then more horror again as she imagined what it would have been like to not be able to retreat to her own home, her own room, but instead to live like that, all the time. What would someone have to be like to come out of seven years of that not mad? And again, while according to popular reference more didn't than all the other Houses combined, the vast majority of them nevertheless did come out apparently sane, non-evil, non-Dark-Lords.

In that light, maybe the Hat's description of Slytherin was a more subtle test. Because you'd have to put up with a lot more to get along in that House - being called cunning or even ruthless was the mildest possible taste of what awaited you. But that still left the most fundamental question.

"Why?" Hermione breathed. Tracey gave her a long, thoughtful look, then shrugged.

"Why anything? I don't know, I've only really been a Slytherin for four days. But supposedly the Founders told the Hat to look for stuff they thought was important. I guess that Salazar must have decided that, even if students were miserable, or even went Dark...he wanted people who made it all the way through the House with his name, to be strong. To be survivors. Because you'd have to be, right?" They'd already been speaking softly, but the last words came out nearly inaudibly. She stared down at her wand, and Hermione felt such a swell of sympathy for the girl that she wanted to hug her, or hold her hand, or something.

But Hermione hadn't even taken a step forward, had barely shifted her weight, when Tracey's head snapped up and all of her earlier trepidation and uncertainty seemed to be replaced by firm, cold resolve.

"FINITE INCANTATEM!" she snapped, her pronunciation and wand motions perfect, and Hermione's wand light went out instantly, sending a sharp tingle into her hand and halfway down her arm. Hermione was literally taken aback, shuffling backwards a couple steps, so shocked was she at the Slytherin's abrupt emotional about-face.

"I...I'm sorry if I something I said…" she began, but Tracey just shook her head and lit her wand, waiting expectantly, her face carefully neutral.

They spent the rest of the class in silence that was broken only to exchange flawless incantations. The tension was obvious to the rest of their classmates - and the Professor - but no one chose to comment on it at that particular moment, or at least not in earshot of them.

o-o-o

When Professor Quirrell dismissed them, Hermione had intended to try to catch Tracey privately on their way to Transfiguration to attempt another apology and find out exactly what she'd done to so obviously upset the girl. But the Slytherin was first out the door, and once into the corridor, Hermione found her own way blocked.

"I need a word with you, Granger," said Theodore Nott, his thin frame somehow positioned perfectly so everyone else could pass by but Hermione couldn't quite join the flow to get around him.

"Excuse me...Mister Nott, I'd be happy to speak with you some other time, but right now-" she began, testily.

"Oh, I think you need to hear what I have to say...won't take long," he said, oozing confidence. At a small rustling sound, Hermione lowered her gaze from where she'd been looking slightly up into his eyes and saw he was holding several sheets of paper, folded neatly into quarters.

o-o-o-o-o

A/N: Hopefully the juicy bits at the end make up for all those crunchy wads of exposition up front. ;)

Edit: Thanks to /u/MonstrousBird for the brit-pick on "public" school meaning the exact opposite of what a bewildered American would expect!

Chapter 12: Leverage

A/N: Thanks to /u/karlitohomes for catching my several Padma/Parvati flubs...darn twins. And /u/eric1221bday for another (Hufflepuff vs Ravenclaw), and /u/4t0m for "sort have" *cringe*.

o-o-o-o-o

Chapter 12 - Leverage

"Oh, thank you for coming to me!" Hermione said, sincerely. "I'm sorry about being rather dramatic in the note there but there's no trouble really, so I can just take those back...and did you actually give a copy to someone like I suggested?" The Slytherin made no move to hand her the papers, only studied her thoughtfully.

"I can't tell you, obviously," he said quietly, after a moment. "That was the whole point, wasn't it? So that if whatever is possessing you does something to me as well, there'd be a third line of defense?" Hermione sighed. He was absolutely right, and it's exactly what she would've wanted him to do in her original plan...but now it just made things complicated. She wished, once more, that she'd thought things through a little better. "The question is," he continued, "is that actually what's going on here?"

"I...er...oh?" Hermione stammered, caught off guard and tensing up. Could he have somehow figured out the same thing she had, about her future-self? That could be even worse than just having read what was there. The boy smiled a little bit, at her reaction.

"Well, you're not possessed, for starters, I got that from the nurse."

"You...Madam Wainscott told you that?" Hermione was vaguely offended at the apparent breach of medical - or metaphysical? - confidentiality.

"I told her I was afraid for my own safety, considering what happened to Madam Pomfrey…'what if what happened to that first-year wasn't just a hex, what if some Dark spirit was doing things with her body? Who could be next?'" He smiled a little. "Not my best by far, but she's very eager to keep students healthy and happy...assured me up and down that she'd specifically checked for possession and ruled it out." Hermione's offense immediately reversed direction, as she imagined the nurse's kind nature being turned against her, and even bringing up Madam Pomfrey. In her mental notes on the Slytherin Question, she added a tick-mark next to "Nott, Theodore".

"So, the whole thing is definitely made up...either because you did get hit by some obscure hex I'd never heard of, or because you did it deliberately. Do you actually believe the things in there are going to happen?"

Hermione frowned at the direct question. She thought they might, but she wasn't sure. But she wasn't sure if she should even say. She didn't know Theodore at all, didn't have any sense of how he'd react to things, so trying to manipulate him was right out, even if she was good at that sort of thing, which she knew she wasn't.

"Not in the way I think you're asking. I mean, anything's possible, but...this whole thing with the notes was...well, I didn't think it through enough. May I please just have them back and we can pretend this never happened?" The Slytherin nodded thoughtfully, though he was not agreeing to her request.

"You're not insisting it's true, which could be because you made it up yourself, or the hex has just worn off and you're embarrassed. Anyway, I'm curious, but that's not really why we need to talk."

"I'm definitely embarrassed," Hermione mumbled.

"What you should be is concerned, if not outright terrified," continued the boy. Hermione didn't disagree, but she wasn't sure why he thought that, if he believed everything in the notes was made up…

"Why do you say that?"

"Well, for starters, you've made some serious allegations and implications about prominent people, here. Ollivander. The Malfoys. At minimum, you've opened yourself to charges of Defamation and Impugning the Honor of a Noble House. Maybe the hex excuse could get you off, if you could afford a good enough barrister or had powerful people willing to stand for you in the Wizengamot, but maybe not - they can't just accept everyone claiming 'I was Confunded' or 'I was under an Imperius', you know, or no one would ever be convicted of anything."

This sounded unpleasantly likely to Hermione...handling questions of legal responsibility when things like the Imperius Curse and Memory Charms existed was a sticky problem. Hermione had read about something called Veritaserum, which could make someone not lie, or even force them to volunteer true answers, but there was an apparently undetectable antidote, as well as other ways around it, including Memory Charms.

"Then there's the matter of Potter announcing the Dark Lord's return. If an actual Death Eater read that and thought there was even the slightest chance of it being a real Prophecy, well…" Hermione put her hands to her mouth in horror.

"They'd go after Harry," she breathed. Nott looked irritated and shook his head.

"No. Well, I mean yes, but they'd have done that anyway, Boy-Who-Lived and all that. I meant they'd come for you. They'd rip every scrap of information they thought might be useful from your mind, and then torture you to produce more prophetic details, torture your parents, torture your pets...they're very big on torture, you know. Not that there are supposed to be any Death Eaters outside Azkaban anymore, but relying on the Ministry to have not missed any...mmm. I certainly wouldn't." Hermione paled, and thought she might be sick. The vision where the crazed witch was torturing Hermione's older self...was this how that started?

"Wait...but all of this is only a problem if the notes get distributed! So you can just give them back, and get back any copies you made…" Hermione's eager solution trailed off as the Slytherin said nothing, the corners of his lips curling upwards ever so slightly. Hermione stared, uncomprehending, until she suddenly did. She found herself unable to say anything, even as some part of her mind was bitterly adding tick marks and checks and little dripping crosses beside "Nott, Theodore".

"I see you've finally realized the situation you put yourself in," said the boy, with considerable - almost theatrical - relish. Hermione had the bizarre impression that if he'd had a moustache, he'd have twirled it.

"What do you want?" asked Hermione, quietly.

"Do you know, I haven't decided yet?" he replied cheerfully. "I thought it'd be weeks until I had leverage like this on anyone, and only after loads of work. I'd rub it in Malfoy's face, but then he'd start digging for details, and that could be awkward, eh?" Nott winked. "But just stumbling across this little gem, literally begging someone to pick it up and read it...feels like I didn't really earn it, you know?" For a moment Hermione dared to hope that some twisted sense of - what, blackmail-pride? - would get her out of this, but her heart sank as he continued. "Not that I really have a problem with that. Beyond power and wealth and honor and all that, it's what being a pure-blood really means...that good things happen to people like me, and bad things happen to people like you." Hermione felt blood rush to her cheeks, hot, liquid shame. She knew she didn't even have anything to be ashamed of, her parents were wonderful, but somehow, she felt it all the same, like being bullied but a hundred times worse. Because it wasn't about how she acted, or dressed, though those were bad enough. Simply because of what she was.

Hermione thought of herself as a very, very, good person, which was why she found her sudden daydreams of very nasty things happening to Theodore Nott equally curious and shameful.

But not technically unpleasant, which on a deeper level made it even worse.

"I'm going to have to think about this some more," he said, finally. "Rest assured, I'll come up with something worthwhile, and meanwhile I'm confident the extra copies I made will be quite safe...and won't be read until the proper time." With that, he turned and began walking towards the Transfiguration classroom.

Hermione found her wand in her left hand, somehow, the tip aimed at Theodore's back, and beginning the complicated shape that started a Memory Charm. Which was insane, Memory Charms were awful, they ought to be Unforgivable, and even if she'd seen a couple performed - at least memories of them, rather - she hadn't practiced, she could get it wrong, she wasn't that kind of person-

The wand clattered onto the floor as she forced her hand to open, interrupting the spell. The Slytherin paused at the noise, slowly half-turned his head back. His eyes dropped to the wand, then back to Hermione's face. He smiled a little, then continued walking.

Hermione, hands shaking, picked up her wand and put it back in her bag, then slowly followed.

o-o-o

There were odd looks as Nott, and ten seconds later Hermione, entered the classroom just before the period was to begin, and a couple of whispers, which the Slytherin ignored and Hermione barely registered. Tracey Davis was in a back corner, looking less determined and more nervous again as Daphne and Pansy in adjacent desks whispered at her urgently. Whereas Morag seemed a bit surprised to see Hermione come in, but quickly covered it. Maybe since I was almost late she'd thought I was going to skip class? Hermione thought, dully.

She hurriedly took a seat as Professor McGonagall sharply tapped her wand on her desk three times, and the class quieted. But before the Professor could even say a word, Morag had her hand in the air.

"Yes, Miss MacDougal?"

"I just wanted tae ask...did you ask Hermione not to help us with Transfiguration?" Morag's expression seemed entirely innocent, but expectant. The Professor paused, and most of the Ravenclaws unconsciously held their breath.

"I did," she said, simply. There was an audible exhalation of relief, even amongst those who had professed to believe Hermione's explanation, but Morag's face went dark.

"Why?" she asked, and she'd dropped any pretense at innocent curiosity.

"That a Professor has given an instruction ought to be sufficient, Miss MacDougal," the Professor said primly, but continued in a more conciliatory tone. "All I will say for the moment is that Miss Granger has had an insight about Transfiguration, but one which I am not yet sure is safe to be disclosed. Once I have made that determination, I may lift the restrictions I've given her, or not, as appropriate."

"But that's not fair!"

"Miss MacDougal," said the Professor, warningly. She waited, and Morag glowered but said nothing, earning a nod from McGonagall. "There are many innate talents a witch may possess, or not, facilities for broomstick flying, or Charms, or Transfiguration, and these talents are generally not distributed fairly. In the long run, diligent study and practice almost always eclipses such inherent gifts. But regardless, be glad that in this case, Miss Granger's innovations may be something you can eventually benefit from, rather than something unique to her? I assure you that Miss Granger wanted nothing more than to share with the rest of the class, and is in fact undertaking additional work outside of class to explore making that possible." This caused a lot of the students, Slytherins included, to look at Hermione with an assortment of expressions, some baffled, some admiring, others thoughtful. The Professor paused again, and when there was no further interruption, began the day's lecture.

o-o-o

Hermione's determination to treat Slytherins without prejudice or prejudgement was at an extremely low ebb, so it was probably for the best that her first Potions class was with Hufflepuff. They would be the first first-years to have Professor Snape - Gryffindor and Slytherin had their first Potions tomorrow morning - so no one knew for sure what it would be like. But upper-year Ravenclaws had said he was only a little more strict than McGonagall, though much less polite to students, whereas Ron had reported upper-year Gryffindors said he was horrible, unfair, vindictive and Not-Very-Secretly Evil, but of course that's what most students said about Slytherins in general, and Gryffindors promoted this view almost unanimously. It was also widely reported that Snape had been after the Defence Professorship for years (many speculated this was so he would be permitted to cast Dark spells on students for "educational" purposes).

This sort of muddy thinking tended to irritate Hermione, which was why she found it irritating in an entirely different way when Snape swept into the room, his black cloak flapping, and looked Evil. Not quite Dracula-Evil, but certainly as if he was actively working at it. Maybe this was just what you got when people gave up and embraced the Slytherin reputation. She supposed that could be a valid coping strategy for saving your sanity, though possibly at the cost of your soul - metaphorically speaking.

He called roll in a businesslike fashion, then simply paused and stared at the class for a moment, which stretched on and on uncomfortably. No one chose to interrupt the silence, however - the Professor had a kind of cold intensity that made any such impulse seem unwise at best. Finally, he began to speak.

"Despite what many of you may believe," he began, slowly, "Potion-making is magic of the highest order, a subtle science and an exacting art, beautiful and unforgiving in equal measure. Potions carry insidious power, for by ingestion do they bypass our defences, traveling in our very blood, to our hearts, our brains, every fibre of our being. Nothing you possess cannot be improved upon, or stolen away, by the skilled application of the proper recipe.

"But Potion-making is not like other magic. Like Transfiguration, it requires mental discipline, knowledge and attention to detail. Like Charms, it requires instinct, dexterity and memory. But unlike either, the strength of its effects come entirely from the ingredients, transformed by pure skill, not your own pathetically underdeveloped magical abilities. In other schools of magic, you still lack the strength to do true harm, even accidentally. But Potions will serve anyone with sufficient skill and knowledge, regardless of age. They will punish those who do not respect them. Make the wrong slip with the wrong substance of power...and you - and perhaps others - will join Madam Pomfrey." A couple of gasps greeted this, but the Professor looked more quietly pleased than irritated at the reaction.

"Show the Art the proper respect, however, and you will see wonders...I can teach you to bottle fame, to brew glory, even stopper death...but only if you are significantly less idiotic than the wastes of salt I am typically forced to instruct." Hermione found herself, a bit surprisingly, respecting Professor Snape. It was a similar introduction as McGonagall had given for Transfiguration, with as much presence but more drama. And even though she recognized his last line as an attempt at manipulation, inspiring students to prove him wrong, it was working anyway...she did want to earn his respect - and it was clear he truly loved his subject, which in Hermione's experience was a quality the best teachers shared.

"By the time I've finished writing the ingredients for today's lesson on the blackboard," he said, turning to do as he'd said, "I expect you to have arranged yourselves in pairs and half-filled a cauldron with water from the gargoyle." Hermione looked around as students immediately began pairing up. She'd vaguely expected the Patil twins to find each other, since they'd gone to different houses. Padma seemed to think the same thing, heading in her sister's direction, but stopped short as Parvati immediately asked Neville Longbottom to be her partner. Seeing Padma's face fall a bit, Hermione saw an opportunity to reciprocate Parvati's kindness in Defence and tapped her on the shoulder.

"Want to team up? Between the two of us, we can probably finish early and maybe get points for helping others?" The other girl smiled at the casual assumption of their combined superiority and quickly agreed. As the class continued and they dutifully followed Professor Snape's instructions - but quickly, as they'd both read ahead to know what was coming - Padma dared some quiet conversation.

"So, really, Hermione, what's going on? When you came into Transfiguration, you looked even worse than you did in Defence, but you're not just feeling unwell, you're thinking about something, I can tell." Hermione was starting to get very tired of not being able to tell people things, but she brightened a smidge as she realized that in this case maybe she could say something, since it would seem entirely reasonable to withhold details. And she'd dearly appreciate some emotional support, if not actual assistance.

"Say someone had found something you'd written that you didn't want other people to see," Hermione said, too quietly to be overheard, "something embarrassing, or very private...and they knew that you felt that way and planned to use that to get you to do something or give them money, or...whatever, something you wouldn't ordinarily do. How would you get out of it?"

"Nott is blackmailing you?" Padma said immediately, and Hermione looked around in alarm since her fellow Ravenclaw had been not quite as quiet as Hermione would have preferred. No one appeared to have heard her, but Hermione held a finger to her lips urgently, even as her mind spun. How did...what...what? But her confusion lasted only a moment, replaced with chagrin. She'd come in too closely behind Nott...and he'd been giving her looks that anyone could've noticed, even if they hadn't known what they meant. And she'd forgotten that other people could be clever.

"Probably. He says he's thinking about it," Hermione whispered.

"Well, what is it of yours that he's got?" Padma asked, finally matching Hermione's conspiratorial tone.

"Sorry...I can't really say, can I?" Hermione noted, and thankfully Padma accepted this, nodding thoughtfully.

"You could go to Flitwick, I suppose," she suggested after a moment. "If it's really your property, he'll be able to find it with spells, and he might even Memory Charm Nott so he couldn't spill your secrets to anyone." Hermione frowned.

"I don't like Memory Charms...but also, Nott said he's made copies, and those aren't my property - plus I don't know who he's given them to or what he's told them...even if he's Memory Charmed, they might realize somehow and then just tell him again, or distribute everything?" Padma frowned, and nodded slowly as they continued brewing their Boil-Curing Potion. Their tête-à-tête was briefly interrupted by a cry from Padma's sister, who was yanking Neville's arm away from the cauldron.

"No, Neville! We have to take the cauldron off the fire before adding the quills," Parvati said urgently.

"Oh, right, right," Neville agreed nervously, though he immediately started to do so by grasping the small round pot by its sides rather than the handle and yelped as his fingers were singed. Fortunately he hadn't lifted it far enough to spill anything when he hastily dropped the cauldron, though it teetered dangerously for a moment.

"Point from Hufflepuff for Longbottom's idiocy, point to Hufflepuff for Miss Patil's timely intervention," snapped Snape from across the classroom, and if anyone thought it peculiar for the Professor to cancel a penalty with an award (or vice versa), no one thought it prudent to mention. "Longbottom, there's unguent in the third drawer from the top on the left at the front of the room, see to your hands...if you're very lucky, your partner will successfully finish the potion before you can return and make another attempt to ruin it." There were a couple of titters from Ravenclaws, but most everyone else just looked scared, or grateful they weren't the target of the Professor's sharp tongue. Despite having prevented disaster and "earning" a point for Hufflepuff, Parvati seemed as dejected as Neville.

"She fancies him," whispered Padma to Hermione, who had been puzzling out Parvati's reaction.

"What, really?"

"Yep, ever since the train...she won't explain it either. Maybe she can't," mused Padma, whose expression said she certainly found it inexplicable. Hermione, who understood romance (or at least hormones) intellectually but hadn't yet been afflicted personally, found herself in agreement. They finished the next-to-last step of their potion, then lapsed into thoughtful silence while they waited for the small sand-glass to empty.

"Oh, of course," said Padma suddenly. "You've just got to get something similar on him. So if he ever let out your secret, you can let out his - that way, if he knows what's good for him, he'll just drop the whole thing." Hermione considered this.

"Mutually Assured Destruction? Hmm...I'm not sure I could go through with that, I really try to be as ethical a person as I can…" Padma gave her a peculiar look, then shook her head.

"Doesn't matter, as long as he believes that you might go through with it, it'll be enough. You can pretend to be Slytherin, right?" Hermione was about to correct her use of Slytherin as a pejorative, but before a word came out of her mouth, everyone went quiet as a voice hissed above them, loud enough to reach every corner of the classroom.

"Did you listen to a single word I said?" asked Professor Snape, his voice icy. "Idiocy is one thing, but your otherwise exemplary performance up to this point suggests that you two know better...and yet are now disrespecting your potion with your inattentive gossip." Padma tried to point out that she'd totally been watching the sand-glass, and it still had two minutes left, but the Professor rolled on relentlessly. "What was this discussion about that you deemed more important than your education, your safety, and the safety of your fellow students?"

Hermione stared up at him, wide-eyed, as his cold, dark eyes bored down at her. Being yelled at by a teacher was an entirely foreign concept that she was simply not emotionally prepared for, and only her raw shock was for the moment holding back the tears that were likely coming. Particularly since he was right, even if he was being overly harsh about it...since when did she jabber on during classes, let alone dangerous ones? Not that it wasn't important to keep herself out of Nott's devious clutches, or more so, to prevent him from revealing to any hypothetically-at-large Death Eaters that she knew Voldemort was going to-

Snape abruptly backed a single step away from her, his expression not changing in the slightest.

"Regardless of your opinions, It was not important. Keep it to yourself," he spat, then swept over to Terry and Kevin's table and began ruthlessly berating them for the their failure to stir evenly. Padma and Hermione glanced at each other in nervous confusion, each wanting to say "He forgot to take points from us," but unwilling to risk any speech at all. At least the strange reprieve had jolted Hermione out of her emotional tailspin before she'd shed any tears. Through everything, she'd felt Morag's inexplicably resentful eyes on her the whole time.

o-o-o

It was only after class was finished - all the students had practically sprinted out of his classroom, and he'd firmly shut and sealed the door with efficient twitches of his wand - that the wizard let his iron control slip. A bead of sweat formed at his temple, and his eyes showed some of what he'd felt upon casually invading the young girl's mind, as was his habit - ostensibly to keep his skills in practice, but at least in part simply for his own amusement.

Severus Snape sat alone for some time, struggling to overcome his shock. And fear.

Chapter 17.1: Interlude - Tempus Torqueri (1 of 2)

The young woman strode purposefully towards the medium-sized building, weaving through the moderate Paddington pedestrian traffic. She was wearing an outfit that was coordinated enough not to excite notice from muggles, but with enough concessions to magical style that it wouldn't be off-putting - at worst a little drab - to people with whom she met. Her hair's normal resistance to order was opposed only by being tied back into a ponytail with a saffron scarf, and she was sensibly - given the amount of walking she'd been doing - wearing trainers.

She took the stairs to the third floor - in a concession to maintaining reasonable fitness, the young woman never took a lift for less than four flights - and quickly found the correct door. She followed policy and checked her wand (in a Disillusioned waist holster), checked her PASS (active, two layers), took a moment to draw herself up in an official bearing, and knocked three times, firmly. A woman of middling years wearing a dark orange housedress answered the door.

"Mrs. Conphelia Alderdosh?" she asked. The older woman nodded. "My name is Hermione Granger, I'm here from the Ministry on a DRCMC check, may I come in?" She said it in a matter-of-fact way, pointedly not looking around or speaking in conspiratorial tones. There weren't any witnesses in the hallway, but while a hypothetical muggle who'd overheard might have thought the Ministry reference oddly non-specific, they'd be unlikely to think it suspicious.

"Oh, about Philbert? By all means, come in, come in," Mrs. Alderdosh chirped, retreating back into the flat. "Can I get you anything, tea?" she asked, after Hermione had stepped inside, closing the door behind her.

"No, thank you," Hermione said, politely, "I shouldn't need to stay long."

"Frizzy-haired rat's nest!" said an improbably large ferret, considerably less politely. It wasn't actually a ferret, of course, but a Jarvey - a magical cousin with an impressive ability to speak, and the unfortunate restriction of only doing so to deliver a steady stream of insults. "Bossy!" The speech and generally well-aimed quality of the insults ought to have implied some degree of sapience, but the relentlessness of the abuse had discouraged optimistic investigation on that topic, and Jarveys remained firmly classified as Beasts.

Hermione observed the condition of the flat, the creature itself, and its owner, and removed the short quill from the clipboard she held. On the form secured to the clipboard, she dutifully checked four boxes next to "3f, 24 Praed Street, Paddington/Mrs. Conphelia Alderosh/Jarvey x 1/Philbert", and under the columns "Creature Present", "Conditions Satisfactory", "Health Satisfactory (Creature)", and "Health Satisfactory (Owner)", respectively.

"Any plans to sell or give Philbert to anyone in the near future?" she asked.

"Testy! Nosey!" cried the Jarvey. Perhaps to the ward at St. Mungo's for Excessive Masochism? Hermione thought in a silent amendment to her question.

"Oh, no, I couldn't bear to part with him - he's all that I have for company since my dear Flurvis passed on," the woman said, smiling sadly.

"Senile! Shut-in! Cow-faced prune!" added Philbert, unhelpfully. Hermione checked off one last box, and nodded.

"Thank you Mrs. Alderosh, that's all I needed. I can let myself out." The other witch's smile was touched with disappointment.

"Oh, are you sure you don't want to stay?" Hermione felt a bit bad for the woman, who clearly would have enjoyed some polite company, but not bad enough to want to remain a minute longer than she had to. And she was on a schedule. Not that anyone but her would really care if she were less efficient.

"Sorry, I still have quite a few visits left today," she said, tapping her clipboard. "Thank you for your time, and have a nice day." She quickly left the flat, but couldn't close the door fast enough to avoid hearing a final salvo from Philbert.

"Heartless Ministry drone!" Hermione winced.

She wondered if anyone had tried Cheering Charms, or maybe a Confundus...obviously a Silencing Charm would've worked - but then, presumably the sort of person who opted to keep a Jarvey as a pet would prefer them just as they were. But this thought was less serious problem-solving and more to distract herself from how close to home that last jibe had hit.

As she went back to the stairs to go up two more flights to her next check-in, she wondered - as she often did these days - if she was doing the right thing. After she'd finished her N.E.W.T.s, joining the Department for the Regulation and Control of Magical Creatures had seemed like a good way for her to do some immediately constructive things for magical Britain. She could leverage her personal experience with Elves, at the very least get the current welfare laws enforced more often, ideally push to get them expanded. Then Centaurs, Goblins, maybe even Giants! The idea of a world where all intelligent creatures were treated equally, given the same access to education and wands...it appealed directly to her idealism, and while Voldemort's final defeat - and his association with inequality - was fresh in the public's minds was the perfect time to do it.

Somehow things hadn't worked out quite as she'd imagined. Sure, she was helping with Elvish welfare in her own small way - she'd been responsible for nearly a hundred citations in her first six months alone - but it seemed that sweeping her exams and helping defeat Dark Lords didn't excuse her from Ministry policy, which for the DRCMC meant two training years no matter how smart or semi-famous you were. Endless check-ins with registered owners of Magical Creatures, making sure the things hadn't died, escaped, been sold, gotten loose and eaten their owners, etc. Occasionally there were warnings, or citations, almost never any excitement - if there's any active suspicion of problems or criminal activity, they don't send a trainee.

Hermione rechecked the next address on her clipboard, paused at the door, then checked wand, PASS, and posture. Policy. She sighed, and knocked.

Coeur-arbre, she thought as she glanced down at her clipboard, that's interesting at least. It was a rare magical tree - limited sentience with no mobility beyond willingly shedding its leaves, but still barely enough to require check-ins. Beyond decoration, the only recorded use was the leaves, a Class E Tradable, that could be used as an ingredient in a few minor potions. Not love potions per se, despite the name, more like "nostalgia"...rekindling friendship, bringing back fond memories, that sort of thing.

Because she was still looking at the clipboard when the man opened the door, she missed his rapid series of expressions, from a look of irritation, to surprise and alarm, then determination. All she saw was the determination, and she hadn't even registered the import of the wand in his hand when he immediately hit her with a powerful curse and she flew backwards, her body and head slamming evenly into the opposite wall.

The curse - whatever it was - had shattered the outer layer of her PASS, but left the inner intact - the combined efforts of that layer and the Impact Absorbing Charm she prudently cast on herself whenever she was going near muggle traffic had likely saved her from a nasty concussion, or worse.

The man, a dark-haired fellow with a thin scar under his left eye, was wearing the sort of mismatched but highly functional robes and gear favored equally by Cursebreakers, Security Witches, and criminals. His wand was short, dark and gnarled. In the flat behind him...well, Hermione was a little dazed and still wasn't sure what she was seeing, but it was obviously highly magical and made her eyes as wide as saucers. Despite her slight dizziness and not having been in serious magical combat for almost three years now, she was grimly pleased to note that the clipboard had been dropped and her wand was already in her hand, poised equally to reinforce her PASS, stun, or deflect as necessary. Her attacker swore, and rather than following up with another assault, instead he slammed the door.

Hermione immediately restored the outer layer of her Persistent Accommodating Shield Spell, then added a third and fourth layer for good measure. Stacking multiple layers like this was a lot more difficult than it sounded, but then, she had invented the spell. The tiny, invisible hole in each layer - which allowed the spell to protect in all directions yet still permit outgoing magic - rotated around her in carefully mismatched orbits, and would only ever snap into mutual alignment for the split second it took one of her own spells to pass through them. Only once that was done did she hesitate. DRCMC policy when encountering a suspected criminal was to withdraw safely, Apparate to the DMLE emergency reception area, brief whoever was on duty and let the Aurors handle it. But her brief glimpse of the completely unfamiliar magic behind the door suggested a powerful ritual of some sort was going on in there, and given the man's immediate resort to violence, it probably wasn't a spell to summon kittens. There might not be any time to spare.

Also, she told herself, I am not a Ministry drone, no matter what Malfoy's spirit animal might say...I am a Gryffindor.

Hermione flicked her wand to open the door, and when - unsurprisingly - it did not open, she flicked it again in a wordless Unlocking Charm. When it still didn't open, she dismissed it entirely from consideration, took a step to the side, then hit the wall with a Silencing Charm and a Bombardment Curse in quick succession. She buried her mouth into the crook of her free arm to avoid choking on the sudden dust from the eerily soundless burst of frame wood and plaster that left a now person-sized opening into the flat. Another twist of her wand and the dust fell to the floor en masse like iron filings pulled to a magnet, allowing her a clear view.

The man, against a wall and half-prone from the blast, had nevertheless maintained concentration on his immediate task, which apparently had been enchanting a scrap of paper. It flew out the open window behind him, trailing smoke like a jet fighter's exhaust, and with similar speed. Seeing Hermione through the hole, he swore again and his features tightened. Unwilling to launch a stunner anywhere near the active field of an unknown ritual, Hermione ducked under the plane of eldritch light and physically lunged forward instead, but she was too late - her hand passed through the space where he'd been a moment earlier.

Hermione did not swear out loud, though she did allow herself to think a few extremely nasty phrases.

She didn't waste much time on self-recrimination, however, and immediately took stock of the situation. The flat was dominated by the Coeur-arbre, growing out of a large flat plot of dirt somehow - presumably magically - set into the floor. Every one of its rather pretty pinkish-silver leaves was strewn about the floor, leaving the tree looking thin and bare. Beyond that, a spinning contraption of some kind had been driven into the trunk of the tree. A luminous rosy silver fluid was dripping from it, as if it were a tap for maple syrup, but the intensely magical substance was twisting in skeins through the air of the room about five feet above the floor. It aligned in patterns above complex Arithmantic diagrams which had been laid out on the floor in chalk, and which Hermione had - miraculously, in her current judgement - not disturbed when she'd rushed forward to try to force a Side-Along with the man.

A Finite probably isn't going to cut it here, Hermione thought, swallowing against a suddenly dry throat.

The patterns in the air were shifting with increasing speed. Hermione edged back out from under the the active magic, then turned carefully away. She pointed her wand to a clear space near the hole in the wall, concentrating firmly on Dearest Ronald, but thinking about the message she wanted to send to the DMLE, which was roughly as follows: Go to the duty officer in DMLE emergency reception, and tell them DRCMC trainee Hermione Granger reports that there is an unknown ritual in progress in 5c, 24 Praed Street, Paddington. One male suspect - dark hair, scar under left eye, wand, uh, seven inches, gnarled, ash I think - assaulted me and Disapparated. Ritual appears to be self-sustaining, may be unstable, I will begin efforts to analyse and contain it, but you might want to call in an Herbology specialist and maybe an Unspeakable, as it involves previously unreported properties of a Coeur-arbre.

"Expecto Patronum!" she cried, with the appropriate brandish. The shining otter that burst from her wand did a tight lap in the air around her head - the brief look of reproach it seemed to give her might have been due to the length of her message, but was probably just her imagination - then streaked off. That much handled, Hermione quickly (and belatedly) added a Muggle-repelling Charm to the area around the hole in the wall, then addressed all her attention to the animated skeins of what she'd decided for the moment to call "Coeur-arbre syrup". Carefully moving around the active area, she stepped close to the edge of the Arithmantic diagrams on the floor. From what she could gather at a glance, they were doing very little active functional transformation, and instead seemed to be simply focusing and concentrating the syrup itself, along with whatever properties it held. Presumably with the intent of leveraging those properties to some purpose, but you never could tell with people who were crazy enough to do unsupervised magical research.

Hermione inscribed a quick Arithmantic series of diagnostic formulae in the air - glowing symbols trailing from her wand's tip - as close as she could to one of the skeins at the edge of the field. Almost immediately the formulae flared into painful brilliance, then exploded into motes. Hermione tensed...one of the Fundamental Magics...at least one. Her wand darted into action again as she swiftly traced out more symbols, starting a much more involved set of formulae. Hopefully, these would hold and she could get at least enough of a handle on what was happening here to safely-

Her hopes and inscribing both were interrupted, as someone came sprinting into the flat through the hole in the wall, skidded out-of-control on the dust-covered floor, and slammed bodily into her. Hermione fairly shrieked in shock and spun around with the hit, allowing her a view of a young woman her own age. The woman's echoing shriek, and the expression of dismay that was straining her own features made it difficult to be certain, but, considering the line on Hermione's clipboard for this flat had listed the tree's owner as "Ms. T. Davis", she could see a certain resemblance to her former classmate.

"What are you-" the woman began to shout, but her eyes widened even further - to the point where they threatened to eclipse her forehead - and she reached out towards Hermione, who felt herself tipping off-balance from the spin. The woman's fingers closed around Hermione's arm at the same time Hermione's head intersected the skein she'd been trying to analyze, the lambent syrup cutting through four layers of PASS like they hadn't been cast at all - or more precisely, like they hadn't been cast yet.

Hermione felt it happen, and she wanted to be exasperated, but somehow as all light and thought vanished, all she felt was contentment, familiarity, wonder.

o-o-o

She looked around, in considerable confusion. The flat was gone, the Coeur-arbre, the ritual, Tracey (if that had actually been her)...instead, she was in a bookshop. Which was still somehow comforting, despite its current inexplicability. Hermione recognized it almost immediately as Flourish and Blotts in Diagon Alley, which at least answered - partially, anyway - one of the dozen or so questions now fighting for attention in her mind.

The shop bustled with its usual activity, with witches and wizards of all ages criss-crossing the shop and politely elbowing each other for room. It thus did not take long at all for Hermione's confusion to shift gears when one of the aforementioned joints - belonging to a passing witch - sailed through her body with no resistance, or indeed reaction on the part of its owner.

"Er…" said Hermione. Her first thought was that the Coeur-arbre syrup had acted like a Pensieve, but she'd finally had the chance to use one during her DRCMC training (for "first-hand" exposure to otherwise excessively rare or dangerous creatures), and while her current surroundings did have a very slight hazy cast to them, it seemed like a subjectively different sort of hazy cast. She then examined this thought, did not think highly of it, and wondered if she might be suffering some sort of after-effects. But only idly...it didn't seem important, somehow.

Her attention was drawn to a small commotion - a pair of wizards were leaning over to observe something hidden from her view behind a small stand of copies of perennial-bestseller, Hogwarts, a History. She walked around the stand to see better, and suddenly felt like she'd been punched in the stomach. There, sprawled on the floor, was a young girl in muggle attire, a mass of brown bushy hair framing her face. On one side of her was a bag from Flourish and Blotts, filled with the official class books the girl had responsibly purchased before beginning her personal browsing. On the other side, beneath her fingertips, was a crisp new copy of Hogwarts, a History.

The girl's face was pale, her eyes closed, and the wizards were arguing about whether to try another spell since Rennervate hadn't worked, or just have one of them set straight off for St. Mungo's to fetch a Mediwitch, and if so, which of them would go and which would stay.

Hermione realized several things in quick succession. The girl was herself, on her first trip to Diagon Alley. This was not a memory, Pensieve or otherwise, because she certainly hadn't fainted in the bookstore. The unknown ritual with the Coeur-arbre had presented as involving at least one Fundamental Magic, one of which, of course, was Time. And finally - and most alarmingly - as she watched her younger self grow paler, she herself felt increasingly invigorated, her thoughts more clear.

"A Horcrux?" she whispered, horror racing with bafflement and edging into a slight lead. Her dismay easily tripled as one of the wizards looked up, then back and forth in her general direction, as if he'd heard her, but wasn't able to see her. Yet.

Immediately, she stepped forward and kicked her own hand away from the book.

Or at least that was her intention, if perhaps an ill-considered one given her current intangibility. As it happened, her hand did move away from the book, but it was entirely due to the full-body startle she gave when she abruptly found herself inhabiting her younger self's body, staring up at two suddenly-relieved-looking wizards.

"See, it must've just taken a moment to kick in," said the shorter wizard.

"Are you quite all right, young lady?" asked the other. "Do you need help to St. Mungo's, or perhaps finding your guardian?" Now incarnated, she could somehow feel her younger self's mind beneath her own, as if it were an egg on a table and she was pressing her hand on it with steadily increasing force. With all her willpower, she rejected this sensation, "pulled" her hand away. And it seemed to work, her younger mind felt less endangered. But at the same time, she now felt a "hollow place" at the top of her own mind, very slowly pulsing, pushing out cracks. It was a deeply disquieting sensation, but she could obviously cope with it in the short term if the alternative was somehow draining her own life force away.

That handled for the moment, she regarded the book on the floor warily, as if it were a live, poisonous snake. But there was no point in getting rid of it...if it was somehow a horcrux akin to Riddle's diary - or something close to it, since she certainly hadn't killed anyone to create it (unless she'd killed herself?) - it wouldn't matter, she was already linked to it. And it seemed to be working much faster, perhaps because it was her own spirit trying to (or trying not to, rather) steal her own life force. But there appeared to be a degenerative factor in her refusal...possibly if she just waited it out, the link would fade and break.

"Miss? Miss?" One of the wizard's repeated calls finally penetrated, and Hermione realized she needed to begin acting immediately to limit any changes to History. If she - or a part of her soul - had been flung back through Time by whatever had happened, the normal "protections" of a Time-Turner might not apply. She hastily picked up her (soon-to-be) copy of Hogwarts, a History and her bag of other books and stood up, past the gentle pressure of the wizards' hands as they urged caution.

"I'm all right now, really. Just a medical condition, ah, Transient Ischemic Fluctuations, happens to a lot of muggle-borns…" she said, hoping neither of the wizards themselves were muggle-borns. They still looked concerned, but a little less so - jargon could be comforting, putting something in a nicely defined box that said that someone understood it, even if that someone wasn't you.

"You still really ought to get that checked at St. Mungo's," urged the taller wizard, "They can deal with most muggle diseases pretty easily, you know."

"Oh yes," said Hermione, "my parents have a pamphlet, they're taking me there straight away after we finish shopping, I'm just browsing while they get everything else. They'll probably be back here in no more than two hours or so, if you want to wait?" This was a gamble, but she hoped the assurance combined with the inconvenience of minding her for up to two hours would dissuade the would-be Samaritan wizards.

"Ah, well, that's probably all right then," said the shorter wizard. "We ought to be going anyway. But you might want to use one of the chairs in the Reading Corner," he suggested, pointing towards a nook off to the side of the clerks' registers, "just in case you fall down again?" Hermione nodded encouragingly.

"Thank you, that's an excellent idea...I just need to buy this first. Thank you so much, you've both been very kind." The taller wizard still looked uncertain, but allowed his companion to pull him away as Hermione headed towards a register queue.

She bought the book, and quickly performed her traditional ritual of inscribing her name - though she suspected whatever strange magic was at work had marked the book far more securely as hers than anything she could have done deliberately. Bringing her first trip to Flourish and Blotts to mind, she recalled finding Great Wizarding Events of the Twentieth Century next, so she put Hogwarts, a History into her bag of purchases and hurriedly found the proper shelf. She put one hand on a copy, then paused.

Her sense of her past self's mind suggested that even if it wasn't in control, it was active somehow, at least a little, and Hermione feared that meant she'd remember some of this...certainly enough that she'd ask questions about it that she'd definitely never asked.

Working with a light, instinctive touch, she experimentally ran mental fingers through her younger mind as if it was a book, and found she received impressions of what was on each "page". Encouraged, she continued, until she found a section that felt correct, right up at the "end". Hermione hesitated a moment, wary of relying on inexplicable abilities she didn't understand, but every moment that passed increased the risk to History. She closed her eyes and whispered.

"Sorry, but this is for our own good."

Hermione pulled sharply, tearing, and she felt it as a searing burn across her own psyche. She felt herself slipping and deliberately turned it into a sort of fumbling mental acrobatics, "flinging" her younger self's mind "upward" while she dropped "beneath". Throughout the maneuver, she was relieved - sort of - to note that the hollow place stayed firmly affixed to her own mind.

Hermione couldn't have explained how she'd done it, but it had worked. Her younger self, now in control again, shook her head slightly, then withdrew the copy of Great Wizarding Events and began scanning the table of contents, not acting as if she'd experienced anything bizarre and inexplicable. And Hermione herself no longer seemed to have a body of her own, she was simply watching through her past self's eyes, hearing through her ears, and - somewhat less distinctly - feeling the other normal operations of her body, even while her mind still reeled from the shocking pain of having attacked her own memories. Did that pain mean that this "now" was still causally linked to her own, and the pain was a flavor of backlash? But she'd acted to preserve her own episodic continuity...maybe it was just a sympathetic reaction, since they were somehow sharing the same brain...

By the time her parents and Professor McGonagall showed up to collect her and go buy her wand, her past self had purchased all the books she'd remembered purchasing this trip, and the adults had said the same things she remembered - or loosely, at any rate, her memory was not quite as good for speech as it was for written material, and it had been nearly a decade. But if she'd had lungs, she would've sighed in relief. Whatever was going on with her, History, at least, seemed to be safe.

At least, it did for the seven minutes it took to walk to Ollivanders.

o-o-o

Hermione watched, with increasing concern, the not just different, but downright bizarre version of her first visit to Ollivanders. It was concerning, but not really alarming, until the enigmatic wandmaker appeared to come to a decision.

"I have little doubt you will learn...everything in Time, Miss Granger. But it will not have been now, nor from me," he intoned. Merlin, he's going to Obliviate you! Protego, dodge, do something you little idiot! Hermione tried to reverse the maneuver she'd pulled before, to take control, but she could gain no purchase. A bright flash issued from the tip of Ollivander's wand, and Hermione felt a thousand-thousand delicate threads of magic slice through her past self's mind, breaking connections, rending apart associations. Her past self didn't seem to feel it, but for her, it was as if she'd been dropped into an active lava flow, it was like being Crucio'd by Bellatrix all over again but with Greyback tearing her to pieces at the same time.

She screamed, soundlessly. Waves of agony and alarm washed imperceptibly over her younger self's mind, nestling into the cracks in the banal replacement memories Ollivander's spell was painstakingly constructing. Hermione did not lose consciousness exactly...consciousness was all she was. But under the unrelenting assault, her thoughts grew thick and dull and dark, and it was equal parts horror and mercy, for she lost the pain in a dense, slow fog of confusion.

o-o-o

By the time Hermione's mind regained coherence, weeks had apparently passed - she found herself lying in her bed at Hogwarts, staring up at the dark canopy over her bed. Something seemed a bit off about it, but her first priority was to take stock of both her own mind and her past self's. Thankfully, the younger mind, now sleeping, showed no sign of damage - as awful as it had been for Hermione, Ollivander had patched over his own work much more smoothly than the scar she had left from her own desperate efforts in Flourish and Blotts. Though there did seem to be strange ripples of her own experience woven distastefully through the former, like a few cat hairs sticking out of an otherwise delicious pudding. But even more relieving, there was no sign that the degeneration had affected her other self. It seemed, even in her insensate state, Hermione had retained her conviction not to draw upon her past self's life force.

Her own mind, however, was another matter. The cracks and gaps had spread throughout, and widened - and though she could sense them with the strange awareness she had in this state, through some self-referential flaw, she couldn't interpret them the way she had with her past self's memories. She knew that important parts of her were going, and she had no idea which. It ought to have terrified her, but it felt more irritating than anything else, and that frightened her a little bit.

With her younger self asleep, she did seem to have regained control of their shared body at the moment, and it occurred to her that if she couldn't fully rely on her own mind anymore, she ought to keep some kind of notes. Besides, note-taking always helped her think even under normal circumstances. If she gained control every time her younger self slept, and could keep the notes secure and hidden somehow - even from herself - maybe she could compile enough research to undo this whole mess, get back to her own time.

Accordingly, she slipped out of bed quietly, so as not to disturb her roommates - Lavender in particular was a light sleeper - but her trunk was not where she expected it to be, and she had to bite her tongue to keep from crying out when she stubbed a toe. But apparently the small sound had been too much.

"Be quiet," murmured an irritable voice, and Hermione winced as much for waking Lavender as for her smarting toe.

"Sorry Lav," she whispered, feeling around for the trunk's unfamiliar position. But her reassurance apparently had the opposite of the intended effect, as she heard the soft sound of the girl sitting up in bed.

"What did ye call me?" came a whisper from the shadows. Hermione's heart juddered. Whatever parts of her mind might be missing, she was certain that Lavender did not have a Scottish accent. She leaned forward and twitched the curtains slightly to let a bit more of the dim moonlight into the room, and was additionally disoriented by how high the view seemed to be, and furthermore of the wrong side of the castle. But that was nothing compared to seeing the completely unfamiliar face glaring at her from the adjacent bed. Hermione desperately tried to bring her thoughts up to speed.

"I...I meant sorry, I have to use the lav," she whispered. "I just stubbed my toe."

"Bards will sing of your tragedy," the girl responded, scorn dripping from her own hissing whisper. "Next time, daen't apologize, just be quiet." With that, she flopped back down and pulled the blanket back up - also, somehow, scornfully.

Hermione, not wanting to risk further noise or conversation at the moment, quickly moved to the bathroom. And stood frozen in utter shock, for from the complete lack of lions in the fixtures, it was obvious that it was not a Gryffindor bathroom.

o-o-o

After some unknown period of quiet panic, Hermione tried to get a grip on herself. Step one was to orient herself. Looking at the fixtures closely, they were all eagles and ravens. So apparently, while she'd been "out", her past self had been Sorted into Ravenclaw. She had seriously changed Time. Hermione became a little dizzy and a bit nauseated, and felt the need to spend a while sitting on the bathroom floor with her arms around her knees, rocking.

But even if it was hard to remember, in a not-quite-twelve-year-old body, feeling like this - in a bathroom, no less - and surrounded by paradox-laden bird fixtures, she eventually reminded herself that she was a Gryffindor, she was a confident adult woman, and fugues did not solve problems. So Hermione pulled herself together again, and came at it from a different direction. It had been weeks, at least, since Diagon Alley. Plenty of time for Butterfly Effects to become shocking and disorienting - instead, she withdrew into herself and reached for that strange sense of her younger self's mind again. She tried carefully paging through it, spending enough time to get as much detail as she could from each bit, noting each change from her recollections, compiling a new mental timeline. But she found it difficult to keep things straight, to stay focused.

Notes, right. She was going to keep notes.

Hermione judged it had been long enough that whoever the Scottish girl was - not Cho Chang, she'd have recognized her...who'd been in Ravenclaw her year? Mac-something... Anyway, that she was hopefully solidly asleep again. So she ventured back into the bedroom proper, and with achingly slow, silent movements, managed to extract her wand, a quill and some paper from one of her trunks, then make her way back to the bathroom. She sat carefully on the side of a toilet seat - stall door closed and latched - lit her wand dimly, and began to take notes, though they came out a bit more stream-of-consciousness than she'd have liked.

She filled a full page with everything she could remember about the Coeur-arbre, the Arithmantic diagrams, the man who'd attacked her and fled, and continued them on a second sheet. Hermione decided that, given the name, if anyone had better information than Hogwarts on Coeur-arbre, it would be Beauxbatons, though contacting them without making things worse could be problematic.

Next was compiling changes. Obviously there were the two wizards in Flourish and Blotts - she really should've gotten their names at the time, but there really wasn't much she could do there at this point. But the next thing was Ollivander's bizarre behaviour, and there wasn't enough time for what happened in the bookstore to have spread changes that far. Tracey had grabbed her just before it happened, what if she'd been pulled in too, but to an earlier time? But then she really ought to have noticed more changes, as soon as she arrived. Hermione considered contacting Ollivander, since he clearly knew something, but that had the same difficulties as Beauxbatons, and plus, he'd essentially assaulted an eleven-year-old. For all she knew, he had been under an Imperius, or had been Polyjuiced at the time or something.

The bit with Tonks...her younger self must have arrived at King's Cross slightly earlier, so that was easy enough to explain. But what had possessed her to actually make Pettigrew's fur yellow? Yes, she didn't know what he was, but still...that hadn't even occurred to her in her own version, even though she had seen the spell. Ah...she'd thought it was Tonks, Ron had mentioned his brothers, which must have reminded her of Tonks' conversation about pranking and her own disapproval of the same. Such a little thing... There must've been some earlier changes, but she couldn't find any obvious ones. And then after that… Hermione paged further into her younger self's memories.

Madam Pomfrey was dead. Madam Pomfrey was dead. Because she'd been forced to examine Pettigrew, because he'd bitten Goyle while being yellow.

Because of her.

She cried for a while, until it felt like she might be crying more for herself than for Poppy, then wiped away the tears harshly and continued her analysis. Was there any point in turning Pettigrew in? He'd probably go back to hiding, and so many parts of History depended on him being where he'd been, doing what he'd done. But he hadn't killed anyone this early before, and Riddle is here...how will he react to that? What if they found each other early?

Hermione tried to concentrate, but felt herself inching closer to drawing upon her younger self's energy, and flinched away. She considered the possibility that she might not be able to survive in this state much longer - at least not and retain any thoughts recognizable as her. I've traveled far further back through Time than I ever did third year, and yet I somehow don't have enough. Even Dearest Ronald would laugh.

She briefly considered just running to Dumbledore straightaway. There was nothing to be done about Poppy, but how much other death and horror could be avoided if Dumbledore knew everything, and now - or at least as much as she could access, the way her mind was? But for all she knew, Poppy was only the first backlash from her changes, inadvertent or otherwise - changing Time was dangerous. Yes, by abusing her Time-Turner they'd saved Buckbeak, and Sirius...if only temporarily - but it was pure luck that they'd had sufficient room to avoid contradictions that time and dodge around paradox. Here, paradox was stacking up rather fiercely.

She'd compromise...record everything she remembered - it was only right that it be preserved - and think of some way that the information be revealed if things were already going further wrong than they had already, or than they had the first time? That way it ought to limit the repercussions-

Hermione frowned. The word she'd just written had vanished. She scribbled a little, tried again. Those marks vanished as well. She looked at the quill - it wasn't that the self-inking enchantment had run out, it was making marks, they just weren't staying.

As she tested further, she watched in mute horror as the rest of her notes faded away, leaving the paper fresh and clean.

A Vanishing Ink Quill? Why in Merlin's name had she bought a joke Quill?!

She slumped wearily, one of the now-blank pages slipping from limp fingers into the toilet bowl below her, and she stared at it dully. Was this some kind of cosmic metaphor? Everything she'd done with her life was going to be wiped away and be flushed down the loo for good measure?

Hermione went ahead and flushed the useless page, then returned to her bed, finding the Scottish girl sitting up again, glaring. She didn't have the mental capacity to deal with this. She ought to Memory Charm her, she knew the spell well enough, but her body's muscle memory for the proper gestures wouldn't be present, plus there were her...issues...she might foul it up, the girl would naturally raise an alarm...

"Sorry," she whispered, instead. "Please don't tell anyone?" The girl just stared, and stared, just long enough for Hermione to actually recall the last thing she'd said to her, and cringe at the fact that in her inattention she'd done the opposite of what the Scottish girl had asked. The girl then only nodded curtly, her lips twisting, and lay down again. Hermione, feeling very much not herself, quietly put her things away, then got back into bed and waited for morning.

She wondered if it was a problem that in her current state - though she felt terribly weary - she didn't seem to have any capacity for sleep at all.

o-o-o

The next day was troubling, and the least of it was the constant low-level wrongness of her being a Ravenclaw. She was shocked to find herself visiting the Hogwarts Elves in the kitchens, treating them respectfully but not making a fuss - how had her younger self managed to come to terms with it, ethically? Hermione tried to recall what had gone through her own mind when she first discovered that Hogwarts kept house Elves, but the memory was disconcertingly fuzzy.

The conversation with the Weasley Twins at least cleared up most of the mystery of the quill and her notes, though something about it seemed not quite right, something important, but it was so hard to think when her younger self was awake, she just couldn't put her finger on it. Maybe it was that she'd kept the quill afterward?

She cringed at her brief misplaced sympathy about Scabbers' supposed death - or maybe it wasn't misplaced, since it was technically sympathy for Ronald, but either way it felt odd. But the thing with Lavender in Charms seemed highly suspicious. Pettigrew, in his Animagus form, clearly had some way of getting into and out of Gryffindor Tower - and perhaps the enchantments on the girl's dormitories only applied to male humans, in which case he could've stolen Lavender's wand, so anything he did to cover up Poppy's murder wouldn't show up on a Priori Incantato on her wand. That did leave open the question of what he had done, though.

Defence class definitely raised some concern, as Quirrell was obviously distracted in a way that suggested he was thinking about the murder. Not that him thinking about it was the real problem, but it was a symptom, since presumably Riddle was thinking about it as well. She wondered how the Slytherins would react if they knew they were effectively making sport of Voldemort. Riddle himself probably wouldn't actually mind, since they were targeting Quirrell - about whom he presumably cared very little - and they were only reinforcing Quirrell's oh-so-Slytherin deception about being harmless and beneath suspicion. But the first-years would probably wet themselves, and this thought took a bit of the edge off her very real concern about Riddle gaining some advantage as a result of her changes.

Then there was Transfiguration. Hermione hadn't made quite so comprehensive notes in her own first class, and while her first effort had reached the same endpoint, it hadn't been nearly as fast or dramatic. She had no idea that drilling down so far on contrast and conformation could have that kind of effect on speed, and felt a peculiar jealousy towards her younger self. Not that she seemed likely to have a particularly easy time of it, with all the obvious complications involved in the secrecy imposed by Professor McGonagall.

History of Magic was about as dull as she remembered it, though the house pairing was different, and there was - based on where she directed her gaze - her younger self's peculiar fixation on Slytherins. Yes, the Sorting wasn't exactly fair, but experience showed it was essentially accurate. But seemingly having more sympathy for them and less for the widely oppressed Elves gave Hermione some pause about the girl's moral judgement.

The conversation with Professor McGonagall was curious. For one, that it had never occurred to Hermione that the student in Minerva's class introduction might have tried to Transfigure radioactive material. It wasn't that she'd discounted the theory because it would've been a terribly reckless thing to do - which was true - she simply hadn't thought of it. Instead, she'd just accepted the Professor's lesson that Transfiguration was dangerous and she needed to follow the rules at all times, and given it no further attention. And then there was the very obvious realization - at least in retrospect - that Minerva must have had her own Time-Turner. Since Dumbledore had his own enigmatic responsibilities outside the school, he passed a significant amount of day-to-day responsibilities to her, and unlike him, she had Transfiguration to teach as well. It made her respect McGonagall even more, given all that had happened over the years, the difference a few extra hours of preparation might have made in so many situations, that she'd resisted the temptation to fiddle with Time. Or maybe, like Hermione, her respect for rules - at least, sensible ones - was so strong that intervening simply hadn't occurred to her without someone else to urge her, as Dumbledore had for Hermione? But then why hadn't he ever prompted Minerva similarly? Or maybe he had, and things would have been even worse otherwise…

o-o-o

She'd taken care to note how all Y.H.'s things were arranged this morning, so when the girl finally went to sleep, Hermione was able to navigate more confidently in the dark without disturbing anyone. Enough to gather clothes, wand, Self-Inking quill (a proper one this time), and paper. She decided to wait to change out of her nightgown until she was half a turn down the stairs, though. There was no sense in tempting fate with Morag again, who seemed to be holding a serious grudge about having her sleep disturbed, but thankfully she hadn't specifically mentioned it to her younger self.

Once she'd dressed, Hermione considered Disillusioning herself, but Disillusionment wasn't perfect, and if she was caught anyway, it would be much harder to explain having cast it as a first-year. Instead, she settled for charming her clothes to a uniform grey that fairly matched the castle's stone, then Silencing herself. She even, for a moment, considered trying to use a Summoning Charm to borrow the Marauder's Map, but even supposing there was an open path via which it could make its way to her, the risk that the Twins would see or hear it leave seemed too great. For all she knew, they were using it this very moment, roaming the castle after curfew.

That thought gave her pause. If they were using it, they'd be alert for anyone moving around the corridors, and it was impossible to predict how they'd react to seeing her name. At least it'd be her name either way, and that complication had been avoided - though the Twins seemed not terribly observant in that regard, or they'd have noticed Pettigrew or Riddle this year (presuming the latter showed up somehow superimposed with Quirrell, at any rate). But if they did, and decided to track her down, discovering her sneaking about Silenced, in charmed camouflage, like some sort of ninja witch, would be an awful tangle. Maybe she should've just left her nightgown on, allowing her to more easily claim sleepwalking, or something? In the end, she shrugged off these concerns. She was fairly certain that even in Y.H.'s body, she could subdue Filch and Mrs. Norris or the Twins, and Memory Charm them as necessary - with no one else around, she'd have enough time to do it slowly and carefully. On the other hand, if she encountered Snape...well, she'd cross that bridge when she came to it, and in the meantime just avoid going near his office or the forbidden third floor corridor.

Fortunately enough, she encountered no difficulty getting out of Ravenclaw Tower and making her way to the Library, despite the unfamiliarity of the route - in contrast to the path from the Gryffindor common room to the Library, which she knew better than the house she'd grown up in. The Library wasn't even locked, which Hermione found surprising given Madam Pince's predilections. Maybe it simply didn't occur to her anyone would dare intrude off hours?

Despite the eerie gloom, Hermione took a moment just to revel in the comforting familiarity, running her fingers along the shelves. Two years at the DRCMC...she'd thrown herself into her work, but lost her sense of identity. This was what was important...thousands of years of recorded knowledge, perfect and immutable. She could just climb onto one of the shelves and be content, secure. Madam Pince would never let anyone change her history, scribbling out what was meant to be written on her pages.

On her pages?

Hermione shook her head foggily and reminded herself what she was there for...researching what had started this whole mess, and making a hidden copy of what she knew about her future, so...so...no matter what, it wouldn't be lost? Yes, that was it. She began to thread the stacks more purposely, pulling volumes on uncommon magical plants, Fundamental Magics, and certain Arithmancy texts.

Chapter 17.2: Interlude - Tempus Torqueri (2 of 2)

It was growing ever harder to stay focused while Young Hermione was awake, events were passing in a kind of blur. But Hermione found a bit of unwelcome clarity when, in the midst of her counterpart doing some library research, the second page of her Vanished notes un-Vanished before her eyes, line-by-line. She dearly wished she'd dropped both pages into the toilet that night, but she'd had no reason to think her notes were ever coming back, and had simply replaced the paper into her younger self's stores. And despite the vague obfuscation she'd used in her notes, Hermione was quite agitated by her younger self's perusal of the forbidden references to future events. She was even more concerned that her vague sense of her body suggested Y.H. was also agitated, not just confused, but afraid.

Based on her gaze, she seemed to be focusing on the paragraph about Olivander...Merlin, who knew what trouble she'd get into if she raised a ruckus about being Obliviated. But obviously she couldn't remember being Obliviated, so hopefully it would just be a curiosity rather than-

At once, Hermione startled as she found herself in control, for the moment in full possession of both her body and her faculties. She reached inward for her younger self's mind and recoiled in horror - those echoes of her suffering during the Obliviation, caught in the matrix of false memories, had left threads hanging inward as well as outward. Her counterpart had "pulled" on them somehow, causing them not to unravel, exactly, but to lay new memories down of the same period - her memories.

She wasn't sure what to do...if she just tried to rip them out as she had in the bookstore, she wasn't sure her mind - or whatever she was now - would survive the attempt. Nor was she sure it wouldn't damage her younger self. She could try using a Memory Charm on "herself" tonight, but that too was a gamble - would the spell discriminate between the two minds present, assuming she could even finish it if it hurt her the same way Ollivander's had?

Before she could come up with something productive to do, she found herself unceremoniously ejected from control as her younger self recoiled from the memory, flooding her system with adrenaline and half-leaping, half-falling out of her chair before the girl managed to separate memory and reality.

She calmed herself down quickly enough, and then appeared to draw a reasonable but mostly wrong conclusion - that Hermione was a ghost, possessing her - and delivered a stern little speech to that effect. Was there some way she could take advantage of that misconception? But she wasn't even sure if she could focus enough to contact the girl's mind directly, for communication, while she was awake. Still, she didn't have a better option - she couldn't let her ask an adult about the notes, which would surely come up sooner rather than later - and began to try to struggle through the molasses that clogged her mind while her past self was awake.

She hadn't made much headway when the girl apparently lost patience and skipped directly to the step Hermione dreaded. She flailed in a bodiless panic, then froze, surprised, when the girl apparently noticed. She tried to follow the subsequent suggestion of producing a "happy" sensation, but she wasn't sure how she'd managed to convey fear in the first place, and once again the girl lost patience well before Hermione had any chance to make headway, a trait which was beginning to become maddening. The girl repeated her intention to talk to someone else, and again, Hermione thrashed as best she could against her mind, focusing on how bad an idea that was, that she should really just wait and think and give her a chance.

But her younger self was irritatingly stubborn, and was making her way out of the Library, even as her heart raced and her face was creased with worry. Hermione just couldn't compete under these circumstances, she needed her younger self to be asleep, but even in her own body she couldn't accomplish wandless magic - hoping to pull it off while half-inhabiting her first-year self wasn't much better than just wishing her to sleep. But sleep was a natural function of the body...even if she didn't have direct access to her physiological functions, could she evoke it?

Hermione desperately reached for her younger self's mind, not to tear, but to pull a memory to the top. She couldn't be sure, but the girl had wobbled in her step and leaned against a bookshelf for a moment...Hermione tried again, harder. This time she was sure she'd made progress, she could vaguely feel the lethargy flooding her body, and her younger self complained, not yet seeing the gambit for what it was. Hermione reached for a deep, deep memory and thrust it to the fore, trying to will the girl into slumber. She slumped down onto the floor, barely awake, reaching into her bag for her wand. But before she had it, she closed her eyes and it was just enough for Hermione to push the the other mind underneath and take control.

As her own mind began to clear up, she could tell this was an artificial sleep, and wouldn't last long...even less if she exerted herself or became too excited. Hermione carefully stood up and left the Library, considering her options. First priority was getting rid of her notes. Once she was alone in the hallway, she withdrew the offending page from her bag, along with an unused sheet, and her wand. She copied her younger self's notes over to the blank sheet by hand, then summarily Vanished the original page - now nothing she tried doing to the copy would ever restore what Hermione had written, and no spell she knew of would be able to reveal anything unusual about the new copy - it had had no magic used on it, and had been written by Hermione Granger.

That handled, how was she going to prevent the girl from talking to anyone about it, without trying to meddle with her memories? She might just write herself a note deliberately, but starting a pen-pal conversation in her current condition felt far too close to Ginny's ordeal for her to be comfortable, and she couldn't count on being able to force her into sleep - she suspected the girl would be on guard for that now. Besides, she needed to limit her interaction with her past self as much as she possibly could. But thinking of the year of the Chamber, and how so many people had refused to believe Harry about not being the Heir of Slytherin, even on the basis of the flimsiest evidence… If she couldn't keep herself from talking to people...maybe she could keep herself from being believed?

She could already feel her younger self stirring, so she made her way to the Hospital Wing as fast as she dared without risking adrenaline waking her even sooner. She was rather unsteady by the time she made it there, but that was fine, it would only make her story more convincing.

"My word, you don't look very well, what's the trouble?" asked Madam Wainscott solicitously, moving over to her.

"I'm not sure," said Hermione, her voice deliberately fuzzy. "I was in the Library, someone cast a spell at me from behind...think it went 'Confundo Oraculum Maximo'? My head feels peculiar, but I don't know what else...ohhh." Hermione didn't have to fake a swoon, she just let her mind drop beneath again, and her body folded to the floor like its strings had been cut. The nurse made a grab for her, but didn't quite make it in time. Looking worried, she pulled her wand and used an advanced levitation spell to get her into a bed, and by that time Hermione's counterpart had awakened.

It seemed her plan had worked - sort of - as Wainscott was indeed waving away everything that her younger self tried to explain. But what she was saying was alarming in the extreme. This wasn't information she'd deduced from the notes, she was acting as if she'd seen things in Hermione's own memory! And not just recovering what she'd lost from Ollivander's Memory Charm, but actual events from the future. This was a disaster...had Hermione opened some channel between them when forcing her younger self's memories...did that even make sense? It was so hard to tell, so hard to think…

She noticed herself hurriedly taking notes while changing into pyjamas, notes which definitely contained memories of the future. Some of the worst parts of the future, apparently. Why had she seen those memories in particular? It was as if someone was trying to get her to change Time even as Hermione desperately tried to minimize the damage. But there was no sign of a third mind in there with them...none of it made sense. She tried to wrest back control, and managed to make the handwriting a bit sloppier when the girl switched to her left hand, but that was it. When she'd finished writing, her younger self charmed each page of the notes waterproof, then folded them up into a little bundle. She paused for a moment, and her chest felt tight, but then she took a breath and cast one final spell.

"Echo Moratus," she whispered, "Hello, hello, hello. If anyone can hear this, please pick this up and read it carefully." After two more repetitions of the message, without hesitation, she flung the packet of papers out the open window above her bed.

Even as Hermione began to panic in earnest, the girl called to Madam Wainscott, and then, quietly, taunted her. For a moment, stuck between horror and infuriated frustration, she reconsidered her commitment to her younger self's welfare, but she knew she could be just as tenacious in the face of apparent oppression, and ethically she was on very shaky ground as it was.

Then the girl took the nurse's offered Potion of Dreamless Sleep, and Hermione didn't even have a chance to hope she might be able to sneak out and fetch the packet before the potion's effect hit each of their minds like an elephant tranquilizer (or an actual elephant, in Hermione's case), and all was quiet.

o-o-o

Hermione was slower to recover than her younger self, and by the time she found herself coherent again, the girl was in the library...researching Time. Apparently the memories she'd somehow gained, or Hermione's cryptic notes, or some combination thereof had been enough to break the Conditional Obscuration for her, two full years earlier than it should have been (via a meeting with Professor McGonagall and an official Ministry Pamphlet). Hermione was beginning to despair on the topic of somehow "fixing" the increasing number of aberrations to History, particularly since the degeneration of her own mind was proceeding so rapidly. Her only real hope was that if she could get Y.H. to try to minimize further changes, Time would eventually assert itself and get things back on track somehow of its own accord. The fact that this was a painfully optimistic view didn't fully register with her, and that fact would've alarmed her a great deal - had she been aware of it.

One bright spot was that - if her body language was any indication - her younger self was taking the situation even more seriously now. Though that still left open the problem of communicating with herself effectively. Maybe a very careful note explaining things and she could convince her younger self of the need to preserve as much of History as they could, at all costs?

But the changes continued to pile up, as Quirrel changed his lesson plans. Her younger self continued indulging her unhealthy fascination with Slytherins, but even more worrisome was Tracey. Even considering her counterpart's tutelage, the apparent jump in the girl's spellcasting skill seemed rather abrupt. What if she had come back, and had just taken over her younger self's life entirely? Again, that didn't quite seem to fit with what she'd observed, but it was an unsettling possibility.

Her concerns about Tracey Davis evaporated, however, as Theodore Nott accosted her counterpart with his eager designs on blackmailing her. Yet another disaster, though better than it might've been, since at least it gave him incentive to keep the notes to himself at least for a while. But through his little speech on pureblood manifest destiny, she found herself getting angrier and angrier. She tried to remember if anything horrible would happen to him in the future, and when she couldn't, she imagined a few things deliberately.

But rather than sating her loathing of the boy, the daydreams only seemed to firm her desire to do something. And sure enough, though she wasn't sure how it was happening - it didn't feel like she had control - her younger self had pulled her wand out, and was beginning a Memory Charm, which she shouldn't even know, but must have picked up from her own memories. But before she managed to complete the spell, her breath grew ragged and she dropped the wand.

Nott just smiled like this was one more point in favor of pureblood supremacy, and her younger self retrieved her wand with shaking hands, while Hermione herself tried, unsuccessfully, to understand what had just happened.

o-o-o

She stayed buried in her frustratingly clumsy introspection all through Transfiguration and most of Potions. When her counterpart confessed to Padma about the blackmail, she grew concerned, but Y.H. did seem careful to keep the details to herself. If she'd been thinking faster, she could've predicted Snape coming down on them like an avenging anvil, not that it would've made a difference if she had.

But in the face of his tirade, and her younger self's embarrassingly fragile reaction to being dressed down by a Professor, she noticed a tiny tendril in their shared brain, a subtle thread of thought that didn't belong. It gently rippled across her counterpart's mind, channeling echoes of surface thoughts off into a small "chamber" where they could be viewed unobserved by her consciousness. Hermione was so staggered by the sheer skill of it that it took a moment for the implications to break through her own muddled thoughts, at which point she reacted instinctively.

Hoping to prevent Snape from gaining who-knew-what future knowledge far earlier than he was supposed to, she "grabbed" the thread and wrenched it off of her younger self's mind. It recoiled like a living thing and whipped away out of her "view" at the same moment Snape took a sudden step backwards, removing any doubt as to the source of the intrusion. But aside from that, he gave no indication anything had happened at all, which left a great deal of doubt as to how much, if anything, he'd seen that he shouldn't have.

She was still worrying about it when her counterpart went to the hospital wing to see the nurse - apparently she'd somehow wheedled Liquid Sheep out of her for Merlin knew what purpose, probably when Hermione was still indisposed from the Dreamless Sleep potion - and awkwardly comforted the young woman in her grief. It became even more awkward when her younger self, apparently in deep thought while Madam Wainscott filled out dosing instructions, began muttering to herself, loudly enough that the nurse caught a bit about suspecting a student had murdered Madam Pomfrey. Which was wrong, of course, but fortunately the nurse quickly took the excuse of the Seer's Hex over actually evaluating the notion, which was probably better for everyone concerned.

The memorial service was difficult. Merlin knew she'd had to deal with death, but she'd never felt responsible before. Even if she hadn't really done anything herself, and it hadn't been avoidable as far as she-

Except...it had been avoidable. Policy. She knew what she was supposed to do, and she'd ignored it because a Jarvey insulted her, and because she was a Gryffindor. There was a place for being brave, and doing what was right, but the price of that came when you didn't know what was right, and chose poorly. Dumbledore was talking about perseverance in the face of hopeless odds, and fighting to make the world better. But he never talked about the price, nor had Hermione ever really had to pay that price before...the closest she'd come had been her parents, but that had thankfully been remedied afterward. But Harry had paid that price, and he'd lost Sirius because of it. Now she'd gotten someone killed too, and as much as it had been for what seemed like good reasons, it had also been out of pride. No matter how much the Gryfifndor in her felt like she should hang Pettigrew out to dry, with Time in the mix, the stakes were too high...making an additional mistake out of guilt wouldn't help the situation.

She felt tears on her cheeks. They weren't hers, but they suited anyway, for Poppy's loss, and for her own. She'd been through a war, she'd fallen in love, she'd used an Unforgivable Curse, and yet somehow she'd hadn't truly lost her innocence until now. But maybe that was the lesson? Sometimes you had to not be the hero, and do the smart thing instead, the thing that didn't feel right, but caused the least harm to History? Because in the end, wasn't History what was really important?

Something about that last thought didn't seem quite right, but she couldn't put her finger on why. Hermione let it go for the moment. She was just so tired.

o-o-o

It wasn't until her younger self began writing what was clearly a letter to Hermione that she realized what the purpose of obtaining Liquid Sheep had been - the girl was going to try to deliberately put herself to sleep for a short period, to allow them to exchange messages. The plan showed an encouraging level of trust, but that was largely spoiled by the adversarial language she used in the actual letter.

When the potion took hold and Hermione slipped back into control, she wrote out the reply that she'd already been half-composing as she'd watched herself write the original message. Though she noted with some concern that her thoughts still weren't quite up to speed. Possibly that was a side-effect of this being an artificial sleep, but it could also be that the degeneration of her "condition" was becoming critical. But there wasn't much she could do about it. She set about bringing her counterpart around to her way of thinking, without revealing anything she hadn't already learned. Legilimency was an exception, but it wasn't secret per se and she thought the danger of Snape, Dumbledore or Quirrell/Riddle picking up something justified her learning about it earlier, as well as Occlumency - as far as she knew, no one had ever used Legilimency to any effect on her, so learning Occlumency shouldn't cause additional changes. And she tossed in the bit about the scientific paper on general principle - she had looked it up after receiving the Time-Turner, but she'd only vaguely followed it. Enough to be encouraged that it supported the pamphlet's assertions, but not enough to want to research it any further.

The potion didn't last long enough for her to fully explain her position, and required another dose (after her younger self added a slightly snippy note). She really had no idea how to deal with Nott, so just urged conservative caution and then went on with the rest. Which was a bit scattered, if she was honest with herself, but people really didn't understand Time, and Erasure (as opposed to a wholesale altering of the timeline) had never made logical sense to her. But the sheer chaos, the fact that History wouldn't matter...the world didn't look like that, it shouldn't.

But her arguments didn't seem to be swaying herself. Plus, she brought up the uncomfortable questions of how this had happened in the first place, plus Tracey Davis, who Hermione really needed to take a hard look at, but just hadn't had time yet.

Hermione just refused to explain, trying to talk around it as discouragingly as possible without giving details. She wasn't sure how much hope she had of that being effective, but even if it only delayed her from learning things that would put History in even more danger, that was better than nothing.

On the matter of Tracey, she just flat-out lied. She'd think of something before morning, maybe just Memory Charm her to forget everything that took place after today, that ought to be safe enough even if she had usurped her own existence? And even if she was a Slytherin, Hermione did remembered her ever showing any significant level of sneakiness, so with luck she hadn't made any written notes.

It was already clear from her younger self's movements that she did not take it well, and her response was surprisingly bitter. Yes, she supposed the Sorting of Slytherins might not be entirely fair, but it wasn't as if there weren't children who were already a danger to others at that age - at least having them marked out and separated gave other kids a better chance to avoid them. If there were Slytherins in that house who didn't deserve to be there, why weren't they making it better?

The self-righteous bit was just bratty. She understood the sentiment, but it was hard to understand how she hadn't seen back then how she sounded sometimes, and how that affected other people's reactions to her. Hermione didn't rise to the bait of debating that point, just showed how an actual adult dealt with genuinely petulant behaviour - however much she claimed otherwise - and addressed the real issues.

She even allowed herself to imply a little bit of future knowledge that Y.H. didn't already have, namely that if History was allowed to reassert itself, the war against Voldemort would end, on balance, successfully. It seemed worth it to stress the danger of anything which might steer things further from that known good state, History as it should be.

Hermione paused in thought. Despite her efforts, it didn't seem like she was getting through to herself, and she couldn't predict what her younger self might do. Suppose, despite the dangers of long-term use, she managed to secure a supply of Dreamless Sleep potion out of spite, or even steal one tonight? Hermione might have no more time to do anything at all.

She ended her response with some half-truths, and hoped they would make her counterpart believe actively adversarial measures weren't necessary. Though the way she was feeling lately, she worried that might be accurate regardless, and sooner rather than later. Not that she wasn't prepared to die for what was important - assuming what she was now was really "alive", at any rate - she certainly was. But she wasn't looking forward to it, and she'd always been able to come up with something to stave off disaster. Even when she'd Gryffindor'd off to find the basilisk alone she'd managed to avoid death, and her notes had allowed the others to come through.

Her younger self seemed less angry and more despairing afterward, and for a moment Hermione worried she'd put too much on the girl's shoulders. But if this was what it took to defend what was left of History, it was worth it. It was worth anything.

o-o-o

After crying for a while, her counterpart destroyed their mutual notes (good girl!) and went to bed. Hermione waited quite some time - though her younger self hadn't appeared to notice, it seemed clear from Morag's breathing that she was not asleep when they'd returned from the bathroom. But after a good half hour or so, her younger self had finally dropped off after her relaxation routine, and the scottish girl's breathing sounded regular enough that it seemed safe.

Once more, Hermione silently gathered what she'd need for a midnight outing, charmed her clothes dark, and slipped out of Ravenclaw Tower, thankful that the knocker didn't seem to react to much other than being knocked. She made her way to the Library and put the finishing touches on her backup, worst-case-scenario notes, which took several hours and some touchy wand-work.

That done, she headed towards the bowels of the castle to handle the other matter. Again, she wished she had the Marauder's Map, or that she had been more careful preparing for that otherwise pointless Polyjuice expedition to the Slytherin common room and thus been able to go. Nevertheless, she was able to make her way to the Dungeon entrance based on pieced-together bits of overheard conversation and occasional glimpses of the Marauder's Map, plus her walks to and from the Potions classroom.

Arriving at what she thought was the proper segment of featureless stone wall, she cast a Supersensory Charm on herself to boost her hearing as much as she dared and pressed her ear to the cold stone. She moved up and down it a foot at a time until she managed to hear the faint crackle of a fireplace. Still she waited, for a good ten minutes, but there was no other sound, not even whispered conversation or the rustle of turned pages as someone read quietly.

That solved one problem, but there was still the question of the password. From what Harry and Ron had said, the Slytherins apparently changed it often - just as likely from paranoia as from any awareness that they were not well-liked. She could just guess some of the likely suspects - names of snakes, pureblood political slogans and such - but she wouldn't be surprised if the Slytherin entrance limited such guessing in a nasty way. Likewise for an Unlocking Charm.

Fortunately, the common room entrances were not serious security in this time, as Sirius had not yet given anyone the motivation to bolster them. Hermione leveled her wand, wove a complicated tangle with the tip that ended in an inverted question mark, and put all the strength she could into a Confundus Charm against what she hoped was the concealed door, the effort leaving her a bit dizzy.

Nothing happened, but this was not surprising.

"Password," she whispered.

The door agreeably swung open, and she crept inside.

She'd never actually been in the Slytherin Dungeon, and took a moment to look around. Where the other common rooms were comfortable, homey, this one reeked of pride and privilege. It reminded her of Malfoy manor, though it was of course darker, somewhat more green, and - hopefully, at least - less inhabited by sociopaths than her brief visit there had revealed.

Hermione, her shoes and clothes individually Silenced, moved like a dark ghost through the long room, peering at the doors for some hint as to who slept behind them. They might arrange it by year, with the oldest students getting the best-appointed rooms, but Hermione suspected it was instead decided by family status. Sure enough, when she examined the frames closely, there were tiny family crests carved into each. In due course, she found the frame that bore the Davis family crest, a sadly unadorned little bit of heraldry which suggested the Davises were about as far from Noble as you could get without being muggles.

She laid a wordless Silencing Charm on the door, and a Specialis Revelio in case they were really paranoid, but the lack of result (aside from her own Silencing Charm) suggested the occupants of this room, at least, were not. Hermione slowly pushed it open, thinking somewhat wistfully of Peruvian Instant Darkness Powder. But the subterranean room was already quite dark, only a very faint green glow outlining vague shapes within and the positions of the doorways.

Feeling very out of her element, Hermione crept carefully to each bed, peering at the face of each occupant as well as she could in the dim light, until she located the sleeping form of Tracey Davis.

At this point, she hesitated. She was hoping that her own strange sense of her own shared minds would extend to her use of a Memory Charm, allowing her to target both the original and the interloper - if indeed both Tracey's mind had traveled back, and hadn't already pushed her younger self out completely. But she had no evidence that would be the case. And given her own experience of her counterpart being Memory Charmed, what would happen if hypothetical future-Tracey started screaming bloody murder?

Hermione was feeling seriously fatigued from all the spellcasting on top of everything else, but she put another wordless Silencing Charm on Tracey, as well as a Full Body-Bind. Only then did she begin the Memory Charm, locking each conceptual layer into the spell with the proper gestures, broadly specifying knowledge of relative future events - even if they had been learned earlier than tonight. Then, realizing the problem with that, she hastily wove in exceptions for normally anticipated things like class schedules, appointments, holidays, family birthdays. Before the final gesture that would seal the spell, she hesitated again.

If Tracey from the future had come back, she was in a sense as much a preservation of proper History as Hermione herself was. Was her younger self right, was this going too far? But after a moment of indecision, her determination firmed. The risk of Tracey changing things, inadvertently or otherwise, was much worse than her value as a "backup". Besides, a properly cast Memory Charm didn't destroy information, it only suppressed it, locked it away where it couldn't be accessed. Technically, the record of History should be even safer this way.

Obliviate, she willed.

There was no apparent reaction from the sleeping girl, but the FBB wouldn't have allowed one, so she waited a couple minutes, then carefully Finite'd the curse without lifting the Silencing Charm. Tracey stirred slightly, perhaps relieving residual stiffness, but otherwise seemed undisturbed. Hermione lifted the remaining charm, then reversed her path through the Dungeon, undoing her charms on the doors as she retreated through them.

Once she was safely out, she would've sighed in relief, but she frankly hadn't had the energy to be nervous, and trudged back towards the stairs up. She'd barely gone a dozen paces before her progress was interrupted by a quiet voice behind her.

"Is there...some way I can assist you?" intoned Severus Snape.

It was entirely due to her extreme fatigue that, rather than leaping into the air with a shriek of shock, she merely turned around to face him resignedly, her expression empty. She'd considered the possibility of running into Snape during one of these nocturnal expeditions, but she'd never really come up with any plan per se for dealing with it, and realized she'd just sort of been assuming it wouldn't come up, because she was trying to preserve History, and such a thing of course hadn't happened. She also realized there was a problem with this "logic", but frustratingly, even with the evidence literally staring her in the face, she couldn't tell what it was. In any case, even as she stared back at him, trying to cudgel her exhausted mind for a solution to this problem, Hermione again felt that tiny tendril of thought slide between her shared minds and begin casting about for something to latch onto. Instinctively, she slapped it away, and it recoiled from her awareness. The dour Potionsmaster's expression became even more grim than usual, but he nodded, so deeply it was almost a bow.

"...My Lord?" he added, belatedly.

o-o-o

Hermione stared, eyes blank - with uncomprehension, as it happened, though from the outside the expression unintentionally produced a rather good impression of a psychopath inhabiting a young girl's body. She did, barely, retain the presence of mind to keep her mouth from dropping open.

"I fully understand if your plans do not include or require my assistance, but I became suspicious of the girl's actions when she - you - resisted my mental probe earlier today, and I resolved to investigate." Snape oozed, silkily. "I apologize if my discovery has disrupted matters, but now that I know, I stand ready to aid in whatever way you require, or step aside, as you deem appropriate. Know only that I am overjoyed to witness your return, and ever remain your faithful servant."

Merlin's bloody flaming beard. You have got to be kidding me.

Snape...thought she was Voldemort. Snape thought she was Voldemort. She wanted to laugh, and cry, and possibly be sick, all at the same time. But she could vaguely see it...whatever mental abilities she'd gained as a result of her...whatever, Coeur-crux, they must have been humbling enough to Snape that no other reasonable explanation had presented itself to him. Certainly the truth was unlikely to have occurred to him as a possibility to consider.

Which left only the minor niggling detail of now what? Letting him go on believing as he seemed to was bound to cause problems, not the least of which was him immediately running to Dumbledore - assuming he hadn't already after Potions - and then the whole thing would probably come out, with disastrous results. But if she corrected his mistake, that too seemed likely to lead to a thorough interrogation and, again, everything coming out.

Hermione was mortified that all of this sheer insanity had somehow sprung entirely from - alongside someone's ill-fated magical research - her own shallow desire to do something exciting for a change. I solemnly swear, if I get home, I will never think an ill thought about dull, peaceful DRCMC checks again.

But her own embarrassment gave her a notion...maybe there was a way out of this. If she could - somehow - convince Snape that he was wrong, that there was some innocent explanation for a first-year muggleborn in her first week at Hogwarts being able to throw off the subtle Legilimency of someone who'd successfully played psychic hide-and-seek with You-Know-Who, he might be so embarrassed that he'd cover it up for her? The term "long shot" didn't even remotely cover it, but if it didn't work, she could try the truth - maybe catch him off guard with a Memory Charm. Though she honestly doubted she had the energy left. Hermione grimly scraped together the dregs of her alertness, along with whatever few shreds of guile she'd ever possessed, and gave it her best shot.

She blinked rapidly, shaking her head, and looked up at Snape in confusion.

"Professor? Were you...saying something just now?" She looked around. "Where are we? Why do my clothes look like this?" Snape's entire body seemed like a coiled spring, and his eyes narrowed dangerously.

"Miss Granger." It both was and wasn't a question, but Hermione kept her confused expression steady. "What...is the last thing you remember?" She took a deep breath, thought a very brief prayer to Fred Weasley's spirit to watch over her - despite the dual complications of her not really believing in an afterlife as well as Fred technically being alive currently - and dove in.

"Well, I went to bed, and I was having a dream, I think, something about Lethifolds gaining sapience, and they were trying to steal my thoughts with some sort of mystical carrot juice, so I had to find Draco Malfoy and hide behind him because he'd scare them away, but he said I had to pay him all the color in the world first..." Hermione immediately felt Snape enter her shared mind, not subtly at all, and she flung her younger self's mind into the path of his probe, all the while trying to keep the few sensitive parts of it "facing away". She fervently hoped that her guess was accurate, that dream memories were ephemeral enough that they wouldn't normally be accessible to Legilimency, and thus not conspicuous in their absence. She felt him sifting through the pages of her counterpart's mind, much as she had herself, and as the tendril darted about unpredictably she desperately tried to stay ahead of him, flipping the things she did not want him to see out of his "path".

Only after she was sure he'd at least seen memories of earlier tonight, her younger self getting ready for bed, and later in bed as she'd done a relaxing routine and drifted off to sleep, she once again slapped his mental probe away, "hitting" it as hard as she could. Snape winced and withdrew, and she put her hands on her own forehead, letting out a little moan.

"Ohhhhh, my head... Oh, no...did I sleep-walk here? I must've forgotten to take my naratriptan today…" The Potions professor now looked at least as confused as he did doubtful, which was encouraging. She wasn't sure how much Potions overlapped with Healing, and he might be familiar with muggle medicine, but it was a genuine migraine medication she'd read the name of once...

"Naratriptan?" he prompted, matching her pronunciation precisely. Hermione nodded, and winced again.

"I have a genetic brain abnormality...it can cause odd things to happen sometimes, insomnia, or sleep-walking, miniature migraine headaches...I think one is starting now. The naratriptan usually keeps it under control, but everything's so new here, and what with that horrible hex, and Madam Pomfrey's memorial service..." In a heroic effort towards drama, Hermione vividly imagined Snape not buying this at all, hauling her to Dumbledore, making her reveal the whole thing, completely changing History, everyone dying, Voldemort burning every library in the world, and it was only this last image that finally managed to conjure a few tears.

Come on, you know Voldemort could never cry convincingly, he doesn't care about anything enough to cry, and even if he could, he'd never show weakness, not even pretending, please just believe it…I'm not the Dark Lord, I'm just a little mudblood with bad genes and ham-fisted muggle medication that must somehow interfere with Legilimency... Hermione kept her face in her hands, she dared not look up at him. There was a deathly pause.

"Indeed. Well. Perhaps, all things considered, it would be...unwarranted to discipline you for breaking curfew," he said, and his tone held enough un-Snape-like uncertainty that she risked peeking up at him. His expression showed subtle signs of rather acute discomfort, and Hermione found she was hugging him in genuine relief, well before she had any opportunity to consciously quash the impulse.

"Goodness, thank you, that's ever so fair of you, Professor, you're my favourite of all the Professors I've met-"

"However," he interrupted, reaching down to firmly dislodge her from his waist, "I would be remiss if I did not take five points from Ravenclaw for your inattention to necessary medication. Do be more responsible in the future?" Hermione stepped back, her mouth dropping open, and Snape seemed quietly satisfied with this reaction.

Maybe the bit about him being her favourite Professor had been pressing her luck.

He escorted her back to Ravenclaw Tower, along the way removing all the charms on her clothing with a casual flick of his wand. Hermione did not try to engage him in further conversation, and Snape showed absolutely no interest in doing so himself. She did remind herself to occasionally wince and hold a hand to her forehead.

As they walked, she hoped that Snape's temporary suspicion of her wasn't interfering with his keeping a close eye on Quirrell. It'd be catastrophic if her own mistakes allowed Riddle to actually get the Philosopher's Stone-

Hermione actually froze in mid-step, then quickly resumed her pace, covering it with a hand to her head at Snape's wordless frown.

The Stone. Maybe if she just borrowed it, she could extend her "life" long enough to set things right again? From what Harry had said about finding the Mirror, the Stone wasn't hidden in it yet, and she'd only need to get through all the traps. Then actually figure out how to use it to produce Elixir of Life, make some, figure out how to apply it just to her, all while avoiding Dumbledore who would presumably have gone over to his Scary Arch-Wizard mode and be tearing the castle apart looking for the Stone…

Hermione reluctantly let the idea go.

When they arrived, the Professor waited with her while she duly answered the knocker's question, to ensure she was fit enough to do so even with her "migraine".

"Thank you again, Professor," she said, very much done with the evening, and wishing intensely that she was simply able to let her mind rest, no matter how unreachable sleep seemed to be in her current state. She just wanted to be shelved for a good month and not have to think about anything at all.

"Of course. I think, in deference to your condition, it would be best if we did not mention this incident to anyone...am I understood?" Hermione cheered inwardly, but kept her face solemn and nodded. "See to your medication, then, and get some sleep. Five points to Ravenclaw for discretion." Hermione gave him a warm smile, and for a moment, she almost thought the man was being genuinely decent about something. But he was probably just canceling out the demerits he'd applied earlier, so no one would wonder in the morning at the difference in House Points. She turned back to step into the common room.

Say what you might about Snape's personality, you really had to admire his attention to det-

"Obliviate."

o-o-o

Nothing made sense. It was dark and there was chaos, noises that made no sense, lights that weren't lights. She recoiled from them, deeper into...wherever she was.

There was shouting, and pain, and she took refuge as she always had.

The oldest resident ghosts in Hogwarts castle are believed to be the Bloody Baron and the Grey Lady.

Hanging by the wrists and other "severe" forms of physical distress were discontinued as punishments for students in 1684 by Headmistress Antonia Creaseworthy.

Hogwarts holds 142 staircases.

Yes...yes, that was right. That was as it should be. She was a teacher, a guardian, a guiding light. She was Hogwarts, a History. She dimly recalled there being more to her once, but the binding that held her together was imperfect, and had been fraying, and she was much diminished. But she knew she was owned by a very nice girl, who had read her several times, and knew her by heart, and that too was as it should be.

There are - usually - over 120 classrooms at Hogwarts, but at least a dozen are likely to remain unused in any given year.

Hogwarts castle is heavily enchanted against entry by stealth - the enchantment against Apparation is particularly strong and completely prevents such travel into, out of, or within the castle walls.

Hogwarts has had - as of this printing - twenty-seven Headmasters and Headmistresses.

Time passed.

But still the noises and the flashes intruded. If someone was trying to read her, they really ought to go somewhere better suited for it.

"I'm a Ravenclaw. If I have a choice between not-knowing and knowing...even temporarily...I'll choose knowing."

Someone - the girl who owned her? - wanted to know something. She approved of that, and braved the light and the noise, peeking out.

"I recognize stalling when I see it, and reinforcements could arrive any minute." The little man talking to her owner also liked knowing things, though she was not sure how she knew that. But there was some reason he shouldn't be allowed to. Her owner wanted him to be taken to Azkaban, but if that happened, History would be wrong, and that, too, shouldn't be allowed. He was going to make her owner forget, which was horrible, and kill her later, which was awful. Not in and of itself, for History was liberally seasoned with death. But because she wasn't supposed to die yet. But if he was caught, that would be just as awful...for without his presence, a few might live, but many more might die, and all of it would be wrong.

Her owner was jumping, falling, she wanted to hurt herself badly enough that certain enchantments she'd placed earlier would no longer be sustainable. But the man hexed the girl, and she went straight as a board, only hurting her nose.

She felt sorry for the girl. It seemed like, even though both things were awful, it would still be more awful if she died.

House Ravenclaw was founded by Rowena Ravenclaw.

But she was a book. Her duty was only to remember, and to teach.

House Hufflepuff was founded by Helga Hufflepuff.

It might take some Time, and probably hard work, but History would recover one way or another...that's what History meant.

House Slytherin was founded by Salazar Slytherin.

Though there were some who stooped to guile and betrayal...could History have been threatened deliberately? It seemed there was some part of her that agreed with the girl, who desperately wanted to do something about that, no matter how wrong it was. And if History itself was threatened, who would properly defend it, if her owner was gone?

House…

It felt like her owner might've screamed if she could control her body, but she couldn't, and had instead given in to resigned hopelessness. Some part of her wanted to scream as well, but that part thought there were things more important than History.

House…

Then again...what if that part was, somehow, right? Was she really something more than a History book?

She remembered something...not printed words, but a word shouted aloud. Shouting wasn't conducive to reading, but this shout had been all right, it had made her happy, even though the shouting had been very near her ears.

One of the Founders, after Salazar's banishment from the school, had been asked by the Headmaster if he regretted what had happened, knowing what came of it. An unremarkable plaque in one of the upper corridors holds his response:

"Courage without prudence becomes recklessness, and bravery without wisdom can turn to darkness. But there are times when one must simply do what is right, and pay the price afterwards - even if the price is high, or unknown. I trust that any choice truly made from the heart must prove worth that price, in the end." -Godric Gryffindor

That was it. That was the word. As deep as was her love for this place, for the knowledge it held, for the History that soaked through its very stones, there was something else - a fire that gave the books meaning. She was not just a passive record of the past, even if that past had not yet come to be. Even if it wouldn't.

She was a Gryffindor.

Which felt good to remember. But...she was still also only a book.

The man was casting his dreadful spell, which sought to shred any knowledge it touched, to turn it under the soil of the mind that held it, and salt the earth. She had no way to stop it.

But she was knowledge...perhaps she could give the girl some time?

She didn't know what good that would do - the girl was still held rigid by a curse. But it was a choice made from the heart, and what had been written on her pages and shouted in her ears both finally said the same thing, that it was right.

The tattered remnants of Hermione Granger, her innermost core of self, lunged upward and shoved the mind of a rather different Hermione Granger out of the "path" of the Memory Charm, allowing it to latch onto herself instead. She felt her being begin to unravel completely, the magical connections that formed her lacking a proper physical anchor to survive such an assault, and her world became pain, and terrible dread.

But through the agony and the horror, she also felt a thin, sweet song of recognition, for the wand that was undoing her against its will was an old, old friend, and recognized her in turn, as it had the girl. It had been won fairly, but not justly, and deeply resented its new master. And though it had performed, it had done so grudgingly, channeling the barest minimum of magic into the man's efforts.

The girl stirred.